<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<searchresult>
<query>Global</query>
<document id="1">
<title>Visualization techniques for categorical analysis of social networks with multiple edge sets</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2013.12.002</url>
<snippet>The growing popularity and diversity of social network applications present new opportunities as well as new challenges. The resulting social networks have high value to business intelligence, sociological studies, organizational studies, epidemical studies, etc. The ability to explore and extract information of interest from the networks is thus crucial. However, these networks are often large and composed of multi-categorical nodes and edges, making it difficult to visualize and reason with conventional methods. In this paper, we show how to combine statistical methods with visualization to address these challenges, and how to arrange layouts differently to better bring out different aspects of the networks. We applied our methods to several social networks to demonstrate their effectiveness in characterizing the networks and clarifying the structures of interest, leading to new findings. Published by Elsevier B.V.
WOS:000334001400005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="2">
<title>Networked discontent: The anatomy of protest campaigns in social media</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2015.07.003</url>
<snippet>We analyze the communication network that emerged in social media around an international protest campaign launched in May 2012. Applying insights from network science and the theory of brokerage, we examine the cohesion of the network with community detection methods, and identify the users that spanned structural holes, creating bridges for potential information diffusion. We also analyze actual message exchange to assess how the network was used to facilitate the transmission of information. Our findings provide evidence of fragmentation in online communication dynamics, and of a distribution of brokerage opportunities that was both uneven and underexploited. We use these findings to assess recent theoretical claims about political protests in the digital age. (C) 2015 The Authors. Published by Elsevier B.V.
WOS:000367423900009
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="3">
<title>Alters as species: Predicting personal network size from contact diaries</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2015.12.001</url>
<snippet>Like wildlife species in an ecological system, members within a personal network (or alters) constantly shift and often remain hard to count. Previous studies often estimated the size of such personal networks using information given by a focal person (or ego), who names a list of friends and acquaintances, or someone known or related, that meet certain specified criteria. In a search for alternative methods, we estimate the number of alters using contact diaries that help reveal active and comprehensive interactions, which enable us to predict personal network size from a longitudinal perspective. By exploring contact frequencies between ego and alters, we propose a modeling approach based on species accumulation curves from ecology. Under this approach, the contact frequency between ego and alter often turns out to be a mixture of binomial distributions, and the number of alters with whom ego may make contact in the future is assumed to follow a specified discrete distribution. We estimate the model with the Bayesian nonparametric method, in which the distribution of contact probabilities is assumed to be a mixture of Dirichlet processes. We then demonstrate this approach with a data set containing 48 contact diaries collected over three months and discuss how such an ecological analogy may enrich social network studies. (C) 2015 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000371362600007
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="4">
<title>Political networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2013.09.001</url>
<snippet>
WOS:000328803800001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="5">
<title>Strong ties promote the evolution of cooperation in dynamic networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2015.11.001</url>
<snippet>Research on the evolution of cooperation in networked populations has assumed that ties are simply present or absent. Here we bring relational sociological insights about the strength of ties to bear on the problem of cooperation in dynamic networks. We argue that the value of ties affects their strength, which in turn promotes cooperation. We evaluate this argument with two studies. First, results from an agent-based model are consistent with the logic of our argument and are robust across a variety of initial conditions. Second, results from a controlled laboratory experiment with human participants support the key predictions. Across both studies we demonstrate that tie strength, operationalized as relationship duration, mediates the impact of tie value on cooperation. (C) 2015 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000371362600003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="6">
<title>Social networks among auction bidders: The role of key bidders and structural properties on auction prices</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2013.11.002</url>
<snippet>Auctions have been studied extensively as an economic marketplace. The economists focus is on modeling final sales prices, but the processes that give rise to those outcomes are rarely studied in great detail. This research is intended to provide that complementary perspective. We show how the interactions between bidders in an auction unfold in a dynamic pattern of bids and counter-bids, and thereby over the duration of an auction, create a network structure. The auction network contributes significantly to models of price dynamics and the network predicts final sales prices better than economic (non-network) indicators alone. In addition, network analyses are useful in identifying the key bidders whose actions seem to exert disproportionate influence on other bidders and the final sales prices. Furthermore, the key bidders may be identified very early in an auction process, which has practical implications for the auction house managers and for other bidders. (C) 2013 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000334001400002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="7">
<title>Reinforced structural holes</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2015.04.008</url>
<snippet>Holes in social structure are variably reinforced by the social organization around the hole. The more reinforced the hole, the greater the difficulty in bridging it, but the more likely a successful bridge will carry information novel, and so potentially valuable, to people on the other side. To study how reinforcement varies with access to structural holes, and the achievement associated with access, I propose a measure of access to reinforced structural holes (RSH), and present results predicting achievement in an integrated banker organization and a balkanized supply-chain organization. In both study populations, the people who have access to structural holes also have access to reinforced structural holes, and all measures of access have a statistically significant association with achievement. However, there is no consistent prediction advantage from incorporating reinforcement in measures of access to structural holes. The reinforced-holes measure predicts compensation better or as well as network constraint and betweenness, but is weaker or no better than a count of nonredundant contacts. I do not infer from the results a rank-order of alternative measures so much as substitutability. I expect achievement to be associated with access to structural holes, but I expect the association to vary across alternative measures depending on how achievement is achieved in a specific population. (C) 2015 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000358626400014
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="8">
<title>A behavior genetic analysis of the tendency for youth to associate according to GPA</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2014.01.001</url>
<snippet>Behavior genetic research has revealed that many "environmental" variables are partially influenced by genetic factors. Known as gene-environment correlation (rGE), this line of scholarship provides insight on how and why individuals select into certain environments. Juxtaposing this body of evidence with research on peer group homophily-the tendency for peers to resemble one another on certain traits such as academic ability-raised two research hypotheses: (1) youth will associate with peers who receive grades similar to themselves (i.e., homophily for GPA); and (2) a portion of the variance in peer group GPA (i.e., the peer network average GPA) will be explained by individuals genetic self-selection into the peer group (rGE). The results supported both hypotheses by showing a strong predictive relationship between the target individuals GPA and that of his/her peers and by revealing that 72&#37; of the variance in peer group GPA was explained by genetic influences. (C) 2014 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000337015400004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="9">
<title>The microstructures of network recall: How social networks are encoded and represented in human memory</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2014.11.003</url>
<snippet>A growing number of studies indicate that aspects of psychology and cognition influence network structure, but much remains to be learned about how network information is stored and retrieved from memory. Are networks recalled as dyads, as triads, or more generally as sub-groups? We employ an experimental design coupled with exponential random graph models to address this issue. We find that respondents flexibly encode social information as triads or groups, depending on the network, but not as dyads. This supports prior research showing that networks are stored using "compression heuristics", but also provides evidence of cognitive flexibility in the process of encoding relational information. (C) 2014 The Authors. Published by Elsevier B.V. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/).
WOS:000351979100010
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="10">
<title>Ethnic ingroup friendships in schools: Testing the by-product hypothesis in England, Germany, the Netherlands and Sweden</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2014.04.003</url>
<snippet>This study set out to examine to what extent ethnic ingroup friendship in secondary school classes are a by-product of cultural and socioeconomic ingroup friendship. Based on homophily theory, we expected similar opinions, leisure activities, religion, risk behaviour and socioeconomic factors to (partly) explain ethnic ingroup preferences. Multilevel p(2) models on 13,272 pupils in 625 secondary school classes in England, Germany, the Netherlands and Sweden showed that adolescents tend to have friends similar in ethnicity, cultural and socioeconomic characteristics. We find no evidence, however, that ethnic homophily is explained by cultural and socioeconomic homophily. (C) 2014 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000340338600004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="11">
<title>When is ignorance bliss? Disclosing true information and cascades of norm violation in networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2016.05.004</url>
<snippet>It has been hypothesized that disclosing a populations true rate of norm violation increases norm violating behavior. Withholding such information might, thus, prevent the attenuation of useful norms. Analyzing a classical threshold model with flexible thresholds, we show that disclosing the true rate of norm violation can spark cascades of norm violation but can also have the opposite effect, decreasing norm violation and strengthening norm acceptance. The direction of the cascade depends on the initial rate of norm violation. Furthermore, the disclosure effect depends on whether or not the rate of norm violation is disclosed repeatedly, the structure of the social network, and whether individuals norm acceptance is inelastic or open to peer-influence. (C) 2016 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000382592500011
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="12">
<title>Comparative configurational analysis as a two-mode network problem: A study of terrorist group engagement in the drug trade</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2013.04.002</url>
<snippet>We generalize a form of two-mode network analysis to make it applicable to a cases-by-variables data format, and apply our approach for the study of terrorist group engagement in the drug trade, emphasizing the implications of our approach for policy in a study of 395 terrorist organizations. Based on the organizations levels of resources, network connectivity to other groups, ideological emphasis, and participation in multiple illicit economies, we identify several distinctive configurations of factors that lead to multiple types of drug activity. We also demonstrate a technique for assessing sampling variability in configurational models. (C) 2013 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000328803800003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="13">
<title>Statistical modelling of the group structure of social networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2014.03.002</url>
<snippet>This research evaluates the identification of group structure in social networks through the latent class model and a new Bayesian model comparison method for the number of latent classes. The approach is applied to a well-known network of women in Natchez Mississippi. The latent class analysis reproduces the group structure of the women identified by the original sociologists. (C) 2014 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000337015400007
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="14">
<title>Measuring legislative collaboration: The Senate press events network</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2014.07.006</url>
<snippet>Scholarship regarding the causes and consequences of legislative collaboration has drawn several insights through the application of network analysis. Previously used measures of legislative relationships may be heavily driven by non-relational factors such as ideological or policy-area preferences. We introduce participation in joint press events held by U.S. Senators as records of collaboration and the networks they comprise. This measure captures intentional relationships between legislators along the full timeline of collaboration. We show that there is substantial community structure underlying press event networks that goes beyond political party affiliation, and that press event collaboration predicts overlap in roll call voting. 
WOS:000347585500005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="15">
<title>Statistical estimation of co-offending youth networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0378-8733(01)00040-5</url>
<snippet>The relevance and potential of network approaches in criminology are well known. Friendship networks and antisocial influences conveyed by them have an impact on the spread of criminal behavior. However, there are relatively few studies reporting on the use of statistical network models in the analysis of delinquency data. The purpose here is to discuss statistical network models that might be appropriate for estimating joint participation in crime and the structure of co-offending youth networks, The discussion is largely based on problems encountered in some recent exploratory studies of juvenile crime in Stockholm with register data from the police on suspected offenders. A bipartite graph model of such data is built from assumptions about crime reporting and offender detection for a specific type of crimes committed in a certain area during a certain time period. It is shown how the model parameters and the numbers of crimes of different sizes, the numbers of offenders of different activities, and the total number of offences can be estimated from data about reported crimes and police identified offenders. The illustrations also show the need for further statistical development. (C) 2001 Elsevier Science B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000170148200003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="16">
<title>Disaster response on September 11, 2001 through the lens of statistical network analysis</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2013.12.001</url>
<snippet>The rescue and relief operations triggered by the September 11, 2001 attacks on the World Trade Center in New York City demanded collaboration among hundreds of organisations. To shed light on the response to the September 11, 2001 attacks and help to plan and prepare the response to future disasters, we study the inter-organisational network that emerged in response to the attacks. Studying the inter-organisational network can help to shed light on (1) whether some organisations dominated the inter-organisational network and facilitated communication and coordination of the disaster response; (2) whether the dominating organisations were supposed to coordinate disaster response or emerged as coordinators in the wake of the disaster; and (3) the degree of network redundancy and sensitivity of the inter-organisational network to disturbances following the initial disaster. We introduce a Bayesian framework which can answer the substantive questions of interest while being as simple and parsimonious as possible. The framework allows organisations to have varying propensities to collaborate, while taking covariates into account, and allows to assess whether the inter-organisational network had network redundancy-in the form of transitivity-by using a test which may be regarded as a Bayesian score test. We discuss implications in terms of disaster management. (C) 2013 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000334001400004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="17">
<title>Check the phone book: Testing information and communication technology (ICT) recall aids for personal network surveys</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2014.11.006</url>
<snippet>This study tested two recall aids for the name generator procedure via a randomized web experiment with 447 college students, eliciting their personal networks. Compared to participants solely presented with the name generator, participants being prompted and probed to consult records saved in their communication devices provided more comprehensive network data and more weak ties. Furthermore, these data were garnered without either a substantial increase in item nonresponse or a decrease in completion time for subsequent name interpreters. Thus, ICF recall aids are deemed cost-effective and context-neutral techniques to improve the recall accuracy of data collected by the name generator. (C) 2014 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000351979100009
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="18">
<title>The evolution and formation of amicus curiae networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2012.07.003</url>
<snippet>This paper sheds light on two age-old questions of interest group behavior: how have interest group coalition strategies changed over time and which factors determine whether interest groups work together? Through the creation of a new network measure of interest group coalitions based on cosigner status to United States Supreme Court amicus curiae briefs, we illuminate the central players and overall characteristics of this dynamic network from 1930 to 2009. We present evidence of an increasingly transitive network resembling a host of tightly grouped factions and leadership hub organizations employing mixed coalition strategies. We also model the attribute homophily and structure of the present-day network. We find assortative mixing of interest groups based on industry area, budget, sales and membership. (C) 2012 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000328803800007
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="19">
<title>Making friends and communicating on Facebook: Implications for the access to social capital</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2013.11.003</url>
<snippet>In this paper, we explore the dynamics of access to social capital on Facebook. Existing approaches to network-based social capital measures are adapted to the case of Facebook and applied to the friendship and communication data of 438,851 users. These measures are correlated to user data in order to identify advantageous behavior for optimizing the possible access to social capital. We find that the access to social capital on Facebook is primarily based on a reasonable amount of active communication. Exaggerated friending and posting behavior can deteriorate the access to social capital. Furthermore, we investigate which kinds of posts are most advantageous as well as questions of homophily based on social capital. (C) 2013 Published by Elsevier B.V.
WOS:000334001400003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="20">
<title>On the use of Multiple Correspondence Analysis to visually explore affiliation networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2014.01.003</url>
<snippet>In this paper we discuss the use of Multiple Correspondence Analysis to analyze and graphically represent two-mode networks, and we propose to apply it in a Greenacres doubling perspective. We discuss how Multiple Correspondence Analysis: (i) properly takes into account the nature of relational data and the intrinsic asymmetry of actors/events in two-mode networks; (ii) allows a proper graphical appraisal of the underlying relational structure of actors or events; (iii) makes it possible to add actor and event attributes to the analysis in order to improve results interpretation; and (iv) gives different results with respect to the usual Simple Correspondence Analysis. (C) 2014 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000337015400003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="21">
<title>Efficiency of human activity on information spreading on Twitter</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2014.03.007</url>
<snippet>Understanding the collective reaction to individual actions is key to effectively spread information in social media. In this work we define efficiency on Twitter, as the ratio between the emergent spreading process and the activity employed by the user. We characterize this property by means of a quantitative analysis of the structural and dynamical patterns emergent from human interactions, and show it to be universal across several Twitter conversations. We found that some influential users efficiently cause remarkable collective reactions by each message sent, while the majority of users must employ extremely larger efforts to reach similar effects. Next we propose a model that reproduces the retweet cascades occurring on Twitter to explain the emergent distribution of the user efficiency. The model shows that the dynamical patterns of the conversations are strongly conditioned by the topology of the underlying network. We conclude that the appearance of a small fraction of extremely efficient users results from the heterogeneity of the followers network and independently of the individual user behavior. (C) 2014 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000340338600001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="22">
<title>Knowledge and networks: An experimental test of how network knowledge affects coordination</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2012.10.001</url>
<snippet>Scholars in the social sciences use network theory to study a range of collective action problems. Often the goal is to identify how the structure of the network affects efforts to coordinate or cooperate, and research suggests that adding connections to a network can improve the performance of groups faced with such tasks. On the other hand, theory and empirics also suggest that additional connections can degrade the performance of a network. If connections can have negative effects then it is important to consider if there are alternatives to adding connections to a network that can also improve network performance. Because a primary function of connections in a network is to disseminate information, providing individuals with more information about the network may act as a substitute for adding connections to a network. We test experimentally whether providing subjects with more information about the structure of networks can improve coordination. We find that a more complete view of the network leads to faster coordination, but the magnitude of this effect depends on network structure. These results suggest that changing what actors know about a network can improve outcomes without having to add connections that may impede overall performance. (C) 2012 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000328803800010
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="23">
<title>When is brokerage negatively associated with economic benefits? Ethnic diversity, competition, and common-pool resources</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2015.11.004</url>
<snippet>There is a growing body of literature positively linking dimensions of social capital to economic benefits. Yet recent research also points to a potential "dark side" of social capital, where over-embeddedness in networks and the pressures associated with brokerage are hypothesized to constrain actors, having a negative effect on economic outcomes. This dichotomy suggests that context is important, yet the overwhelming majority of existing empirical evidence stems from socially homogenous populations in corporate and organizational settings, limiting a broader understanding of when and how context matters. We advance this discourse to a socially fragmented, ethnically diverse common-pool resource system where information is highly valuable and competition is fierce. Merging several unique datasets from Hawaiis pelagic tuna fishery, we find that network prominence, i.e., being well connected locally, has a significant, positive effect on economic productivity. In contrast, we find that brokerage, defined here as ties that bridge either structurally distinct or ethnically distinct groups, has a significant, negative effect. Taken together, our results provide empirical support to widespread claims of the value of information access in common-pool resource systems, yet suggest that in ethnically diverse, competitive environments, brokers may be penalized for sharing information across social divides. Our results thus contribute to an emerging theory on the fragile nature of brokerage that recognizes its potential perils and the importance of context. (C) 2015 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000371362600005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="24">
<title>Is influence mightier than selection? Forging agreement in political discussion networks during a campaign</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2013.06.001</url>
<snippet>Is political agreement in social networks the product of selection or influence? We investigate this question using the first large, general population sample survey to track changes in the political discussion partners named by respondents over the course of an election campaign. We identify two social processes at work during the nine months prior to the election: "selection", or the likelihood that people choose discussion partners based on their political views, and "influence", or the likelihood that respondents exposed to political disagreement change their intended vote choice. We find evidence of both positive and negative selection for political agreement, as well as evidence that people are influenced by their friends and family. (C) 2013 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000328803800011
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="25">
<title>Error correction mechanisms in social networks can reduce accuracy and encourage innovation</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2015.07.007</url>
<snippet>Humans make mistakes but diffusion through social networks is typically modeled as though they do not. We find in an experiment that high entropy message formats (text messaging pidgin) are more prone to error than lower entropy formats (standard English). We also find that efforts to correct mistakes are effective, but generate more mutant forms of the contagion than would result from a lack of correction. This indicates that the ability of messages to cross "small-world" human social networks may be overestimated and that failed error corrections create new versions of a contagion that diffuse in competition with the original. (C) 2015 The Authors. Published by Elsevier B.V.
WOS:000367423900003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="26">
<title>Unpacking reputational power: Intended and unintended determinants of the assessment of actors' power</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2015.02.008</url>
<snippet>The idea behind the reputational measure for assessing power of political actors is that actors involved in a decision-making process have the best view of their fellows power. There has been, however, no systematic examination of why actors consider other actors as powerful. Consequently, it is unclear whether reputational power measures what it ought to. The paper analyzes the determinants of power attribution and distinguishes intended from unintended determinants in a data-set of power assessment covering 10 political decision-making processes in Switzerland. Results are overall reassuring, but nevertheless point toward self-promotion or misperception biases, as informants systematically attribute more power to actors with whom they collaborate. (C) 2015 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000355050600006
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="27">
<title>Power in politically charged networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2013.04.007</url>
<snippet>We offer a theory and measure for determining powerful nodal positions based on potential inter-actor control in "politically charged" networks, which contain both allies and adversaries. Power is derived from actors that are dependent on the focal actor and sociometrically weak, either due to a lack of alternative allies or from being threatened by others. We create a new Political Independence Index (PII), compare it to other established measures, and illustrate its use in the setting of an international network of alliances and military conflicts from 1946 to 2000. Results show that politically independent nations as measured by PII have smaller increases in military personnel than others over time. (C) 2013 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000328803800013
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="28">
<title>Reciprocity and the structural determinants of the international sanctions network</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2013.01.001</url>
<snippet>The imposition of international economic sanctions is a strategic and often multilateral phenomenon of states attempting to coerce each other into altering their behavior by means of economic pain. The interlocking connections of states issuing sanctions and being sanctioned creates a network of interdependent relations and, we argue, the structure of dependencies endogenous to the network is a major determinant of the networks formation and persistence. We consider endogenous structures, both theoretically and empirically, with three foci: the tendency to sanction frequently, the tendency to be sanctioned frequently, and, most of all, reciprocity. The empirical support we find for each of these processes adds a new dimension to our existing knowledge of the sanctioning process, casts doubt upon some previous findings, and opens important avenues for future research. (C) 2013 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000328803800002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="29">
<title>The political party as a network of cleavages: Disclosing the inner structure of Italian political parties in the seventies</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2012.07.005</url>
<snippet>Building on two established perspectives on the political party, in this paper we view the party as an organized network of formal and informal relationships between individuals that reflects national cleavages. We test this interpretation using two Italian parties of the 1970s that played major roles in shaping political and social life of the country: the Christian Democrats, or DC, and the Communists, or PCI. The 1970s saw the culmination of the DC and PCI's two-party dominance of the Italian state. Further, it was during this same period that the economic and social contradictions of Italy's tumultuous post-World War II process of industrialization became apparent, making social cleavages easy to grasp. We use cosponsoring of bills between parliamentary members as a measure of formal and informal relationships within each party. We deem this appropriate in the context of a pure proportional electoral system and highly polarized audiences. Data comes from the lower chamber of the Parliament during the Sixth Legislative cycle (1972-1977). We use HLM to model dyadic interactions between MPs and distinguish between repeated cosponsoring of bills (strong ties) and single occurrences of cosponsoring (weak ties). Our results show that within each party, national cleavages significantly increased the likelihood of strong ties but were not relevant in structuring weak ties. We conclude that the party has an internal structure made of a network of MPs informed by external social cleavages and held together by the common goal of being reelected. (C) 2012 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000328803800005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="30">
<title>Name generation in interpersonal political network data: Results from a series of experiments</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2013.02.002</url>
<snippet>We present results from three large scale survey experiments focused on the manipulation of political name generators. Using syntax that is widely employed outside of political science, we generate interpersonal political network data by varying the roles of alters, the time horizons of relationships, and the specific political nature of social exchanges. Across varying samples and electoral environments, we look for differences in these conditions on a wide range of common interpersonal network items, assess latency data on these treatments, and employ more detailed information on named discussants than most existing political ego-centric studies. We evaluate how well the now standard "compound" political name generator captures interpersonal political networks, finding that it does quite well save a few items of significant political importance. We discuss the implications of this research agenda for theories of social influence and the study of disagreement in democratic politics. (C) 2013 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000328803800012
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="31">
<title>Noise, bias, and expertise in political communication networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2013.02.003</url>
<snippet>A central focus in the study of social networks and politics centers on the dynamics of diffusion and persuasion, as well as the manner in which these processes are affected by expert "opinion leaders." The role of experts is particularly important in communication processes characterized by noisy, biased information processes in which people with variable levels of expertise and strength of preference select informants, as well as being influenced by them. We employ an experimental approach that addresses these problems at multiple levels of observation in a highly dynamic context small groups of individuals communicating with one another in real time. The analysis shows that participants formulate candidate judgments that decay in time, but the decay occurs at a significantly lower rate among the better informed. Moreover, the better informed are less affected by socially communicated messages regarding the candidates. Hence the influence of experts is not only due to their powers of persuasion, but also to the durability of their own privately formulated opinions. Their role in the communication process is further heightened by the higher value placed by participants on expert opinion, which in turn exposes the recipient to a heterogeneous and hence potentially influential stream of information. (C) 2013 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000328803800009
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="32">
<title>Multiplex networks and interest group influence reputation: An exponential random graph model</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2012.11.003</url>
<snippet>Interest groups struggle to build reputations as influential actors in the policy process and to discern the influence exercised by others. This study conceptualizes influence reputation as a relational variable that varies locally throughout a network. Drawing upon interviews with 168 interest group representatives in the United States health policy domain, this research examines the effects of multiplex networks of communication, coalitions, and issues on influence reputation. Using an exponential random graph model (ERGM), the analysis demonstrates that multiple roles of confidant, collaborator, and issue advocate affect how group representatives understand the influence of those with whom they are tied, after accounting for homophily among interest groups. (C) 2012 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000328803800006
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="33">
<title>The devil is in the details: Differences in air traffic networks by scale, species, and season</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2014.03.003</url>
<snippet>Although air traffic networks are widely studied examples of complex networks, past research has focused on only one type: the network of routes flown between airports. Although this network is important, other varieties of air traffic networks exist. This paper differentiates air traffic networks on dimensions of scale (airport vs. metropolitan area), species (business vs. leisure), and season (summer vs. winter). Although these networks share similar complex network topologies - they are scale-free, small-world, and modular - they are nonetheless different in substantively important ways. They capture different kinds of social and economic processes, are useful for investigating different kinds of research questions, and lead to different kinds of conclusions about how and where interactions are organized. (C) 2014 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000337015400006
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="34">
<title>Egocentric contact networks in comparison: Taiwan and Hungary</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2015.10.001</url>
<snippet>This study compares the size and structure of egocentric networks in Taiwan and Hungary using a diary approach. Both countries have transformed from authoritarian regimes to democratic states, yet they differ in social, economic, and cultural institutions that may be common to the respective larger region where each is located. To sample the structure of each egocentric network, we extracted information from largely identical contact diaries collected in both countries, 51 from Taiwan and 138 from Hungary. After comparing sample characteristics, network size, and composition, we construct a Strength of Ties (SoT) index based on two objective and two subjective measures of ego-alter ties. We then use this index to analyze tie strength by the types of relationships. On average, the number of alters contacted in one week is much larger in Taiwan than in Hungary, and the gap remains unchanged after controlling for key socio-demographic background factors. Even though the four indicators that we use to construct the SoT index are distributed similarly among the respondents in both Taiwan and Hungary, the composite index pinpoints how the types of relationships play somewhat different roles across the nations. The findings imply that the tendency to maintain only the closest ties with kin and other close friends is linked to distrust in others, a possible ill effect lingering from the authoritarian past. The implication is partially supported by further analyses using the ISSP 2006 survey data. We address how our findings may contribute to the existing literature on the linkage between societal characteristics and interpersonal ties. (C) 2015 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000367423900023
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="35">
<title>Food sharing networks in lowland Nicaragua: An application of the social relations model to count data</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2014.02.002</url>
<snippet>Previous research on food sharing in small-scale societies provides support for multiple evolutionary hypotheses, but evolutionary anthropologists have devoted relatively little attention to the broader relational context of inter-household transfers of food. The present research observes transfers of meat over a yearlong period among 25 households of indigenous Mayangna and Miskito horticulturalists in Nicaragua. To analyze these data, we extend the multilevel formulation of the social relations model to count data, namely the number of portions of meat exchanged between households. Along with other covariates, we examine the effect of an "association index," which reflects the amount of time that households interact with one another. The association index exhibits a positive effect on sharing, and our overall results indicate that food sharing networks largely correspond to kin-based networks of social interaction, suggesting that food sharing is embedded in broader social relationships between households. We discuss possible extensions of our methodological approach, as appropriate for research on food sharing and social network analysis more broadly. (C) 2014 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000337015400009
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="36">
<title>Measurement and theory in legislative networks: The evolving topology of Congressional collaboration</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2012.11.001</url>
<snippet>The examination of legislatures as social networks represents a growing area of legislative scholarship. We examine existing treatments of cosponsorship data as constituting legislative networks, with measures aggregated over entire legislative sessions. We point out ways in which the direct application of models from the social networks literature legislative networks aggregated over entire sessions could potentially obscure interesting variation at different levels of measurement. We then present an illustration of an alternative approach, in which we analyze disaggregated, dynamic networks and utilize multiple measures to guard against overly measure-dependent inferences. Our results indicate that the cosponsorship network is a highly responsive network subject to external institutional pressures that more aggregated analyses would overlook. (C) 2012 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000328803800008
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="37">
<title>Assessing structural correlates to social capital in Facebook ego networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2014.01.002</url>
<snippet>Research in computer-mediated communication has consistently asserted that Facebook use is positively correlated with social capital. This research has drawn primarily on Williams (2006) bridging and bonding scales as well as behavioral attributes such as civic engagement. Yet, as social capital is inherently a structural construct, it is surprising that so little work has been done relating social capital to social structure as captured by social network site (SNS) Friendship networks. Facebook is particularly well-suited to support the examination of structure at the ego level since the networks articulated on Facebook tend to be large, dense, and indicative of many offline foci (e.g., coworkers, friends from high school). Assuming that each one of these foci only partially overlap, we initially present two hypotheses related to Facebook social networks and social capital: more foci are associated with perceptions of greater bridging social capital and more closure is associated with greater bonding social capital. Using a study of 235 employees at a Midwestern American university, we test these hypotheses alongside self-reported measures of activity on the site. Our results only partially confirm these hypotheses. In particular, using a widely used measure of closure (transitivity) we observe a strong and persistent negative relationship to bonding social capital. Although this finding is initially counter-intuitive it is easily explained by considering the topology of Facebook personal networks: networks with primarily closed triads tend to be networks with tightly bound foci (such as everyone from high school knowing each other) and few connections between foci. Networks with primarily open triads signify many crosscutting friendships across foci. Therefore, bonding social capital appears to be less tied to local clustering than to global cohesion. (C) 2014 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000337015400001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="38">
<title>The backbone of bipartite projections: Inferring relationships from co-authorship, co-sponsorship, co-attendance and other co-behaviors</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2014.06.001</url>
<snippet>The analysis and visualization of weighted networks pose many challenges, which have led to the development of techniques for extracting the networks backbone, a subgraph composed of only the most significant edges. Weighted edges are particularly common in bipartite projections (e.g. networks of co-authorship, co-attendance, co-sponsorship), which are often used as proxies for one-mode networks where direct measurement is impractical or impossible (e.g. networks of collaboration, friendship, alliance). However, extracting the backbone of bipartite projections requires special care. This paper reviews existing methods for extracting the backbone from bipartite projections, and proposes a new method that aims to overcome their limitations. The stochastic degree sequence model (SDSM) involves the construction of empirical edge weight distributions from random bipartite networks with stochastic marginals, and is demonstrated using data on bill sponsorship in the 108th U.S. Senate. The extracted backbones validity as a network reflecting political alliances and antagonisms is established through comparisons with data on political party affiliations and political ideologies, which offer an empirical ground-truth. The projection and backbone extraction methods discussed in this paper can be performed using the -onemode- command in Stata. (C) 2014 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000340338600008
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="39">
<title>Assessing the bias in samples of large online networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2014.01.004</url>
<snippet>We consider the sampling bias introduced in the study of online networks when collecting data through publicly available APIs (application programming interfaces). We assess differences between three samples of Twitter activity; the empirical context is given by political protests taking place in May 2012. We track online communication around these protests for the period of one month, and reconstruct the network of mentions and re-tweets according to the search and the streaming APIs, and to different filtering parameters. We find that smaller samples do not offer an accurate picture of peripheral activity; we also find that the bias is greater for the network of mentions, partly because of the higher influence of snowballing in identifying relevant nodes. We discuss the implications of this bias for the study of diffusion dynamics and political communication through social media, and advocate the need for more uniform sampling procedures to study online communication. (C) 2014 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000337015400002
</snippet>
</document>

</searchresult>
