<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<searchresult>
<query>Global</query>
<document id="1">
<title>Effects of missing data in social networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2005.07.002</url>
<snippet>We perform sensitivity analyses to assess the impact of missing data on the structural properties of social networks. The social network is conceived of as being generated by a bipartite graph, in which actors are linked together via multiple interaction contexts or affiliations. We discuss three principal missing data mechanisms: network boundary specification (non-inclusion of actors or affiliations), survey non-response, and censoring by vertex degree (fixed choice design), examining their impact on the scientific collaboration network from the Los Alamos E-print Archive as well as random bipartite graphs. The simulation results show that network boundary specification and fixed choice designs can dramatically alter estimates of network-level statistics. The observed clustering and assortativity coefficients are overestimated via omission of affiliations or fixed choice thereof, and underestimated via actor non-response, which results in inflated measurement error. We also find that social networks with multiple interaction contexts may have certain interesting properties due to the presence of overlapping cliques. In particular, assortativity by degree does not necessarily improve network robustness to random omission of nodes as predicted by current theory. 
WOS:000238117100004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="2">
<title>The &lt;i&gt;VL&lt;/i&gt; control measure for symmetric networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2008.10.004</url>
<snippet>In this paper we measure "control" of nodes in a network by solving an associated optimisation problem. We motivate this so-called VL control measure by giving an interpretation in terms of allocating resources optimally to the nodes in order to maximise some search probability. We determine the VL control measure for various classes of networks. Furthermore, we provide two game theoretic interpretations of this measure. First it turns out that the VL control measure is a particular proper Shapley value of the associated cooperative network game. Secondly, we relate the measure to optimal strategies in an associated matrix search game. 
WOS:000262547600009
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="3">
<title>Basic notions for the analysis of large two-mode networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2007.04.006</url>
<snippet>Many large real-world networks actually have a two-mode nature: their nodes may be separated into two classes, the links being between nodes of different classes only. Despite this, and despite the fact that many ad hoc tools have been designed for the study of special cases, very few exist to analyse (describe, extract relevant information) such networks in a systematic way. We propose here an extension of the most basic notions used nowadays to analyse large one-mode networks (the classical case) to the two-mode case. To achieve this, we introduce a set of simple statistics, which we discuss by comparing their values on a representative set of real-world networks and on their random versions. This makes it possible to evaluate their relevance in capturing properties of interest in two-mode networks. (C) 2007 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000253735700003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="4">
<title>Measuring ego-centered social networks on the web: Questionnaire design issues</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2008.03.002</url>
<snippet>Collecting survey data on ego-centered social networks is a difficult task, owing to the complex questionnaire format. Usually, the interviewer handles the dynamics of the question-answer exchange, motivates the respondent and ensures the proper recording of the data. Self-administered modes of data collection, especially web data collection, are more problematic, as the respondents are left alone with a complex and burdensome questionnaire. Therefore, questionnaire layout is crucial for ensuring cooperation and data quality. In this paper we examined three key components of the corresponding web questionnaire: the number of name boxes using a single name generator, question format for assessing alter characteristics (i.e. alter-wise vs. question-wise) and number of name interpreters (i.e. alter characteristics). The number of name boxes was found to be essential for the reported size of social networks and also for some aspects of data quality. Specific data quality effects were also found with respect to variations in question format, where question-wise format performed better than alter-wise. The number of name interpreters had a relatively minor effect. Suggestions for possible standardization of the web interface layout are also given, so that equivalence with other data collection modes can be established. 
WOS:000257568200004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="5">
<title>Legislative cosponsorship networks in the US House and Senate</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2005.11.003</url>
<snippet>
WOS:000240890700011
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="6">
<title>Curved exponential family models for social networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2006.08.005</url>
<snippet>Curved exponential family models are a useful generalization of exponential random graph models (ERGMs). In particular, models involving the alternating k-star, alternating k-triangle, and alternating k-twopath statistics of Snijders et al. [Snijders, T.A.B., Pattison, P.E., Robins, G.L., Handcock, M.S., in press. New specifications for exponential random graph models. Sociological Methodology] may be viewed as curved exponential family models. This article unifies recent material in the literature regarding curved exponential family models for networks in general and models involving these alternating statistics in particular. It also discusses the intuition behind rewriting the three alternating statistics in terms of the degree distribution and the recently introduced shared partner distributions. This intuition suggests a redefinition of the alternating k-star statistic. Finally, this article demonstrates the use of the statnet package in R for fitting models of this sort, comparing new results on an oft-studied network dataset with results found in the literature. 
WOS:000246430600004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="7">
<title>Networks embedded in &lt;i&gt;n&lt;/i&gt;-dimensional space:: The impact of dimensionality change</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2005.11.002</url>
<snippet>Social networks can be embedded in an n-dimensional space, where the dimensions may reveal or denote underlying properties of interest. When the pertaining actors occupy niches of resources in this space, e.g., organizational niches of affiliates, we show there exists a non-monotonic effect of dimensionality change. Depending on niche width, relatively narrow or wide, dimensionality change has opposing effects on niche volume. 
WOS:000240890700010
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="8">
<title>Group betweenness and co-betweenness: Inter-related notions of coalition centrality</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2009.02.003</url>
<snippet>Vertex betweenness centrality is a metric that seeks to quantify a sense of the importance of a vertex in a network in terms of its 'control' on the flow of information along geodesic paths throughout the network. Two natural ways to extend vertex betweenness centrality to sets of vertices are (i) in terms of geodesic paths that pass through at least one of the vertices in the set, and (ii) in terms of geodesic paths that pass through all vertices in the set. The former was introduced by Everett and Borgatti [Everett, M., Borgatti, S., 1999. The centrality of groups and classes. journal of Mathematical Sociology 23 (3), 181-201], and called group betweenness centrality. The latter, which we call co-betweenness centrality here, has not been considered formally in the literature until now, to the best of our knowledge. In this paper, we show that these two notions of centrality are in fact intimately related and, furthermore, that this relationship may be exploited to obtain deeper insight into both. In particular, we provide an expansion for group betweenness in terms of increasingly higher orders of co-betweenness, in a manner analogous to the Taylor series expansion of a mathematical function in calculus. We then demonstrate the utility of this expansion by using it to construct analytic lower and upper bounds for group betweenness that involve only simple combinations of (i) the betweenness of individual vertices in the group, and (ii) the co-betweenness of pairs of these vertices. Accordingly, we argue that the latter quantity, i.e., pairwise co-betweenness, is itself a fundamental quantity of some independent interest, and we present a computationally efficient algorithm for its calculation, which extends the algorithm of Brandes [ Brandes, U., 2001. A faster algorithm for betweenness centrality. journal of Mathematical Sociology 25,1631 in a natural manner. Applications are provided throughout, using a handful of different communication networks, which serve to illustrate the way in which our mathematical contributions allow for insight to be gained into the interaction of network structure, coalitions, and information flow in social networks. (C) 2009 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000267838900003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="9">
<title>Impact of methods for reducing respondent burden on personal network structural measures</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2006.12.005</url>
<snippet>We examine methods for reducing respondent burden in evaluating alter-alter ties on a set of network structural measures. The data consist of two sets, each containing 45 alters from respondent free lists: the first contains 447 personal networks, and the second 554. Respondents evaluated the communication between 990 alter pairs. The methods were (1) dropping alters from the end of the free-list, (2) randomly dropping alters, (3) randomly dropping links, and (4) predicting ties based on transitivity. For some measures network structure is captured with samples of less than 20 alters; other measures are less consistent. Researchers should be aware of the need to sample a minimum number of alters to capture structural variation. 
WOS:000246430600009
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="10">
<title>Re-evaluating the community question from a German perspective</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2007.01.008</url>
<snippet>The far-reaching effects of the social systemic division of labor on the organization and contents of primary ties make the Community Question an important issue for many sociologists. This paper looks at the personal embeddedness of families in three German cities (Berlin, Hamburg, and Stuttgart) and examines the Community Question with data collected at the end of 2003. It is based on the theoretical views of Wellman [Wellman, B., 1979. The community question. The intimate networks of East Yorkers. American Journal of Sociology 84 1201-1231], who used a network analysis perspective to conceptualize "the Community Question". The results of this German study generally support the results of Wellmans second East York Study. However, the network structures analyzed in my study vary from the three ideal-type models. Cluster analysis shows that Wellmans typology can be replicated relatively well in Germany. In contrast to traditional discourse related to the Community Question, particular network types are not associated with low levels of social relations. Moreover. structural factors do not explain the existence of different network types. Thus, the networks are not a product of only one community model. They suggest that it is less helpful to talk about "Saved", "Lost", or "Liberated" communities than it is to regard communities as a mixture of strongly-knit nuclear clusters and of broader, sparsely-knit relations that provide access to different groups and their resources. 
WOS:000248429500003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="11">
<title>Social creativity as a function of agent cognition and network properties: A computer model</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2010.04.001</url>
<snippet>Inventions - concepts, devices, procedures - are often created by networks of interacting agents in which the agents can be individuals (as in a scientific discipline) or they can themselves be collectives (as in firms interacting in a market). Different collectives create and invent at different rates. It is plausible that the rate of invention is jointly determined by properties of the agents (e.g., their cognitive capacity) and by properties of the network of interactions (e.g., the density of the communication links), but little is known about such two-level interactions. We present an agent-based model of social creativity in which the individual agent captures key features of the human cognitive architecture derived from cognitive psychology, and the interactions are modeled by agents exchanging partial results of their symbolic processing of task information. We investigated the effect of agent and network properties on rates of invention and diffusion in the network via systematic parameter variations. Simulation runs show, among other results, that (a) the simulation exhibits network effects, i.e., the model captures the beneficial effect of collaboration; (b) the density of connections produces diminishing returns in term of the benefits on the invention rate: and 
WOS:000283402000002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="12">
<title>Bridging: Locating critical connectors in a network</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2010.03.003</url>
<snippet>This paper proposes several measures for bridging in networks derived from Granovetters (1973) insight that links which reduce distances in a network are important structural bridges. Bridging is calculated by systematically deleting links and calculating the resultant changes in network cohesion (measured as the inverse average path length). The average change for each nodes links provides an individual level measure of bridging. We also present a normalized version which controls for network size and a network-level bridging index. Bridging properties are demonstrated on hypothetical networks, empirical networks, and a set of 100 randomly generated networks to show how the bridging measure correlates with existing network measures such as degree, personal network density, constraint, closeness centrality, betweenness centrality, and vitality. Bridging and the accompanying methodology provide a family of new network measures useful for studying network structure, network dynamics, and network effects on substantive behavioral phenomenon. (C) 2010 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000279409000006
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="13">
<title>Duocentered networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2007.07.001</url>
<snippet>When a pair of individuals is central to a research problem (e.g., husband and wife, PhD student and supervisor) the concept of "duocentered" networks can be defined as a useful extension of egocentered networks. This new structure consists of a pair of central egos and their direct links with alters, instead of just one central ego as in the egocentered networks or multiple egos as in complete networks. The key point in this kind of network is that ties exist between the central pair of egos and between them and all alters, but the ties among alters are not considered. Duocentered networks can also be considered as a compromise between egocentered and complete networks. Complete network measurements are often costly to obtain and tend to contain a large proportion of missing data (especially for peripheral actors). Egocentered network data are less costly but a lot of information is lost with their use when a pair of individuals is the relevant unit of analysis. From the definition of duocentered networks, we develop new social network measures, some of which based on the measures for complete networks such as degree, closeness centrality or density, both absolute and relative, while others are tailored to dealing with specific characteristics of the duocentered network structures. The proposed measures are used in the analysis of the networks of Slovenian PhD students and their supervisors. We specify three regression models to predict PhD student's academic performance on the basis of these duocentered network measures for different relations such as advice, collaboration, emotional support, and trust. The results show that absolute duocentered measures predict performance best. When compared with egocentered network measures a higher predictive power of duocentered networks is revealed. (C) 2007 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000253735700004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="14">
<title>Exploratory social network analysis with Pajek</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2005.12.002</url>
<snippet>
WOS:000238117100005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="15">
<title>An algorithm and metric for network decomposition from similarity matrices: Application to positional analysis</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2007.11.002</url>
<snippet>We present an algorithm for decomposing a social network into an optimal number of structurally equivalent classes. The k-means method is used to determine the best decomposition of the social network for various numbers of subgroups. The best number of subgroups into which to decompose a network is determined by minimizing the intra-cluster variance of similarity subject to the constraint that the improvement in going to more subgroups is better than a random network would achieve. We also describe a decomposability metric that assesses how closely the derived decomposition approaches an ideal network having only structurally equivalent classes. Three well-known network data sets were used to demonstrate the algorithm and decomposability metric. These demonstrations indicate the utility of the approach and suggest how it can be used in a complementary way to Generalized Blockmodeling. (C) 2007 Elsevier B.V All rights reserved.
WOS:000255583700004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="16">
<title>Core/periphery structure models:: An alternative methodological proposal</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2005.11.001</url>
<snippet>The idea of a structure made up of a core and periphery is a common, classic paradigm in many fields of science. Following this line, in 1999, researchers Stephen Borgatti and Martin Everett developed a model of structural analysis based on the delimitation of a core formed by a group of densely connected actors, in contrast to a class of actors, more loosely connected and forming the periphery of the system. The original approach of these authors is modified, employing measures that, in our opinion, show a larger degree of coherence and accuracy in the proposed objectives. 
WOS:000240890700009
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="17">
<title>What are friends for? Elective communities of single people</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2008.07.001</url>
<snippet>The paper presents the results of a qualitative research on friendship networks of single people. The research has been undertaken using social network analysis tools (egonetworks) and qualitative interviews, on a non-representative sample of 23 heterosexual singles of Milan, aged between 25 and 35 years, 12 male and 11 female. Framed within the theory of community, we formulated some questions that are addressed through the analysis: the role of friendship in single people's everyday life, which in some cases substitutes the traditional family as a source of emotional, social, material and economical support; the possibility that friendship is not always intended as a source of support, and people can name friends even if they do not provide any kind of support; the effect of the network structure on the strength of dyads, that will easily disconnect if not embedded in a cohesive network. Four different kinds of friendship networks have been found: the small cliques, the company, the core/periphery structure, and the contextualised components. In the discussion section, empirical findings are analysed focusing on different strategies of friendship, and special attention is given to the gender issue. (C) 2008 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000260367400005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="18">
<title>It's not who you know, it's how you know them:: Who exchanges what with whom?</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2007.01.007</url>
<snippet>Reciprocity - doing for others if they have done for you - is a key way people mobilize resources to deal with daily life and seize opportunities. In principle, reciprocity (the Golden Rule) is a universal norm. In practice, it is variable. Personal networks rarely operate as solidarities and as such, people cannot count on all the members of their networks to provide help all the time. Rather, social support comes uncertainly from a variety of ties in networks. This paper uses survey research to understand the variable and contingent nature of reciprocity and inquires about the kinds of resources exchanged between people. We investigate the extent to which interpersonal ties, network characteristics, and peoples personal characteristics (e.g., gender) affect the nature of reciprocal relationships. The evidence is extraordinarily clear on one subject - giving Support is strongly associated with getting it. Analyses show that getting support from network members is the key to East Yorkers reciprocating - usually in kind but sometimes with other forms of support. 
WOS:000248429500005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="19">
<title>The network is personal:: Introduction to a special issue of &lt;i&gt;Social Networks&lt;/i&gt;</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2007.01.006</url>
<snippet>
WOS:000248429500001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="20">
<title>Computing continuous core/periphery structures for social relations data with MINRES/SVD</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2009.09.003</url>
<snippet>When diagonal values are missing or excluded, MINRES is a natural continuous model for the core/periphery structure of a symmetric social network matrix. Symmetric models, however, are not so useful when dealing with asymmetric data. Singular value decomposition (SVD) is a natural choice to model asymmetry, but this method also requires the presence of diagonal values. In this paper we offer an alternative, more general, approach to continuous core/periphery structures, the minimum residual singular value decomposition (MINRES/SVD), where each node in the network receives two indices, an "in-coreness" and an "out-coreness." The algorithm for computing these coreness vectors is a least squares computation similar to, but distinct from the SVD, again because of the missing diagonal values. And in contrast to the standard, symmetric MINRES algorithm, we can more accurately model asymmetric matrices. This allows us to distinguish, for example, countries in the world economy that are more in the exporting core than they are in the importing core. We propose two nested PRE (proportional reduction of error) measures of fit: (1) the PRE from the MINRES vector with respect to the data and (2) the PRE of the product of the two MINRES/SVD vectors. Applying the resulting method to citations between journals and to international trade in clothing, we illustrate insights gained from being able to model asymmetrical flow patterns. Finally, two permutation tests are introduced to test independently for the MINRES and MINRES/SVD results. (C) 2009 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000276669100003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="21">
<title>Identifying regular blocks in valued networks: A heuristic applied to the St. Marks carbon flow data, and international trade in cereal products</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2005.12.001</url>
<snippet>While the concept of regular equivalence is equally applicable to dichotomous as well as valued networks, the identification of regular blocks in regular blockmodels is somewhat problematic when dealing with valued networks. Applying the standard procedure for identifying ties in such blockmodels, a procedure perhaps most suited for dichotomous networks, does tend to generate block images and reduced graphs that differ from intuitive notions of such structures. This paper outlines a formal heuristic procedure for identifying regular ties in valued networks where the "significance" of ties is related to each actor's role sets. Combined with measures for block criteria fulfillment, the procedure yields reduced graphs, which seem more sensitive to patterns, rather than strengths, of ties. Two data sets are used as examples in this paper: the St. Marks carbon flow web dataset, and a new dataset containing international trade flows of cereals and cereal products based on Comtrade data. 
WOS:000244397100005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="22">
<title>Popularity trajectories and substance use in early adolescence</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2010.10.001</url>
<snippet>This paper introduces new longitudinal network data from the "Promoting School-Community-University Partnerships to Enhance Resilience" or "PROSPER" peers project. In 28 communities, grade-level sociometric friendship nominations were collected from two cohorts of middle school students as they moved from 6th, to 9th grade. As an illustration and description of these longitudinal network data, this paper describes the school popularity structure, changes in popularity position, and suggests linkages between popularity trajectory and substance use. In the cross-section, we find that the network is consistent with a hierarchical social organization, but exhibits considerable relational change in both particular friends and position at the individual level. We find that both the base level of popularity and the variability of popularity trajectories effect substance use. (C) 2010 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000291175400001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="23">
<title>Did distance matter before the Internet? Interpersonal contact and support in the 1970s</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2007.01.009</url>
<snippet>Well before the coming of the Internet, strong ties with friends and relatives stretched beyond the neighborhood: the traditional domain of community. Phones, cars and planes allowed people to have contact over substantial distances. But the mere fact that ties stretched over long distances does not tell us the extent to which distance mattered for contact and support in pre-Internet days. Although, scholars have mused about this question, they have not provided empirical evidence. This paper applies multi-level analysis to assess the extent contact and support declines with distance. It shows a marked drop in the frequency of face-to-face contact at about 5 miles. The frequency of contact continues to decrease steadily further away, with substantial declines happening at about 50 and 100 miles. Distance affects telephone contact somewhat differently, with a marked drop only happening at about 100 miles. Distance also has a significant impact on providing tangible support. As our data were gathered in 1978 in the Toronto area of East York, they allow comparisons with how relationships have changed in light of new forms of communication, such as the Internet and mobile phones. 
WOS:000248429500006
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="24">
<title>Tastes, ties, and time: A new social network dataset using Facebook.com</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2008.07.002</url>
<snippet>Scholars have long recognized the potential of Internet-based communication technologies for improving network research-potential that, to date, remains largely underexploited. In the first half of this paper, we introduce a new public dataset based on manipulations and embellishments of a popular social network site, Facebook.com. We emphasize five distinctive features of this dataset and highlight its advantages and limitations vis-a-vis other kinds of network data. In the second half of this paper, we present descriptive findings from our first wave of data. Subgroups defined by gender, race/ethnicity, and socioeconomic status are characterized by distinct network behaviors, and students sharing social relationships as well as demographic traits tend to share a significant number of cultural preferences. These findings exemplify the scientific and pedagogical potential of this new network resource and provide a starting point for future analyses. (C) 2008 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000260367400006
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="25">
<title>Clustering in weighted networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2009.02.002</url>
<snippet>In recent years, researchers have investigated a growing number of weighted networks where ties are differentiated according to their strength or capacity. Yet, most network measures do not take weights into consideration, and thus do not fully capture the richness of the information contained in the data. In this paper, we focus on a measure originally defined for unweighted networks: the global clustering coefficient. We propose a generalization of this coefficient that retains the information encoded in the weights of ties. We then undertake a comparative assessment by applying the standard and generalized coefficients to a number of network datasets. (C) 2009 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000265325900006
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="26">
<title>Generalized blockmodeling of valued networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2006.04.002</url>
<snippet>The paper presents several approaches to generalized blockmodeling of valued networks, where values of the ties are assumed to be measured on at least interval scale. The first approach is a straightforward generalization of the generalized blockmodeling of binary networks [Doreian, P., Batagelj, V, Ferligoj, A., 2005. Generalized Blockmodeling. Cambridge University Press, New York.] to valued blockmodeling. The second approach is homogeneity blockmodeling. The basic idea of homogeneity blockmodeling is that the inconsistency of an empirical block with its ideal block can be measured by within block variability of appropriate values. New ideal blocks appropriate for blockmodeling of valued networks are presented together with definitions of their block inconsistencies. 
WOS:000244397100009
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="27">
<title>Structure and time evolution of an Internet dating community</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2004.01.007</url>
<snippet>We present statistics for the structure and time evolution of a network constructed from user activity in an Internet community. The vastness and precise time resolution of an Internet community offers unique possibilities to monitor social network formation and dynamics. Time evolution of well-known quantities, such as clustering, mixing (degree-degree correlations), average geodesic length, degree, and reciprocity is studied. In contrast to earlier analyses of scientific collaboration networks, mixing by degree between vertices is found to be disassortative. Furthermore, both the evolutionary trajectories of the average geodesic length and of the clustering coefficients are found to have minima. (C) 2004 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000221286300004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="28">
<title>A graph-theoretic perspective on centrality</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2005.11.005</url>
<snippet>
WOS:000240890700012
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="29">
<title>Networks and collective action</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2012.06.003</url>
<snippet>This paper proposes a new measure for a groups ability to lead society to adopt their standard of behavior, which in particular takes account of the time the group takes to convince the whole society to adopt their position. This notion of a groups power to initiate action is computed as the reciprocal of the resistance against it, which is in turn given by the expected absorption time of a related finite state partial Markov chain that captures the social dynamics. The measure is applicable and meaningful in a variety of models where interaction between agents is formalized through (weighted) binary relations. Using Percolation Theory, it is shown that the group power is monotonic as a function of groups of agents. We also explain the differences between our measure and those discussed in the literature on Graph Theory, and illustrate all these concerns by a thorough analysis of two particular cases: the Wolfe Primate Data and the 11S hijackers network. (C) 2012 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000313304100021
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="30">
<title>The school class as a social network and contextual effects on childhood and adult health: Findings from the Aberdeen Children of the 1950s cohort study</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2011.08.004</url>
<snippet>Little is known about the health consequences of the school class as a social network. The present study asked whether overall school-class structure has contextual effects on psychiatric problems in childhood and adult self-rated health. From longitudinal data on a Scottish cohort, measures of school-class structure (centralisation, degree of reciprocity and proportion of isolates) were constructed based on sociometric information. Multilevel analysis demonstrated significant effects of centralisation on both health outcomes. It is suggested that highly centralised classes are characterised by inequality, resulting in a low level of integration, with subsequent negative consequences for health. (C) 2011 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000298122200004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="31">
<title>On the robustness of centrality measures under conditions of imperfect data</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2005.05.001</url>
<snippet>An analysis is conducted on the robustness of measures of centrality in the face of random error in the network data. We use random networks of varying sizes and densities and subject them (separately) to four kinds of random error in varying amounts. The types of error are edge deletion, node deletion, edge addition, and node addition. The results show that the accuracy of centrality measures declines smoothly and predictably with the amount of error. This suggests that, for random networks and random error, we shall be able to construct confidence intervals around centrality scores. In addition, centrality measures were highly similar in their response to error. Dense networks were the most robust in the face of all kinds of error except edge deletion. For edge deletion, sparse networks were more accurately measured. 
WOS:000236007800002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="32">
<title>Family comes first: Men's and women's personal networks in Tehran</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2007.01.004</url>
<snippet>This paper examines the characteristics of middle class Tehranis networks, based upon a survey of 318 individuals from the 159 households. The results show that women and men have similar-size networks. However, their networks differ substantially in gender composition, with each having almost two-thirds of network members of their own gender. Mens and womens networks contain a large proportion of kin overall. Most ties tend to be with immediate kin: children, parents and siblings. An immediate kin is usually the socially closest member of a network. Apart from voluntary factors, the importance of kinship ties in mens and womens networks may be the result of the macro-structural conditions under which patterns of social relationships take place. 
WOS:000248429500002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="33">
<title>Generalized blockmodeling</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2006.02.001</url>
<snippet>
WOS:000238117100006
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="34">
<title>A model for collaboration networks giving rise to a power-law distribution with an exponential cutoff</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2005.12.003</url>
<snippet>Recently several authors have proposed stochastic evolutionary models for the growth of complex networks that give rise to power-law distributions. These models are based on the notion of preferential attachment leading to the "rich get richer" phenomenon. Despite the generality of the proposed stochastic models, there are still some unexplained phenomena, which may arise due to the limited size of networks such as protein, e-mail, actor and collaboration networks. Such networks may in fact exhibit an exponential cutoff in the power-law scaling, although this cutoff may only be observable in the tail of the distribution for extremely large networks. We propose a modification of the basic stochastic evolutionary model, so that after a node is chosen preferentially, say according to the number of its inlinks, there is a small probability that this node will become inactive. We show that as a result of this modification, by viewing the stochastic process in terms of an urn transfer model, we obtain a power-law distribution with an exponential cutoff. Unlike many other models, the current model can capture instances where the exponent of the distribution is less than or equal to two. As a proof of concept, we demonstrate the consistency of our model empirically by analysing the Mathematical Research collaboration network, the distribution of which has been shown to be compatible with a power law with an exponential cutoff. 
WOS:000244397100006
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="35">
<title>The authority of Supreme Court precedent</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2007.05.001</url>
<snippet>We construct the complete network of 30,288 majority opinions written by the U.S. Supreme Court and the cases they cite from 1754 to 2002 in the United States Reports. Data from this network demonstrates quantitatively the evolution of the norm of stare decisis in the 19th Century and a significant deviation from this norm by the activist Warren Court. We further describe a method for creating authority scores using the network data to identify the most important court precedents. This method yields rankings that conform closely to evaluations by legal experts, and even predicts which cases they will identify as important in the future. An analysis of these scores over time allows us to test several hypotheses about the rise and fall of precedent. We show that reversed cases tend to be much more important than other decisions, and the cases that over-rule them quickly become and remain even more important as the reversed decisions decline. We also show that the Court is careful to ground overruling decisions in past precedent, and the care it exercises is increasing in the importance of the decision that is overruled. Finally, authority scores corroborate qualitative assessments of which issues and cases the Court prioritizes and how these change over time. (C) 2007 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000253735700002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="36">
<title>On variants of shortest-path betweenness centrality and their generic computation</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2007.11.001</url>
<snippet>Betweenness centrality based on shortest paths is a standard measure of control utilized in numerous studies and implemented in all relevant software tools for network analysis. In this paper, a number of variants are reviewed, placed into context, and shown to be computable with simple variants of the algorithm commonly used for the standard case. (C) 2008 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000255583700003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="37">
<title>Representing degree distributions, clustering, and homophily in social networks with latent cluster random effects models</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2009.04.001</url>
<snippet>Social network data often involve transitivity, homophily on observed attributes, community structure, and heterogeneity of actor degrees. We propose a latent cluster random effects model to represent all of these features, and we develop Bayesian inference for it. The model is applicable to both binary and non-binary network data. We illustrate the model using two real datasets: liking between monks and coreaderships between Slovenian publications. We also apply it to two simulated network datasets with very different network structure but the same highly skewed degree sequence generated from a preferential attachment process. One has transitivity and community structure while the other does not. Models based solely on degree distributions. such as scale-free, preferential attachment and power-law models, cannot distinguish between these very different situations, but the latent cluster random effects model does. (C) 2009 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000267838900004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="38">
<title>Models and methods in social network analysis.</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2007.02.001</url>
<snippet>
WOS:000250964800009
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="39">
<title>VIP-club phenomenon: Emergence of elites and masterminds in social networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2005.07.005</url>
<snippet>Hubs, or vertices with large degrees, play massive roles in, for example, epidemic dynamics, innovation diffusion, and synchronization on networks. However, costs of owning edges can motivate agents to decrease their degrees and avoid becoming hubs, whereas they would somehow like to keep access to a major part of the network. By analyzing a model and tennis players partnership networks, we show that combination of vertex fitness and homophily yields a VIP-club made of elite vertices that are influential but not easily accessed from the majority. Intentionally formed VIP members can even serve as masterminds, which manipulate hubs to control the entire network without exposing themselves to a large mass. If based on network topology only, elites are not distinguished from many other vertices. Understanding network data is far from sufficient; individualistic factors greatly affect network structure and functions per se. 
WOS:000240890700002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="40">
<title>To tell the truth: Measuring concordance in multiply reported network data</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2005.11.009</url>
<snippet>Social network data must accurately reflect actors relationships to properly estimate network features. Here, we examine multiple reports of sexual, drug-sharing and social tie data on high-risk networks in Colorado Springs. By comparing multiple reports on the same ties, we can evaluate the reliability of this studys network data. Our findings suggest that these data have a high level of reporting agreement. From these findings, we discuss implications for analysis of these and similar data and provide suggestions for future social network data collection efforts. 
WOS:000244397100004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="41">
<title>Induced, endogenous and exogenous centrality</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2010.06.004</url>
<snippet>Centrality measures are based upon the structural position an actor has within the network. Induced centrality, sometimes called vitality measures, take graph invariants as an overall measure and derive vertex level measures by deleting individual nodes or edges and examining the overall change. By taking the sum of standard centrality measures as the graph invariant we can obtain measures which examine how much centrality an individual node contributes to the centrality of the other nodes in the network, we call this exogenous centrality. We look at exogenous measures of degree, closeness and betweenness. (C) 2010 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000283402000008
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="42">
<title>Partitioning signed social networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2008.08.001</url>
<snippet>Structural balance theory has proven useful for delineating the blockmodel structure of signed social networks. Even so, most of the observed signed networks are not perfectly balanced. One possibility for this is that in examining the dynamics underlying the generation of signed social networks. insufficient attention has been given to other processes and features of signed networks. These include: actors who have positive ties to pairs of actors linked by a negative relation or who belong to two Mutually hostile Subgroups; some actors that are viewed positively across the network despite the presence of negative ties and subsets of actors with negative ties towards each other. We suggest that instead viewing these situations as violations of structural balance, they can be seen as belonging to other relevant processes we call mediation, differential popularity and internal Subgroup hostility. Formalizing these ideas leads to the relaxed structural balance blockmodel as a proper generalization of structural balance blockmodels. Some formal properties concerning the relation between these two models are presented along with the properties of the fitting method proposed for the new blockmodel type. The new method is applied to four empirical data sets where improved fits with more nuanced interpretations are obtained. 
WOS:000262547600001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="43">
<title>The use of sparsest cuts to reveal the hierarchical community structure of social networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2008.03.004</url>
<snippet>We show that good community structures can be obtained by partitioning a social network in a succession of divisive sparsest cuts. A network flow algorithm based on fundamental principles of graph theory is introduced to identify the sparsest cuts and an underlying hierarchical community structure of the network via maximum concurrent flow. Matula [Matula, David W., 1985. Concurrent flow and concurrent connectivity in graphs. In: Alavi, Y., et al. (Eds.), Graph Theory and its Applications to Algorithms and Computer Science. Wiley, New York, NY, pp. 543-559.] established the maximum concurrent flow problem (MCFP), and papers, on divisive vs. agglomerative average-linkage hierarchical clustering [e.g., Matula, David W., 1983. Cluster validity by concurrent chaining. In: Felsenstein, J. (Ed.), Numerical Taxonomy: Proc. of the NATO Adv. Study Inst., vol. 1. Springer-Verlag, New York, pp. 156-166 (Proceedings of NATO ASI Series G); Matula, David W., 1986. Divisive vs. agglomerative average linkage hierarchical clustering. In: Gaul, W., and Schader, M. (Eds.), Classification as a Tool of Research. Elsevier, North-Holland, Amsterdam, pp. 289-301; Thompson, Byron J., 1985. A flow rerouting algorithm for the maximum concurrent flow problem with variable capacities and demands, and its application to cluster analysis. MasterThesis. School of Engineering and Applied Science, Southern Methodist University] provide the basis for partitioning a social network by way of sparsest cuts and/or maximum concurrent flow. The MCFP extends the [Ford Jr., Lester R., Fulkerson, Delbert R., 1956. Maximal flow through a network. Canadian journal of Mathematics 8, 399-404; Ford Jr., Lester R., Fulkerson, Delbert R., 1962. Flows in Networks. Princeton University Press, Princeton, NJ] source-sink max-flow problem to all-pairs maximum concurrent flow. The density of an (S, T)-cut is vertical bar(S, T)\(vertical bar S vertical bar center dot vertical bar T vertical bar) where vertical bar(S, T)vertical bar is the number of edges (equivalently, links or bonds) between communities S and T with vertical bar S vertical bar center dot vertical bar T vertical bar being the maximum number of edges possible. The minimum density cut in the network is the sparsest cut. When the edges are weighted, the density is the average weight of the (S, T)-cut edges, with absent edges treated as edges of zero weight. Sparsest cuts (i.e., minimum density) of the remaining components are iteratively determined via linear programming until a multipartite cut is identified that is more constraining to concurrent flow than any sparsest cut. Empirical results on real-world networks with known hierarchical structures and random networks with embedded communities are used to compare this sparsest-cut community structure criterion to the weighted Girvan-Newman community structure criterion [e.g., Newman, M.E.J., 2004. Analysis of weighted networks.. Physical Review E 70, 056131] that is based on edge betweenness centrality. A new measure of accuracy M is defined to evaluate the results of the graph partitionings found by these criteria. 
WOS:000257568200005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="44">
<title>Predictors of short-term decay of cell phone contacts in a large scale communication network</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2011.07.002</url>
<snippet>Under what conditions is an edge present in a social network at time t likely to decay or persist by some future time t + Delta t? Previous research addressing this issue suggests that the network range of the people involved in the edge, the extent to which the edge is embedded in a surrounding structure, and the age of the edge all play a role in edge decay. This paper uses weighted data from a large-scale social network built from cell-phone calls in an 8-week period to determine the importance of edge weight for the decay/persistence process. In particular, we study the relative predictive power of directed weight, embeddedness, newness, and range (measured as outdegree) with respect to edge decay and assess the effectiveness with which a simple decision tree and logistic regression classifier can accurately predict whether an edge that was active in one time period continues to be so in a future time period. We find that directed edge weight, weighted reciprocity and time-dependent measures of edge longevity are highly predictive of whether we classify an edge as persistent or decayed, relative to the other types of factors at the dyad and neighborhood level. (C) 2011 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000298122200001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="45">
<title>Treatment of non-response in longitudinal network studies</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2008.04.004</url>
<snippet>The collection of longitudinal data on complete social networks often faces the problem of actor non-response. The resulting incomplete data pose a challenge to statistical analysis, as there typically is no natural way to treat the missing cases. This paper examines the problems caused by actors missing as nominators, but still occurring as nominees, in complete, directed networks measured in a panel design. In the framework of stochastic actor-driven models for network change ("SIENA models"), different methods to cope with such incomplete data are investigated. Data on a friendship network among female high school students are used to illustrate the procedures. Missing data problems related to early panel exit and late panel entry are not addressed. (C) 2008 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000260367400003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="46">
<title>Dynamic exchange networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2006.12.003</url>
<snippet>Considering the theoretical and empirical untenability of static exchange networks, researchers have asked how exchange outcomes change when links are added or deleted. The present paper assesses the validity of seemingly sensible propositions concerning the effects of adding and deleting a link on (i) the payoffs of the actors in the link, (ii) the payoffs of actors in neighboring links and (iii) the variance of payoffs in the exchange network. The propositions were examined by applying expected value theory (EVT) to all 13,597 networks up to size 8. All propositions were falsified. Some falsifications of propositions could be attributed to EVTs prediction that actors use sub-optimal exchange relations. Since other well-known theories of exchange, like power-dependence theory and network exchange theory, also predict that actors use sub-optimal relations, these results are robust to selection of the theory of exchange. 
WOS:000246430600007
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="47">
<title>Clearing the FOG: Fuzzy, overlapping groups for social networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2008.03.001</url>
<snippet>Humans are well known to belong to many associative groups simultaneously, with various levels of affiliation. However, most group detection algorithms for social networks impose a strict partitioning on nodes, forcing entities to belong to a single group. Link analysis research has produced several methods which detect multiple memberships but force equal membership. This paper extends these approaches by introducing the FOG framework, a stochastic model and group detection algorithm for fuzzy, overlapping groups. We apply our algorithm to both link data and network data, where we use a random walk approach to generate rich links from networks. The results demonstrate that not only can fuzzy groups be located, but also that the strength of membership in a group and the fraction of individuals with exclusive membership are highly informative of emerging group dynamics. 
WOS:000257568200003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="48">
<title>The structure of educational research: The role of multivocality in promoting cohesion in an article interlock network</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2007.08.001</url>
<snippet>Researchers interested in the social and intellectual features of scholarly knowledge have emphasized the importance of small-scale, informally organized groups of people interested in the same or closely related research problems. The structure of these social networks, in large part, influences the way which research problems are identified, studied and transformed into policy. Building on popular concerns about the state of the educational research field, this study examines what its structure implies about the fields ability to integrate ideas and practices. Using data about which articles readers access from the online database of the Teachers College Record, one of the fields more popular journals, it is shown that the article interlock network exhibits a structure that fits parameters of both small-world and structurally cohesive models. Furthermore, this study unpacks the networks community structure to show that those articles that serve as the core through which much of the network is connected possess a multivocal identity; an ambiguous identity that appeals to multiple audiences simultaneously. Results are suggestive of mechanisms that could be used to promote greater cohesion across the networks distinct communities. (C) 2007 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000253735700006
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="49">
<title>Node centrality in weighted networks: Generalizing degree and shortest paths</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2010.03.006</url>
<snippet>Ties often have a strength naturally associated with them that differentiate them from each other. Tie strength has been operationalized as weights. A few network measures have been proposed for weighted networks, including three common measures of node centrality: degree, closeness, and betweenness. However, these generalizations have solely focused on tie weights, and not on the number of ties, which was the central component of the original measures. This paper proposes generalizations that combine both these aspects. We illustrate the benefits of this approach by applying one of them to Freemans EIES dataset. (C) 2010 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000279409000009
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="50">
<title>An introduction to exponential random graph (&lt;i&gt;p*&lt;/i&gt;) models for social networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2006.08.002</url>
<snippet>This article provides an introductory summary to the formulation and application of exponential random graph models for social networks. The possible ties among nodes of a network are regarded as random variables, and assumptions about dependencies among these random tie variables determine the general form of the exponential random graph model for the network. Examples of different dependence assumptions and their associated models are given, including Bernoulli, dyad-independent and Markov random graph models. The incorporation of actor attributes in social selection models is also reviewed. Newer, more complex dependence assumptions are briefly outlined. Estimation procedures are discussed, including new methods for Monte Carlo maximum likelihood estimation. We foreshadow the discussion taken up in other papers in this special edition: that the homogeneous Markov random graph models of Frank and Strauss [Frank, O., Strauss, D., 1986. Markov graphs. Journal of the American Statistical Association 81, 832-842] are not appropriate for many observed networks, whereas the new model specifications of Snijders et al. [Snijders, T.A.B., Pattison, P., Robins, G.L., Handock, M. New specifications for exponential random graph models. Sociological Methodology, in press] offer substantial improvement. 
WOS:000246430600002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="51">
<title>A new method for finding hierarchical subgroups from networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2010.03.005</url>
<snippet>We present a new method for decomposing a social network into an optimal number of hierarchical subgroups. With a perfect hierarchical subgroup defined as one in which every member is automorphically equivalent to each other, the method uses the REGGE algorithm to measure the similarities among nodes and applies the k-means method to group the nodes that have congruent profiles of dissimilarities with other nodes into various numbers of hierarchical subgroups. The best number of subgroups is determined by minimizing the intra-cluster variance of dissimilarity subject to the constraint that the improvement in going to more subgroups is better than a network whose n nodes are maximally dispersed in the n-dimensional space would achieve. We also describe a decomposability metric that assesses the deviation of a real network from the ideal one that contains only perfect hierarchical subgroups. Four well known network data sets are used to demonstrate the method and metric. These demonstrations indicate the utility of our approach and suggest how it can be used in a complementary way to Generalized Blockmodeling for hierarchical decomposition. (C) 2010 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000279409000008
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="52">
<title>Actor network utilities and network evolution</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2005.05.002</url>
<snippet>Considerable attention has been devoted to the evolution of social networks through time. Some has been descriptive, some has sought fundamental principles for studying network evolution and some has been analytical. The work described in this paper represents all three approaches and is cast within the framework of rational choice theory. One foundation is found in the work of Jackson and Wolinsky [JW] [Jackson, M.O., Wolinsky, A., 1996. A strategic model of social and economic networks, Journal of Economic Theory, 71, 44-74] who consider actors having some calculus for the costs of maintaining social ties and the benefits received by virtue of being located in a network of ties. By parameterizing the costs and benefits, they derived equilibrium structures under specified combinations of parameters when ties arc formed by rational actors. The second foundation is found in the simulations of Hummon [Hummon, N.P., 2000. Utility and Dynamic Social Networks, Social Networks, 22, 221-249.] that were based on the JW work. Hummon found that there were equilibrium structures that were not anticipated in the formal analyses of JW. To resolve this discrepancy, using networks with a fixed set of vertices and using the JW framework, this paper explores the transitions between networks on the lattices of all graphs with a fixed number of vertices through the addition and deletion of ties. While these transitions can be described, a close examination of them reveals the equilibrium structures anticipated by JW, the equilibrium structures located by the Hummon simulations, plus some other equilibria. Modified theorems for the equilibria forms are presented together with a generalization of the equilibrium concept. 
WOS:000236007800003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="53">
<title>Capturing context: Integrating spatial and social network analyses</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2011.10.007</url>
<snippet>
WOS:000300131600001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="54">
<title>Triadic configurations in limited choice sociometric networks: Empirical and theoretical results</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2008.04.002</url>
<snippet>Previous research demonstrated that information contained in triad censuses from heterogeneous collections of social networks occupies a high dimensional space. Regions of this space, and locations of triad censuses within it, are largely defined by lower order network properties: network density and dyad distributions [Faust, K., 2006. Comparing social networks: size, density, and local structure. Metodoloski Zvezki (Advances in Methodology and Statistics) 3 (2), 185-216: Faust, K., 2007. Very local structure in social networks. Sociological Methodology 37, 209-256]. The Current paper extends comparative work on triad censuses by addressing three related issues. First, it determines and interprets the space occupied by triad censuses for 128 friendship networks gathered using a limited choice sociometric protocol. Second, it constructs a theoretical space for triad censuses expected given lower order graph properties and examines the dimensionality and shape of this space. Third, it brings together these lines of investigation to determine where the empirical triad censuses reside within the theoretical space. Results show that the empirical triad censuses are almost perfectly represented in one dimension (explaining 99&#37; of the data) and that network density explains over 96&#37; of the variance in locations on this dimension. In contrast, the theoretical space for triad censuses is at least four-dimensional, with distinctive regions defined by network density and dyad distributions. Within this theoretical space, the empirical triad censuses occupy a restricted region that closely tracks triad censuses expected given network density. Results differ markedly from prior findings that the space occupied by triad censuses from heterogeneous social networks is of high dimensionality. Results also reinforce observations about constraints that network size and density place on graph level indices. (C) 2008 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000260367400001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="55">
<title>Social networkers: Measuring and examining individual differences in propensity to connect with others</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2008.04.003</url>
<snippet>The research examined individual differences in peoples propensity to connect with others (PCO). A measure of PCO, with components for making friends (strong ties), making acquaintances (weak ties), and joining others (bridging ties), was developed and tested in two studies involving 144 undergraduates and 197 health-care employees. PCO and its components were significantly positively associated with social network characteristics (including size, betweenness centrality, and brokerage) and indicators of personal adjustment including support received. attainment, well-being, influence, and suggestion-making. PCO had effects beyond those of major personality traits, and PCO components displayed distinctive relationships with work network characteristics. (C) 2008 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000260367400002
</snippet>
</document>

</searchresult>
