<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<searchresult>
<query>Global</query>
<document id="1">
<title>Reliability and validity of egocentered network data collected via web - A meta-analysis of multilevel multitrait, multimethod studies</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2005.07.006</url>
<snippet>Our goal in this article is to assess reliability and validity of egocentered network data collected through web surveys using multilevel confirmatory factor analysis under the multitrait multimethod approach. In this study, we analyze a questionnaire of social support of Ph.D. students in three European countries. The traits used are the frequency of social contact questions. The methods used are web survey design variants. We consider egocentered network data as hierarchical; therefore, a multilevel analysis is required. Within and between-ego reliabilities and validities are defined and interpreted. Afterwards, we proceed to a meta-analysis of the results of the three countries where within and between-ego validities and reliabilities are predicted from survey design variables which have to do with question order (by questions or by alters), response category labels (end labels or all labels) and lay-out of the questionnaire (graphical display or plain text). Results show that question order by questions, all-labeled response categories and a graphical display lay-out with images lead to a better data quality. Our basic approach consisting on multilevel and meta-analysis can be applied to evaluate the quality of any type of egocentered network questionnaire, regardless of the data collection mode. 
WOS:000238117100002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="2">
<title>Too much investment in social capital?</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2004.01.009</url>
<snippet>
WOS:000221206000005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="3">
<title>A measure of betweenness centrality based on random walks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2004.11.009</url>
<snippet>Betweenness is a measure of the centrality of a node in a network, and is normally calculated as the fraction of shortest paths between node pairs that pass through the node of interest. Betweenness is, in some sense, a measure of the influence a node has over the spread of information through the network. By counting only shortest paths, however, the conventional definition implicitly assumes that information spreads only along those shortest paths. Here, we propose a betweenness measure that relaxes this assumption, including contributions from essentially all paths between nodes, not just the shortest, although it still gives more weight to short paths. The measure is based on random walks, counting how often a node is traversed by a random walk between two other nodes. We show how our measure can be calculated using matrix methods, and give some examples of its application to particular networks. (C) 2004 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000227500500003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="4">
<title>The motivational foundation of social networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0378-8733(01)00052-1</url>
<snippet>The origins of motivations for network behavior are found in modem theories of early childhood development. There are two types of early motivations: safety on the one hand and efficacy on the other. Safety corresponds to and is generated by networks of cohesion, while efficacy comes about from separation and corresponds to networks with structural holes and is typical of brokerage situations. Both cohesion and brokerage are necessarily involved in any network situation as a matter of fundamental theoretical necessity, but they occur under different circumstances in individual and organizational action. Studies axe reviewed that show that effective relations both within and between organizations require both cohesive bases and brokerage between otherwise not well connected units. (C) 2002 Elsevier Science B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000174169100004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="5">
<title>Social structure and support networks in Beijing and Hong Kong</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2005.04.001</url>
<snippet>This study examines personal support networks in Beijing and Hong Kong, based on survey data collected in 2000. It was found that these two Chinese cities, which share a common Confucian cultural heritage, are similar in many aspects of social support. The supportive roles of spouse or partner are prominent and diffuse. Other close relatives are more involved in instrumental than emotional support. Non-kin primary ties specialize in emotional support. Neither extended kin support nor institutional support is significant. Nonetheless, the two cities differ in certain aspects of social support, reflecting their differences in such macro social-structural forces as economic modernization, urbanization and the social organization of work. Compared to the Hong Kong Chinese, the Beijing Chinese are more likely to seek support from close kin or coworkers, but less likely to rely on institutional help. Sources of support in both cities are also affected by the micro social-structural positions people occupy, particularly marital status and household income. It is noted that about 10&#37; of the respondents in both cities reported "no one" to turn to for support. Among the various types of support, emotional comfort is the most difficult to find. 
WOS:000230256300005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="6">
<title>Bridge decay</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0378-8733(02)00017-5</url>
<snippet>This paper is about three points: network bridges are critical to the advantage known as social capital, bridges relative to other kinds of relationships show faster rates of decay over time, and the faster decay in bridges has implications for the stability of social capital. A bridge connects people not otherwise connected; in other words, it spans a structural hole in the surrounding organization. I have 4 years of data on the social networks of bankers in a large organization. I show that bridge relations are associated with more positive peer reputations and higher compensation, but bridges decay at an alarming rate. Out of 10, 9 bridges this year are gone next year. I describe factors in the rate of decay, find slower decay in the networks of bankers experienced with bridge relationships, and conclude that social capital accrues to those who already have it. An appendix is included on the kinked decay functions observed in contractual bridge relationships. (C) 2002 Elsevier Science B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000177947300003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="7">
<title>Relational instability at the network core: Support dynamics in developmental networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2005.04.003</url>
<snippet>We present a descriptive model of developmental networks - interpersonal ties who take an active interest in and concerted action to advance ones career - and argue that both network structure and relational content are necessary for understanding how individuals receive early career support. By following 77 MBA graduates over three time periods (N=977 ties), we find evidence for an inner-outer core network structure in which ties providing high psychosocial support and low career support populate the inner core. 
WOS:000235101000003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="8">
<title>The sexual organization of the city</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2007.01.003</url>
<snippet>
WOS:000246430600013
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="9">
<title>Impact of methods for reducing respondent burden on personal network structural measures</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2006.12.005</url>
<snippet>We examine methods for reducing respondent burden in evaluating alter-alter ties on a set of network structural measures. The data consist of two sets, each containing 45 alters from respondent free lists: the first contains 447 personal networks, and the second 554. Respondents evaluated the communication between 990 alter pairs. The methods were (1) dropping alters from the end of the free-list, (2) randomly dropping alters, (3) randomly dropping links, and (4) predicting ties based on transitivity. For some measures network structure is captured with samples of less than 20 alters; other measures are less consistent. Researchers should be aware of the need to sample a minimum number of alters to capture structural variation. 
WOS:000246430600009
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="10">
<title>Diversity in social support by role relations: A typology</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2005.10.001</url>
<snippet>Social support is fundamental for social integration and emotional well-being. One aspect of social support that is often the focus of attention is the size of a persons support network. However, additional complex measures of social support are necessary to capture qualitative aspects of support networks, such as the diversity in types of support available from specific types of alters. This paper presents a simple way to acquire this comprehensive information and a condensed way to represent the complexity of a persons support network so this information can easily be included in classic survey analyses. Log-linear latent class analysis is used to construct a typology of ego-centric support networks showing the types of support respondents can expect from alters with a specific role. Depending on the role relation for the five support items, this diversity can adequately be represented by distinguishing 2-4 types of respondents. For the role relation friends, we can differentiate between respondents who expect only companionship from their friends, those expecting emotional support as well as companionship, and respondents expecting no social support at all from their friends. For immediate kin, we find those with only emotional support, those with emotional and instrumental support, those with all types of support, and finally a group of respondents expecting no support at all from immediate kin. The approach presented in this article enables a more detailed measurement of the dimensions of social support contents by managing to compile the diversity by distinguishing types of respondents. Such typologies can easily be used as explanatory variables in subsequent analyses. 
WOS:000240890700008
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="11">
<title>Persistence of close personal ties over a 12-year period</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2005.07.008</url>
<snippet>Using data on 60 intentional communities from the Urban Communes Data Set, we examine factors related to the persistence of ties 12 years later, when nearly all members had left the groups. We find strong evidence of triadic effects-people are more likely to remain in contact with others when they share patterns of contact with third parties. Such triadic effects retain importance even when we use alternative measures of contact, and when we control for individual-, dyadic-, and group-level effects including geographic separation. When we examine friendship as opposed to contact, we find that the triadic effects can be decomposed into some effects pertaining to hierarchy and other effects pertaining to reciprocation, giving us a sense of how networks structure themselves over time. 
WOS:000240890700004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="12">
<title>Structural properties of work groups and their consequences for performance</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0378-8733(02)00049-7</url>
<snippet>Over the past several decades, social network research has favored either ego-centric (e.g. employee) or bounded networks (e.g. organization) as the primary unit of analysis. This paper revitalizes a focus on the work group, which includes structural properties of both its individual members and the collection as a whole. In a study of 182 work groups in a global organization, we found that structural holes of leaders within groups as well as core-periphery and hierarchical group structures were negatively associated with performance. We show that these effects hold even after controlling for mean levels of group communication, and discuss implications for the future of network analysis in work groups and informal organizations. (C) 2003 Elsevier Science B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000184386200001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="13">
<title>Measuring personal networks with daily contacts: a single-item survey question and the contact diary</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2005.01.008</url>
<snippet>This paper examines two extreme approaches that are alternatives to measure egocentric networks with network generators. The single-item approach to measure daily contacts differentiates the individuals effectively, corresponds closely with complex network measures, and reveals well how individuals vary in both expressive and instrumental returns, as supported by 14 large-scale probability surveys from three Chinese societies over a decade. This paper also draws upon three sets of sophisticated contact diaries, which yielded rich data about the circumstance of each contact, the alters characteristics and the ego-alter relationship. Along with the diary approach, which offers sophisticated data about contacts, ties and networks, the single-item survey approach is another extreme yet straightforward measure of daily contacts. 
WOS:000230256300001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="14">
<title>How to search a social network</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2005.01.007</url>
<snippet>We address the question of how participants in a small world experiment are able to find short paths in a social network using only local information about their immediate contacts. We simulate such experiments on a network of actual email contacts within an organization as well as on a student social networking website. On the email network we find that small world search strategies using a contact's position in physical space or in an organizational hierarchy relative to the target can effectively be used to locate most individuals. However, we find that in the online student network, where the data is incomplete and hierarchical structures are not well defined, local search strategies are less effective. We compare our findings to recent theoretical hypotheses about underlying social structure that would enable these simple search strategies to succeed and discuss the implications to social software design. 
WOS:000230256300002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="15">
<title>Measuring social networks cross-culturally</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2005.07.007</url>
<snippet>This paper explores the reliability and validity of a cross-cultural survey approach to network measurement using data from two ethnic groups in rural West Africa. Over a 2-week test-retest period, no significant differences in network size were detected. Network composition was less stable over the same period, particularly among peripheral versus core network members. Comparisons with support networks identified through lifecycle interviews and 24 h recall support the construct validity of the survey approach in both ethnic groups. 
WOS:000240890700005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="16">
<title>Partner naming and forgetting: Recall of network members</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2006.12.004</url>
<snippet>Network researchers must contend with recall, forgetting, alters whose names are not known, and other potential biases in estimating the size of personal (ego) networks. We use data from a longitudinal study of sexual and drug use ego networks. Results show 6&#37; forgetting for 30-day sex partners, 18&#37; for drug use partners, and 26&#37; for close friends. Forgetting is decreased by behavioral specificity and salience. Forgetting increases with network size and time frame. In the domain of sex relationships, global estimates of network size, at least over a period of 30 days, are equivalent to estimates from partner naming 92&#37; of the time if anonymous partners are accounted for. 
WOS:000246430600008
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="17">
<title>Social networks and loss of capital</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2004.01.004</url>
<snippet>Economic sociologists and white-collar criminologists offer competing predictions about the outcomes of socially embedded transactions. Economic sociologists stress the protective and beneficial role of social networks. Their evidence shows that social ties improve transaction outcomes. White-collar criminologists focus on the harmful and exploitative role of social networks. Their evidence shows that social ties facilitate successful economic crimes. Our case permits a critical test of the protective versus harmful effects of social ties: a business that operated as a legitimate enterprise and also engaged in ongoing financial fraud. This case is strategic because the role of social networks ex post is theoretically ambiguous for a legitimate-fraudulent business. Do social networks lower, raise, or have no effect on the probability of loss of capital, given that an investment has been made? The probability of loss of capital depends on due diligence and type of social tie. Investors who fail to conduct due diligence and do not use social ties have a 79&#37; probability of loss of capital, controlling for other factors. Investors who conduct due diligence (and do not use social ties) have a 49&#37; probability. Investors with preexisting social ties to the principals, sales representatives, or employees of the company (and do not conduct due diligence) have a 39&#37; probability of loss, while those with this type of social tie who also conduct due diligence have a 14&#37; probability. Investors with preexisting social ties to prior investors are not significantly more or less likely to lose their capital. Even in a business that was partly fraudulent, preexisting social ties to the company played a protective and beneficial role. Ironically, fraudulent behavior lowered the probability of loss for investors with this type of social tie: Illegal practices allowed the company to favor friends and acquaintances in the ex post allocation of proceeds. (C) 2004 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000221286300001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="18">
<title>Gender differences in the creation of different types of social capital: A multilevel study</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2005.04.002</url>
<snippet>This study examined gender differences in the creation of hard and soft social capital in a sample of 352 female and 486 male faculty members. Men were shown to be more effective in creating hard social capital, but, unexpectedly, women were not found to be the emotional specialists they often are thought to be. Moreover, multilevel analyses indicated that men were more effective in using emotional intensity of ties to create hard social capital, and they were also more effective using team-related resources to create both hard and soft social capital. 
WOS:000235101000002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="19">
<title>The Resource Generator: social capital quantification with concrete</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2004.10.001</url>
<snippet>In research on the social capital of individuals, there has been little standardisation of measurement instruments, and more emphasis on measuring social relationships than on social resources. In this paper, we propose two innovations. First, a new measurement method: the Resource Generator; an instrument with concretely worded items covering general social capital in a population, which combines advantages of earlier techniques. Construction, use, and first empirical findings are discussed for a representative sample (N = 1004) of the Dutch population in 1999-2000. Second, we propose to investigate social capital by latent trait analysis, and we identify four separately accessed portions of social capital: prestige and education related social capital, political and financial skills social capital, personal skills social capital, and personal support social capital. This underlines that social capital measurement needs multiple measures, and cannot be reduced to one total measure of indirectly owned resources. Constructing a theory-based Resource Generator is a challenge for different contexts of use, but also retrieves meaningful information when investigating the productivity and goal specificity of social capital. (C) 2004 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000227500500001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="20">
<title>The distant core: social solidarity, social distance and interpersonal ties in core-periphery structures</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0378-8733(01)00033-8</url>
<snippet>We examine three hypotheses at the foundation of theories concerned with the organization of social space and social solidarity in differentiated groups. The most important of these hypotheses is that interpersonal ties between actors in different positions of a social structure foster social solidarity; however, the theories are silent on the question of whether this effect of interpersonal ties is maintained regardless of the distance that separates the positions of two actors in the groups social space. In addition, the current zeitgeist on the organization of social space hypothesizes that interpersonal solidarity and ties are negatively associated with the distance that separates the positions of actors in social space. Although interpersonal ties foster solidarity, social distance reduces the likelihood of interpersonal ties and solidarity. Our evidence suggests unqualified support only for the first hypothesis. Surprisingly, the expected negative effects of social distance on interpersonal ties and solidarity appear to be properties of particular forms of social organization and are not ubiquitous implications of social differentiation. These negative effects are more or less pronounced (even reversible) in core-periphery structures depending upon the distance between the core and peripheral positions in the social space of the group. (C) 2001 Elsevier Science B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000171391200001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="21">
<title>Effects on reliability and validity of egocentered network measurements</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2005.01.001</url>
<snippet>This paper examines the reliability and validity of egocentered networks. Reliability and validity are estimated by the multitrait-multimethod (MTMM) approach. A split ballot MTMM design [.Saris, W.E., 1999. Forced choice or agree/disagree questions? An evaluation by the split ballot MTMM experiment. In: Proceeding of the Meeting of the IRMCS, pp. 122-146; Kogovsek, T., Ferligoj, A., Coenders, G. Saris, W. E., 2002. Estimating the reliability and validity of personal support measures: full information ml estimation with planned incomplete data. Social Networks 24, 1-20] is used, in which separate groups of respondents received different combinations of two methods. The effect of factors such as the methods used and the personal characteristics of respondents that can affect the quality of data was estimated by a meta analysis. Measurement method, type of question, network size, age, gender, extraversion and emotional stability all had statistically significant effects on the validity of measurement. After the list of alters is obtained with name generators, name interpreter questions can be asked in two ways. One way ("by alters") is to take each alter individually and to ask all the questions about him/her, going alter by alter until the end of the list of alters. The other way ("by questions") is to take the question and ask this question for all alters on the list, going question by question until the end of the list of name interpreter questions. Telephone interviewing (both by alters and by questions) gave more valid measurements than face-to-face interviews. Behavioral questions were more valid than questions with emotional content. The characteristics of ties were more validly measured in smaller networks. With reference to respondents' personal characteristics younger respondents, men, extraverted and emotionally stable respondents all had more valid measurements. Reliability was significantly affected by the measurement method, the type of question and age. The telephone/by alters method was the most reliable measurement method. Behavioral questions were more reliable than questions with emotional content. Measurements among younger respondents were also more reliable. 
WOS:000230256300003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="22">
<title>Detecting measurement bias in respondent reports of personal networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0378-8733(02)00013-8</url>
<snippet>Inaccuracy of sociometric reports poses a serious challenge to social network analysis. Nevertheless, researchers continue to draw potentially misleading conclusions from flawed data. We consider two particular types of systematic error in measurement of network size: individuals over/underreporting others (expansiveness bias), and individuals being over/underreported by others (attractiveness bias). We examine evidence of individual variation in these biases in one apparently typical sociometric dataset. We specifically suggest that variation in expansiveness bias may commonly distort findings concerning characteristics of individual networks (e.g. size, range, density), and properties of whole networks (e.g. inequality, transitivity, clustering, and blockmodels). We suggest methodological improvements and urge further research. (C) 2002 Published by Elsevier Science B.V.
WOS:000177947300004
</snippet>
</document>

</searchresult>
