<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<searchresult>
<query>Global</query>
<document id="1">
<title>More than one's negative ties: The role of friends' antipathies in high school gossip</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.11.009</url>
<snippet>Gossip is universal, and multiple studies have demonstrated that it can have beneficial group-level outcomes when negative reports help identify defectors or norm-violators. Gossip, however, seldom happens in a social vacuum. Instead, it is enmeshed in a fabric of positive and negative relationships that creates opportunities, constraints, and also motives to gossip. This article studies the importance of friendships and antipathies among the three concerned parties (sender, receiver, target) for negative gossip among adolescents. We contrast two theoretical accounts. According to the first, gossip brings closer individuals who have "enemies" in common. Based on this, we infer that gossip appears in triads where both the sender and receiver share their antipathy against the target. The second position argues that gossip is used to compromise different opinions of friends towards the target. Thus, what predicts gossip is direct antipathy against the target or being friends with someone who dislikes the target (indirect antipathy) rather than the combination of the two antipathies. We test these two lines of reasoning with sociometric data from 17 classroom observations (13 unique classrooms in different time points) in Hungary. Bayesian Exponential Random Graph Models yield support for direct antipathy in 13 (nine unique) classrooms and indirect antipathy in five. No evidence for shared antipathy is found. Results suggest that, at least among adolescents, negative gossip is not about bonding with potential allies but more about consensus-making between friends. Also, results reveal that negative gossip concentrates on the two ends of the reputational echelon, hinting that, in the classroom, high reputation might be contested instead of rewarded.
WOS:000724026400003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="2">
<title>Vertical organizations, flat networks: Centrality and criminal collaboration in the Italian-American Mafia</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.06.001</url>
<snippet>While criminal organizations often feature hierarchical positions, scholars debate the extent to which networks of informal collaboration among criminals reflect such hierarchies. This research uses historical data on collaboration involving more than 700 criminals across 24 Italian-American Mafia families and applies network regression models and simulations to determine whether mafiosi of similar centrality-based status were more likely to be criminal associates than mafiosi of dissimilar status. Rather than forming vertical collaborations linking mafia members into a centralized, hierarchical network structure, we find that mafiosi collaborated disproportionately more with colleagues of similar status. While network centrality predicted tie formation, formal rank in an organizational chart generally did not. Knowledge simply of a covert organizations formal structure may not translate to understanding "on-the-ground" collaborations.
WOS:000700623500011
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="3">
<title>The free encyclopedia that anyone can dispute: An analysis of the micro-structural dynamics of positive and negative relations in the production of contentious Wikipedia articles</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2018.12.003</url>
<snippet>We consider two rival hypotheses on the emergence of organization in open production communities. According to the first ("reputation hypothesis"), patterns of agreement and disagreement among participants in open production communities are explained by differences in individual reputation for quality of contribution. The reputation hypothesis predicts that participants will tend to agree with more reputable others and disagree with less reputable others thus contributing to establish a stable open production community. According to the second hypothesis ("balance hypothesis"), patterns of agreement and disagreement are explained by membership in sub-communities of "friends" and "enemies." The balance hypothesis predicts that participants in open production communities will agree mainly with friends and disagree mainly with enemies, regardless of considerations about reputation for the quality of their contributions. In this paper, we examine which one of these hypotheses is more consistent with patterns of positive and negative interaction events observed during the production of the complete set of 1,206 English-language Wikipedia articles officially considered controversial. We specify and estimate new models for signed and weighted relational event networks predicting the probability that a user deletes the contributions of another user - thus expressing personal disagreement - and/or protects the contributions of another user against deletion from third parties - thus expressing personal agreement. In an analysis of positive and negative interaction among Wikipedia contributors consisting of more than 60 million observations, we find strong support for the balance hypothesis and for the predictions of the reputation hypothesis that are more consistent with alter-centric interpretations of social status as conferred by alters through observable acts of deference.
WOS:000501619700002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="4">
<title>"Offending with the accomplices of my accomplices": Evidence and implications regarding triadic closure in co-offending networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.02.013</url>
<snippet>We measured triadic closure in co-offending networks - i.e., the tendency of two individuals to co-offend if they share an accomplice - using a method that addresses the risk of overestimating clustering coefficients when using one-mode projections. We also assess the statistical significance of clustering coefficients using null models. The data relates to adult offenders (N = 274,689) connected to criminal investigations (N = 286,591) in Colombia. The observed coefficients range between 0.05 and 0.53 and are statistically significant, indicating that accomplices become sources of information about potential associates. They support the idea of preventing crime by targeting offenders' trustworthiness and disrupting information flows.
WOS:000793127500002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="5">
<title>Using social network analysis to study crime: Navigating the challenges of criminal justice records (Reprinted from vol 66, pages 50-64, 2021)</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.01.008</url>
<snippet>The use of social network analysis to study groups of offenders engaged in illicit activities such as drug trafficking and terrorism has grown in popularity over the last three decades. Along with such growth, however, researchers have been confronted with a suite of challenges related to the use of data extracted from criminal justice records. In this paper, we review these challenges through a discussion of the extant empirical literature utilizing social network analysis approaches that draw data from the criminal justice system. First, we outline and discuss the different types of data used across this literature. Second, we chronicle the challenges that have emerged across the field of criminal networks via a comprehensive review of the literature. In particular, we draw on the documented experiences of researchers in the field, including our own, and detail "archeological" approaches that future researchers can utilize to adapt and overcome said challenges. The use of criminal justice records can suffer from a number of limitations, mainly with respect to accuracy, validity and reliability. Such data may include errors, both intentional (e.g. aliases, false information) and unintentional (e.g. transcription errors), including missing data. The use of criminal justice records present particular problems with defining the network boundary as the boundary as determined by law enforcement or prosecution agencies may not correspond to the boundary as defined by network members. We conclude by offering a number of recommendations for re-searchers about data collection and preparation when utilizing criminal justice records.
WOS:000777028500007
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="6">
<title>The network of interfamily marriages in 'Ndrangheta</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.08.012</url>
<snippet>A common claim is that mafia families arrange marriages strategically to seal alliances, cement partnerships and enhance cohesion. However, this claim is mainly based on anecdotal evidence and limited case studies. In this paper, by relying on an original database of biographical and relational information on over 4,600 members, we carry out the first large-scale exploratory analysis of the network of interfamily marriages in Ndrangheta. Our analysis shows that this alliance network is polycentric, made up of cohesive subgroups centered around well-connected, powerful families, that occupy different positions in the network. The presence of patterns suggests that marriages in Ndrangheta are possibly the result of family strategies to explore and exploit their power and business. We discuss the implications of these findings for the study of marriages as an organizational instrument.
WOS:000702773800007
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="7">
<title>A hostile reputation: A social network approach to interstate hostility</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.06.004</url>
<snippet>State-level decisions to initiate militarized conflicts are the result of various factors, ranging from geographic proximity to the previous actions of potential foes. However, we know little about how the reputations of hostile actions shape future conflict and whether they vary for different types of country pairs. Through the adoption of a social network perspective, this research examines the role of post-Cold War hostility on the likelihood of future conflicts using the Militarized Interstate Dispute data from the Correlates of War project. We apply temporal exponential random graph models to evaluate whether the previous hostility levels of a country can determine future patterns of interstate conflict. Additionally, we consider how this association varies based on whether a countrys experience with an adversary is direct (a result of previous conflict with the adversary) or indirect (based on extra-dyadic disputes). Consistent with previous research, results suggest that pairs of countries with a direct history of hostile actions are more likely to fight in the future. However, in absence of this shared history, states are less likely to initiate conflict with those that have a particularly hostile or peaceful history, and instead target adversaries with middling levels of previous hostility.
WOS:000828391400001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="8">
<title>The way bullying works: How new ties facilitate the mutual reinforcement of status and bullying in elementary schools</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2018.12.006</url>
<snippet>This study addresses the puzzle how high-status bullies in elementary school are able to maintain high status among their classmates despite bullying (some of) them. The dynamic interplay between bullying and status was studied, focusing on how relational bullying affects the creation, dissolution, and maintenance of status attributions, and vice versa. Longitudinal round-robin peer nomination data were obtained from 82 school classes in 15 Dutch elementary schools (2055 students; 50&#37; boys) followed over three yearly measurements, starting out in grades 2-5 when students were aged 8-11. An age-dependent effect of bullying on the creation of new status attributions was found. Whereas the youngest group punished bullying by a refusal to attribute status to the bully, this turned into a reward of bullying in the oldest groups. Unexpectedly, high-status bullies seemed to avoid continual bullying of the same victims, pointing to explanations of why their status can persist.
WOS:000501619700007
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="9">
<title>Avoidance in action: Negative tie closure in balanced triads among pupils over time</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.03.006</url>
<snippet>We study avoidance tie closure in balance triads among pupils in two Dutch secondary schools using stochastic actor-oriented models (SAOMs). We find that pupils were likely to avoid the friends of those they avoided but not enough evidence is found to either fully accept or refute the idea that pupils disagree with their friends on whom to avoid. Moreover, pupils migration background does not seem to influence avoidance tie closure in balanced triads. Results are discussed in terms of their theoretical implications. Based on our findings, we elaborate on the possibility of a singular balance promoting effect rather than multiple distinct ones. Limitations are pointed out and future research suggestions are offered.
WOS:000798769300002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="10">
<title>Dynamics and disruption: Structural and individual changes in two Dutch Jihadi networks after police interventions</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.04.001</url>
<snippet>Longitudinal studies of criminal networks are rare yet necessary to assess the adaptation and recovery of criminal networks after disruptions. We study the structural and individual effects of law enforcement disruption on criminal networks using longitudinal data on two Dutch jihadi networks (n1 = 57; n2 = 26). We expect that actors in criminal networks under disruption seek security and to remain concealed as much as possible. We argue how the structural properties of networks as well as mechanisms operating at the actor level might change after a disruption. We used descriptive measures of network cohesion together with core-periphery model fit and modularity to analyse the structural changes in the networks. To obtain the actor-level tendencies, we used undirected stochastic actor oriented models. At the structural level, both networks display opposite tendencies - the larger one is becoming less cohesive after the disruption, whereas the smaller network counter-intuitively becomes structurally more cohesive. Despite the structural differences, the actor-level mechanisms are similar in both studied networks with actors being inclined towards triadic closure and reliance on pre-existing ties. Our study demonstrates the importance of considering the analytical levels of networks and actors by showing that a disruption may disrupt the network at the structural level, while triggering contradictory unintended consequences by increasing individual-level connectivity as in the case of our second network.
WOS:000802754200001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="11">
<title>Studying organized crime networks: Data sources, boundaries and the limits of structural measures</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.03.002</url>
<snippet>Network studies of organized crime (OC) normally explore two key relational issues: the internal structure of groups and the interactions among groups. The paper first discusses in depth two data sources that have been used to address these questions - phone wiretaps and police-generated "events"- and reviews issues of validity, reliability and sampling. Next, it discusses challenges related to OC network data in general, focusing on the double boundary specification problem and the time span of data collection. We conclude by arguing that structural analysis cannot be divorced from a deep contextual (qualitative) knowledge of the cases. The paper refers to concrete research dilemmas and solutions faced by scholars, including ourselves.
WOS:000777556900014
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="12">
<title>Key aspects of covert networks data collection: Problems, challenges, and opportunities</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2019.10.002</url>
<snippet>Data quality is considered to be among the greatest challenges in research on covert networks. This study identifies six aspects of network data collection, namely nodes, ties, attributes, levels, dynamics, and context. Addressing these aspects presents challenges, but also opens theoretical and methodological opportunities. Furthermore, specific issues arise in this research context, stemming from the use of secondary data and the problem of missing data. While each of the issues and challenges has some specific solution in the literature on organized crime and social networks, the main argument of this paper is to try and follow a more systematic and general solution to deal with these issues. To this end, three potentially synergistic and combinable techniques for data collection are proposed for each stage of data collection - biographies for data extraction, graph databases for data storage, and checklists for data reporting. The paper concludes with discussing the use of statistical models to analyse covert networks and the cultivation of relations within the research community and between researchers and practitioners.
WOS:000777028500001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="13">
<title>The coevolution of trade agreements and investment treaties: Some evidence from network analysis</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2019.08.005</url>
<snippet>Regional trade agreements (RTAs) and bilateral investment treaties (BITs) are expected to promote trade and investment relationships. One critical feature of such agreements is the network, so the multiplex coevolution of RTAs and BITs should be captured by the dynamics of their two networks. Although many studies have examined the roles of RTAs and BITs, most studies do not account for crucial network properties. This study explores how RTAs and BITs coevolve by applying a stochastic actor-oriented model of multiplex network evolution. In particular, we examine the roles of (i) cross-network dyadic interinfluences and (ii) within- and cross-network preferential attachments to discuss the dynamic relationships between RTAs and BITs. The results are as follows. First, our estimation supports cross-network dyadic interinfluences. Countries that sign a BIT are willing to establish an RTA, while those that sign an RTA are reluctant to establish a BIT. Second, concerning preferential attachments, countries prefer to sign BITs with partners that have more RTA and BIT links. However, countries tend to form RTAs with partners that have more BIT links but are reluctant to form RTAs with those that have more RTA links. We discuss possible justifications for these results, including arguments regarding the benefits and costs associated with the formation of RTAs and BITs.
WOS:000512481500004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="14">
<title>The contagion of democracy through international networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2019.08.009</url>
<snippet>Work on democratization typically considers the diffusion of democracy through interstate partnerships. However, such partnerships constitute complex networks that scholars have yet to fully explore as vectors for the spread of democracy. We develop a network theory of democratization which characterizes these networks as epistemic communities that influence elites attitudes towards favorable regime types. Our theory predicts, and our empirical strategy confirms, that direct and indirect ties in the alliance network are vectors for democratization. In contrast to conventional wisdom, we find that direct influence is only transmitted through the defensive alliance network and find evidence of higher-order effects.
WOS:000512481500008
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="15">
<title>How social ties transcend class boundaries? Network variability as tool for exploring occupational homophily</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.02.003</url>
<snippet>The research on social network analysis established the existence of class homophily, the tendency that personal networks are homogeneous in the class sense, as one of the governing patterns. This is explained via two main mechanisms: choice homophily and induced homophily. But the literature focused less on the question how can class boundaries be transgressed and what are the channels of class heterophily. This paper explores class heterophily on Croatian data acquired through position generator, which measures social capital (resources captured in social relations) by exploring the range of different occupational positions which are accessible to an individual (extensity index). Network variability is thereby taken as proxy for class composition of personal networks. The paper concludes that that political participation and sociability enable cross-class ties, since this offers an opportunity to meet and befriend people from all walks of life; and that people on the middle of the social hierarchy have the most diverse social networks. The hypotheses that social mobility can represent a vehicle for class heterophily; and that class heterophily is more pronounced in smaller settlements, where society networks show more overlap between social circles; were confirmed only partially, and require further investigation. These findings concern class boundaries related to the notion of choice homophily. As for induced homophily, the paper concludes that here too the boundaries are not watertight, as cultural omnivores have a wider range of class contacts.
WOS:000527272000004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="16">
<title>Charting the hidden City: Collecting prison social network data</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2019.09.005</url>
<snippet>Penologists have long emphasized the importance of studying social relationships among prisoners to understand how people adapt to confinement. While several penological traditions clearly implicate social networks as an explanatory mechanism, network methods have rarely been applied in prison research. We suspect that prison scholars have been slow to incorporate social networks into their research because of the challenges-both real and perceived-of collecting social network data in the prison setting. In this article, we argue that successfully collecting network data from prisoners can be achieved by carefully adapting methods to the peculiarities and constraints of the prison setting. We draw upon experiences from the Prison Inmate Networks Study (PINS) and its associated projects in five Pennsylvania prisons to construct a framework for understanding and overcoming the obstacles to network data collection in prisons.
WOS:000777028500002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="17">
<title>Non-parametric estimation of reciprocity and triadic effects in relational event networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.08.004</url>
<snippet>Relational event networks arise naturally from social interactions: interactions can be considered time-stamped edges between vertices of social actors. By studying the factors that influence the interaction inter-arrival times we can get insight in the drivers of interaction dynamics. Relational event models provide a succinct way to analyse a broad family of interactional patterns and their influence on network dynamics. These models can easily incorporate a wide range of mechanisms involving both endogenous and exogenous network effects. It has been typical for quantitive models to assume that endogenous network mechanisms, such as reciprocity or triadic effects, remain stable over time. However, a number of studies argued that reciprocity has a strong tendency to decay over time. This paper proposes to model the dynamic structure of reciprocal and triadic effects in relational event networks via stratified baseline hazards. This avoids having to define arbitrary temporal windows for what can be considered reciprocity or triadic closure. A two-step estimation framework is used, based on the stratified Cox proportional hazards model, followed by non-parametric estimation of the stratified cumulative hazard functions. This framework is illustrated by a simulation study and its application to two studies involving email communication and classroom interactions.
WOS:000702773800005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="18">
<title>Keeping to the code: How local norms of friendship and dating inform macro-structures of adolescents' romantic networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.11.012</url>
<snippet>Even though romantic partnerships are often understood as pairwise relationships, there is value in conceptualizing the dating patterns of adolescents as network phenomena, particularly as related to the spread of sexually transmitted infections. The current study adopts this perspective to evaluate how a local norm guiding the coexistence of dating and friendship informs macro-level romantic network structures. Using twelve months of romantic relationship data from the Peers and the Emergence of Adolescent Romance (PEAR) study, we find that the global dating network resembles a chain-like, spanning tree structure consistent with that observed by Bearman and colleagues (2004)in their foundational study. Then, through the application of temporal ERGMs, we uncover evidence that adolescents adhere to a social norm against dating their friends previous romantic partners. We use these findings to empirically ground a series of network simulations, which demonstrate that the romantic networks structure becomes less redundant and more clustered as the norm against dating friends previous partners is relaxed. By understanding how local norms shape patterns of friendship and dating, we can better conceptualize the macro-level structural patterns of romantic networks and their implications for infectious disease diffusion.
WOS:000819930800004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="19">
<title>Network sampling coverage III: Imputation of missing network data under different network and missing data conditions</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.05.002</url>
<snippet>Missing data is a common, difficult problem for network studies. Unfortunately, there are few clear guidelines about what a researcher should do when faced with incomplete information. We take up this problem in the third paper of a three-paper series on missing network data. Here, we compare the performance of different imputation methods across a wide range of circumstances characterized in terms of measures, networks and missing data types. We consider a number of imputation methods, going from simple imputation to more complex modelbased approaches. Overall, we find that listwise deletion is almost always the worst option, while choosing the best strategy can be difficult, as it depends on the type of missing data, the type of network and the measure of interest. We end the paper by offering a set of practical outputs that researchers can use to identify the best imputation choice for their particular research setting.
WOS:000700623500013
</snippet>
</document>

</searchresult>
