<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<searchresult>
<query>Global</query>
<document id="1">
<title>ACCESS TO OCCUPATIONS THROUGH SOCIAL TIES</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0378-8733(86)90003-1</url>
<snippet>
WOS:A1986F332300003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="2">
<title>A NOTE ON SOCIOMETRIC ORDER IN THE GENERAL SOCIAL SURVEY NETWORK DATA</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0378-8733(86)80002-8</url>
<snippet>
WOS:A1986C737500002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="3">
<title>NAME GENERATORS IN SURVEYS OF PERSONAL NETWORKS</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0378-8733(91)90006-F</url>
<snippet>To investigate the consequences of name generators for network data, we compare characteristics of egocentric networks from Wellmans East York survey, Fischers Northern California Communities Study, the General Social Survey, and our study of networks in 81 Nashville, Tennessee neighborhoods. Network size, age and education heterogeneity, and average tie characteristics were most strongly affected by the name generator used. Network composition, and racial and sexual heterogeneity, were more invariant across different kinds of name generators.
WOS:A1991GW01000001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="4">
<title>SOCIAL RESOURCES AND SOCIOECONOMIC-STATUS</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0378-8733(86)80017-X</url>
<snippet>
WOS:A1986C312000005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="5">
<title>HOMOGENEITY IN CONFIDING RELATIONS</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0378-8733(88)90010-X</url>
<snippet>
WOS:A1988P565500003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="6">
<title>MEASURING AGE AS A STRUCTURAL CONCEPT</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0378-8733(91)90011-H</url>
<snippet>
WOS:A1991FY71900001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="7">
<title>A NOTE ON STRANGERS, FRIENDS AND HAPPINESS</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0378-8733(87)90002-5</url>
<snippet>
WOS:A1987M626800002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="8">
<title>ESTIMATING RELATIONAL ATTRIBUTES FROM SNOWBALL SAMPLES THROUGH SIMULATION</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0378-8733(89)90009-9</url>
<snippet>
WOS:A1989AL14200002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="9">
<title>NETWORK RANGE IN PERSONAL NETWORKS</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0378-8733(90)90009-X</url>
<snippet>
WOS:A1990EF81800005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="10">
<title>THE RELIABILITY OF NETWORK DENSITY AND COMPOSITION MEASURES</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0378-8733(93)90014-C</url>
<snippet>
WOS:A1993MN52100004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="11">
<title>THEORETICAL AND METHODOLOGICAL MODELS OF NETWORKS AND RELATIONS</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0378-8733(91)90009-I</url>
<snippet>Biased net models developed to formalize Blaus macro-level distributional theory of social structure are extended to cover the micro-level analysis of intrapopulation variation in intergroup relations. The relational data analyzed are counts of relations (e.g., marriages, friendships) which are crossclassified by the social characteristics of the partners (e.g., occupation, religious preference). This theoretically based analytical approach is contrasted with a methodologically based one which uses general log-linear models to analyze the pattern of inter- and intragroup relations in such data. Both nominal and graduated dimensions of social differentiation are used in the comparison. Results indicate that, by and large, the theoretical approach offers a viable, and appropriately specialized alternative to the methodologically based analysis.
WOS:A1991GW01000004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="12">
<title>A NOTE ON SCALING THE GENERAL SOCIAL SURVEY NETWORK ITEM RESPONSE CATEGORIES</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0378-8733(86)90004-3</url>
<snippet>
WOS:A1986F332300004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="13">
<title>SOCIAL NETWORKS, MARITAL-STATUS, AND WELL-BEING</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0378-8733(93)90010-I</url>
<snippet>Recent research demonstrates both the role social networks play in well-being through the provision of social support and the connection between marital status and well-being. Research has also demonstrated that networks serve as resources through the provision of instrumental aid. In this paper, we build upon these literatures by asking whether the form and composition of social networks affect well-being and whether these effects vary contextually by marital status. Using multiple indicators of life satisfaction and anomia, we find that social networks do affect both aspects of well-being, and that the effects of network structure on life satisfaction differ across marital status. The pattern of these effects suggests that different structural positions (e.g. marital statuses) produce a need for different types of resources. We find no contextual effects on the relationship between network structure and anomia, however.
WOS:A1993MA39900005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="14">
<title>MEASURING A LARGE NETWORK QUICKLY</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0378-8733(94)90001-9</url>
<snippet>We describe work in which we used three days of interviewing to identify and measure the network among 200 people significant in a complex production process. The capture-recapture strategy should be useful in other settings: (1) Conduct survey network interviews with people (informants) positioned in the study population such that their contacts overlap to provide recaptured relations. (2) Estimate reliability from data consistency across recaptures. (3) Triangulate relation response categories to assign quantitative scores to the categories. (4) Use reliability correlates to weight recaptured relations in the final network pooled across interviews. (5) Extrapolate from the known strengths of the captured relations to define the uncaptured relations.
WOS:A1994NG53300001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="15">
<title>SMALL NETWORKS AND SELECTIVITY BIAS IN THE ANALYSIS OF SURVEY NETWORK DATA</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0378-8733(87)90003-7</url>
<snippet>
WOS:A1987M626800003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="16">
<title>THE COMPONENTS OF STRONG TIES AMONG HOMELESS WOMEN</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0378-8733(87)90016-5</url>
<snippet>
WOS:A1987H247300002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="17">
<title>THE EFFECT OF NETWORK DENSITY AND HOMOGENEITY ON ATTITUDE POLARIZATION</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0378-8733(90)90003-R</url>
<snippet>
WOS:A1990DU34500003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="18">
<title>A NOTE ON THE GENERAL SOCIAL SURVEYS ERSATZ NETWORK DENSITY ITEM</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0378-8733(87)90019-0</url>
<snippet>
WOS:A1987H247300005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="19">
<title>HOW MUCH OF A NETWORK DOES THE GSS AND RSW DREDGE UP</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0378-8733(87)90017-7</url>
<snippet>
WOS:A1987H247300003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="20">
<title>INTEGRATING INDIVIDUAL, RELATIONAL AND STRUCTURAL-ANALYSIS</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0378-8733(91)90007-G</url>
<snippet>The first part of this paper presents a statistical model which integrates individual, relational and network data, despite their different units of analysis. The model uses a stepwise approach to find the least number of parameters which adequately fit the data. The second part of this paper uses this model to analyze how the marital status of Torontonians is related to the kinship composition and social density of their intimate networks. It shows that kinship and friendship usually comprise independent social circles within these networks. The larger networks of married respondents tend to contain a higher proportion of kin, and consequently, to be more densely-knit. Yet single respondents tend to have more densely-knit clusters of intimates within their friendship-based networks. This is because marriage rarely joins the intimates of spouses.
WOS:A1991GW01000002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="21">
<title>THE IMPACT OF SOCIAL AND HUMAN-CAPITAL ON THE INCOME ATTAINMENT OF DUTCH MANAGERS</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0378-8733(91)90013-J</url>
<snippet>
WOS:A1991FY71900003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="22">
<title>COHESION, EQUIVALENCE, AND SIMILARITY OF BEHAVIOR - A THEORETICAL AND EMPIRICAL-ASSESSMENT</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0378-8733(93)90009-A</url>
<snippet>Network analysts have debated the extent to which cohesion versus structural equivalence serves as a source of similar behavior among actors. More recently, role equivalence has emerged as an alternative to structural equivalence. Using data on the contribution patterns of corporate political action committees, I examine the effect of various indicators of cohesion, structural equivalence, and role equivalence on the extent to which firms behave similarly. Although various operationalizations of all three concepts are correlated with similar behavior, the most consistent predictor is the joint prominence of two firms in the network. I argue that this common location in central positions is a form of role equivalence, but one that is distinct from conventional definitions of the concept. I then suggest a distinction between what I term central and peripheral role equivalence.
WOS:A1993MA39900004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="23">
<title>AN EGOCENTRIC NETWORK TALE - COMMENT</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0378-8733(93)90015-D</url>
<snippet>The record is set straight as to who did what in the earlier days of egocentric network analysis - Toronto style.
WOS:A1993MN52100005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="24">
<title>USING EGOCENTERED NETWORKS IN SURVEY-RESEARCH - A METHODOLOGICAL PREVIEW ON AN APPLICATION OF SOCIAL NETWORK ANALYSIS IN THE AREA OF FAMILY RESEARCH</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0378-8733(91)90014-K</url>
<snippet>
WOS:A1991FY71900004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="25">
<title>A NOTE ON MISSING NETWORK DATA IN THE GENERAL SOCIAL SURVEY</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0378-8733(87)90018-9</url>
<snippet>
WOS:A1987H247300004
</snippet>
</document>

</searchresult>
