<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<searchresult>
<query>Global</query>
<document id="1">
<title>More than one's negative ties: The role of friends' antipathies in high school gossip</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.11.009</url>
<snippet>Gossip is universal, and multiple studies have demonstrated that it can have beneficial group-level outcomes when negative reports help identify defectors or norm-violators. Gossip, however, seldom happens in a social vacuum. Instead, it is enmeshed in a fabric of positive and negative relationships that creates opportunities, constraints, and also motives to gossip. This article studies the importance of friendships and antipathies among the three concerned parties (sender, receiver, target) for negative gossip among adolescents. We contrast two theoretical accounts. According to the first, gossip brings closer individuals who have "enemies" in common. Based on this, we infer that gossip appears in triads where both the sender and receiver share their antipathy against the target. The second position argues that gossip is used to compromise different opinions of friends towards the target. Thus, what predicts gossip is direct antipathy against the target or being friends with someone who dislikes the target (indirect antipathy) rather than the combination of the two antipathies. We test these two lines of reasoning with sociometric data from 17 classroom observations (13 unique classrooms in different time points) in Hungary. Bayesian Exponential Random Graph Models yield support for direct antipathy in 13 (nine unique) classrooms and indirect antipathy in five. No evidence for shared antipathy is found. Results suggest that, at least among adolescents, negative gossip is not about bonding with potential allies but more about consensus-making between friends. Also, results reveal that negative gossip concentrates on the two ends of the reputational echelon, hinting that, in the classroom, high reputation might be contested instead of rewarded.
WOS:000724026400003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="2">
<title>Local policymakers' attitudes towards climate change: A multi-method case study</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.09.001</url>
<snippet>Local authorities play a key role in tackling climate change by implementing targeted adaptation and mitigation measures. The specific implementation of a mix of adaptation and mitigation strategies is the outcome of the interaction of policymakers through a political debate and their attitudes towards climate change. By concentrating on the political discourses occurring in the Assembly of an Italian region (Emilia-Romagna), we use a multi-method approach of Discourse Network Analysis and Concept Mapping to investigate local policymakers positioning. Our investigation shows that actors are grouped not only according to their political affiliation, but also to the debated topics, and this relates to the preference for supporting adaptation or mitigation measures, which characterizes the local policy debate.
WOS:001084110900001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="3">
<title>Drivers of tie formation in the Canadian climate change policy network: Belief homophily and social structural processes</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.06.004</url>
<snippet>Extant research on policy networks tends to focus on explaining successes and/or failures of particular policy efforts. One commonly used theoretical framework - the Advocacy Coalition Framework (ACF) - focuses on actor attributes external to policy networks. We argue this leads to an incomplete understanding of the social dynamics of climate change policy making. We incorporate a policy network analytic approach with the ACF in an ERGM of collaboration in a Canadian climate change policy network, showing the role micro-structural network processes play in giving rise to informal policy networks. We find certain policy beliefs are correlated with tie formation. We also find micro-structural network processes related to reciprocity, structural equivalence and transitive closure are correlated with tie formation. We argue combining these two prominent streams of policy network literature has potential to improve our understanding of climate change policy making processes.
WOS:001084695500001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="4">
<title>Analysing networks of networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2023.02.002</url>
<snippet>We consider data with multiple observations or reports on a network in the case when these networks themselves are connected through some form of network ties. We could take the example of a cognitive social structure where there is another type of tie connecting the actors that provide the reports; or the study of interpersonal spillover effects from one cultural domain to another facilitated by the social ties. Another example is when the individual semantic structures are represented as semantic networks of a group of actors and connected through these actors social ties to constitute knowledge of a social group. How to jointly represent the two types of networks is not trivial as the layers and not the nodes of the layers of the reported networks are coupled through a network on the reports. We propose to transform the different multiple networks using line graphs, where actors are affiliated with ties represented as nodes, and represent the totality of the different types of ties as a multilevel network. This affords studying the associations between the social network and the reports as well as the alignment of the reports to a criterion graph. We illustrate how the procedure can be applied to studying the social construction of knowledge in local flood management groups. Here we use multilevel exponential random graph models but the representation also lends itself to stochastic actor-oriented models, multilevel blockmodels, and any model capable of handling multilevel networks.
WOS:000972522300001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="5">
<title>Collecting survey-based social network information in work organizations</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.04.003</url>
<snippet>Collecting social network data among organization members using surveys is challenging and requires a well considered strategy. Based on extensive past experience with collecting social network information in work organizations with surveys, we identify and discuss four major elements of the data collection process, all linked with and dependent on the specific research question and objective: 1) negotiating access to the organization; 2) identifying the networks boundary, the relevant formal organizational structures that affect social networks, and the sampling approach; 3) deciding how to approach research subjects and collect network data; and, 4) providing useful and ethically-sensitive feedback to the organization and its members. Decisions on each of these elements and their co-alignment, particularly with respect to the chosen research question, is crucial to a successful study. We offer guidelines and provide examples for each of these elements.
WOS:000700623500003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="6">
<title>Gender bias in the classroom: A network study on self and peer ability attribution</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.09.001</url>
<snippet>Stereotypes can contribute to the gender gap in STEM by shaping peoples expectations on their own and others performance. When gender is salient, expectations on task performance might reflect gender constructs even when information on individual abilities is available. We tested this hypothesis in a network study on students from ten high school classes in Milan, Italy. We asked the students to choose the four best candidates from their classmates for three hypothetical inter-class competitions in reading, math, and science. Results showed that females were more likely to be nominated for the reading competition but less likely for science. We did not find any statistically significant results for the math competition. We also found that female students were less likely to nominate themselves for any competition, regardless of the subject, even controlling for their own perfor-mance and self-concept.
WOS:000861598500002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="7">
<title>Evaluating heterogeneous brokerage: New conceptual and methodological approaches and their application to multi-level environmental governance networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2019.08.002</url>
<snippet>We present two new approaches for assessing the relative contributions of different types of actors to heterogeneous brokerage in networks. These approaches distinguish between the tendency of certain types of actors to (1) mediate between dissimilar actors (heterogeneous brokerage "activity"), and (2) be the sole mediators between dissimilar actors ("exclusivity"). We present methods for implementing these approaches, using baseline models of tie formation and node removal, respectively. To illustrate the value of both approaches, independently and in combination, we apply them to evaluate horizontal and vertical heterogeneous brokerage in two environmental governance networks. Our analysis reveals certain types of actors with high heterogeneous brokerage activity but low exclusivity (and vice versa), which has important implications for governance processes and outcomes. Likewise, results show many similarities across the evaluated networks, but also some notable differences, suggesting that the incentives and constraints for heterogeneous brokerage vary not only by actor type, but also by network-level contextual differences.
WOS:000512481500001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="8">
<title>Leadership and contagion by COVID-19 among residence hall students: A social network analysis approach</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2023.01.001</url>
<snippet>University students have changed their behaviour due to the COVID-19 pandemic. In this paper, we describe the characteristics of PCR+ and PCR-nodes, analyse the structure, and relate the structure of student leaders to pandemic contagion as determined by PCR+ in 93 residential university students. Leadership comes from the male students of social science degrees who have PCR +, with an eigenvector centrality structure, beta-centrality, and who are part of the bow-tie structure. There was a significant difference in beta-centrality between leaders and non-leaders and in beta-centrality between PCR+ and non-leaders. Leading nodes were part of the bow-tie structure. MR-QAP results show how residence and scientific branch were the most important factors in network formation. Therefore, university leaders should consider influential leaders, as they are vectors for disseminating both positive and negative outcomes.
WOS:000920256100001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="9">
<title>Organizational roles and network effects on ideational influence in science-policy interface: Climate policy networks in Germany and Japan</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.01.014</url>
<snippet>We examined how scientific information influences policy beliefs among organizations in climate change policy networks in Germany and Japan. Different combinations of information types, policy beliefs, and organizational roles were found to play instrumental roles. Ideational influence can occur when (1) the sender is a credible information source, (2) the receiver can understand the "message," and (3) the receiver depends on the senders information. Organizational roles involved in this ideational influence are different in technical and political information exchange. The leverage of influence depends on the organizational ecology of different roles in each country.
WOS:001084750500001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="10">
<title>Missing data in cross-sectional networks - An extensive comparison of missing data treatment methods</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.02.004</url>
<snippet>This paper compares several missing data treatment methods for missing network data on a diverse set of simulated networks under several missing data mechanisms. We focus the comparison on three different outcomes: descriptive statistics, link reconstruction, and model parameters. The results indicate that the often used methods (analysis of available cases and null-tie imputation) lead to considerable bias on descriptive statistics with moderate or large proportions of missing data. Multiple imputation using sophisticated imputation models based on exponential random graph models (ERGMs) lead to acceptable biases in descriptive statistics and model parameters even under large amounts of missing data. For link reconstruction multiple imputation by simple ERGM performed well on small data sets, while missing data was more accurately imputed in larger data sets with multiple imputation by complex Bayesian ERGMs (BERGMs).
WOS:000527272000011
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="11">
<title>To make and keep friends: The role of health status in adolescent network tie formation and persistence</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2023.04.005</url>
<snippet>Health status may shape network structure through network dynamics (tie formation and persistence) and direction (sent and received ties), net of typical network processes. We apply Separable Temporal Exponential Random Graph Models (STERGMs) to National Longitudinal Study of Adolescent to Adult Health survey data (n = 1779) to differentiate how health status shapes network sent and received tie formation and persistence. Results indicate that networks are shaped by withdrawal of adolescents experiencing poor health, highlighting the importance of separating distinct and directed processes of friendship formation and persistence when considering how health relates to adolescent social life.
WOS:001001289400001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="12">
<title>Networks and institutions in sustainable forest use: Evidence from South-East Tanzania</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.03.002</url>
<snippet>Despite growing interest in the impacts of both forest certification and networks in effective natural resource management, there is little literature that brings these two lines of inquiry together. Combining longitudinal remote sensing and village-level forest governance network data, we estimate Cox proportional hazard models predicting the risk of forest loss within 100-square meter forest plots in areas that eventually came under Forest Stewardship Council certification. Our models indicate Forest Stewardship Council certification substantially reduces deforestation, despite that the system is not explicitly designed to do so. While villages with ties to civil society organizations also tend to experience reduced deforestation, those with ties to private sector organizations experience more forest loss. Further, we find that forest loss declines as the share of closed triangles in villages governance networks increases. Our results indicate network structure may complement Forest Stewardship Council certifications impact on forest cover and account for some reduction in deforestation previously attributed to certification itself.
WOS:001149883100001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="13">
<title>Functional differentiation in governance networks for sea level rise adaptation in the San Francisco Bay Area</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.02.010</url>
<snippet>Climate change governance networks help actors overcome collective action problems by building social capital. The literature studies these networks as embodying a single underlying social problem: coordination or cooperation. This approach overlooks actor heterogeneity and cannot account for the empirical coexistence of different types of social capital. We contend that climate change governance networks consist of functionally differentiated communities of actors who build bonding or bridging social capital depending on their characteristics and goals. We test these claims with an Affiliation Graph Model (AGM) in the empirical case of adaptation to sea level rise in the San Francisco Bay Area, using original data collected in 2018. We distinguish three social processes: leadership/brokerage, translation, and following. Further research on different combinations of social capital across different networks is warranted.
WOS:001083656800001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="14">
<title>A matter of information - The influence of international bureaucracies in global climate governance networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.02.009</url>
<snippet>International bureaucracies, also called International Public Administrations (IPAs), have been identified as potentially influential actors within the global climate change regime complex. To assess how these organizations exert influence, scholars have predominantly relied on case studies, interviews and descriptive (network) statistics. This article aims to contribute to this literature with a systematic analysis that is not limited to an organization, issue or region, but applies exponential random graph models (ERGMs) to data from an original large-N survey (n = 342) of participants of global climate negotiations. Our findings indicate that IPAs have a considerable potential to influence global climate policy outputs. This potential influence is associated with the information they provide to regime stakeholders.
WOS:001089037700001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="15">
<title>Network ties, institutional roles and advocacy tactics:Exploring explanations for perceptions of influence in climate change policy networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.11.008</url>
<snippet>The extent to which a policy actor is perceived as being influential by others can shape their role in a policy process. The interest group literature has examined how the use of advocacy tactics, such as lobbying or media campaigns, contributes to an actors perceived influence. The policy networks literature, in turn, has found that network ties and occupying certain institutional roles can explain why actors are perceived as influential. When investigating what explains perceptions of influence, interest groups scholars have not accounted for network interdependencies and network scholars have so far not examined the advocacy tactics used by interest groups. This paper addresses the gap at the intersection of these two literatures by investigating the relationship between network ties, institutional roles, advocacy tactics and the presence of influence attribution ties in climate change policy networks. Exponential random graph models are applied to network data collected from the organisations participating in the national climate change policymaking processes in six EU countries that vary by the extent to which they are majoritarian or consensual democracies: Czechia, Finland, Germany, Ireland, Portugal, and Sweden. The results show that network ties and institutional roles are better predictors of influence attribution ties than advocacy tactics and that there is no pattern in the relationship between advocacy tactics and influence attribution ties across different institutional contexts. These findings suggest that because influence is primarily associated with structural factors (network ties and institutional roles) that more established policy actors are likely to have more influence, which may inhibit the need for a significant step change in climate policies.
WOS:001164709200001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="16">
<title>Bayesian nonparametric mixtures of Exponential Random Graph Models for ensembles of networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2023.03.005</url>
<snippet>Ensembles of networks arise in various fields where multiple independent networks are observed, for example, a collection of student networks from different classes. However, there are few models that describe both the variations and characteristics of networks in an ensemble at the same time. In this manuscript, we propose to model ensembles of networks using a Dirichlet Process Mixture of Exponential Random Graph Models (DPM-ERGMs), which divides an ensemble into different clusters and models each cluster of networks using a separate Exponential Random Graph Model (ERGM). By employing a Dirichlet process mixture, the number of clusters can be determined automatically and changed adaptively with the data provided. Moreover, in order to perform full Bayesian inference for DPM-ERGMs, we develop a Metropolis-within-slice sampling algorithm to address the problem of sampling from the intractable ERGMs on an infinite sample space. We also demonstrate the performance of DPM-ERGMs with both simulated and real datasets.
WOS:000969755400001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="17">
<title>Tolerable disagreements: Collective action capacity &amp; shape of coalitions</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.04.002</url>
<snippet>This paper examines collective action (CA) capacity and shape of coalitions. By applying temporal exponential random graph models on original datasets of Ottoman and French contenders, it finds that coalitions form both for strategic and ideological reasons; but strategically unified coalitions are more likely to take CA. Also, coalition shape depends on the type of disagreements among partners. Ideological polarization induces side taking; actors build ideologically oriented disconnected blocs. Absent ideological disagreements, strategically likeminded actors form cliques. Otherwise, umbrella coalitions emerge. This study ocers a novel theory to explain the kind of coalitions that are more likely to take CA.
WOS:000700623500002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="18">
<title>Assessing harmfulness and vulnerability in global bipartite networks of terrorist-target relationships</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.08.003</url>
<snippet>In this paper we leverage a massive attack-focused terrorist database and we design a dynamic bipartite network analysis to examine the structural evolution of terrorists-targets relationships. We introduce two novel measures to jointly assess harmfulness and vulnerability of terrorist and target groups, both at local and global level. Statistical validation using null models provides evidence that the information contained in these measures is new and not included in other variables, thus emphasizing the usefulness of these topological indicators. Finally, a policy-support experiment designed as network dismantling-like drill is proposed to assess the effects of potential attack preventive strategies.
WOS:000855088000002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="19">
<title>Actors and issues in climate change policy: The maturation of a policy discourse in the national and international context</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.08.005</url>
<snippet>Policy discourses are important platforms for political actors to express their preferences on certain issues and are usually linked to a specific policy subsystem. From a research perspective, they have the potential to indicate ideological coalitions, policy change and learning. Using discourse network analysis, we identify core policy actors, issues, and coalitions in Switzerlands climate policy discourse and investigate how they have evolved over the past 15 years. In line with the policy process literature, we expected to see more stability than change in the discourse linked to the mature climate policy subsystem. However, our results have shown that policy discourses are more volatile than policy subsystems, and that national and international policy developments are able to trigger change, particularly in terms of the configuration of actor coalitions and the issues discussed.
WOS:001084301100001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="20">
<title>Network sampling coverage III: Imputation of missing network data under different network and missing data conditions</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.05.002</url>
<snippet>Missing data is a common, difficult problem for network studies. Unfortunately, there are few clear guidelines about what a researcher should do when faced with incomplete information. We take up this problem in the third paper of a three-paper series on missing network data. Here, we compare the performance of different imputation methods across a wide range of circumstances characterized in terms of measures, networks and missing data types. We consider a number of imputation methods, going from simple imputation to more complex modelbased approaches. Overall, we find that listwise deletion is almost always the worst option, while choosing the best strategy can be difficult, as it depends on the type of missing data, the type of network and the measure of interest. We end the paper by offering a set of practical outputs that researchers can use to identify the best imputation choice for their particular research setting.
WOS:000700623500013
</snippet>
</document>

</searchresult>
