<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<searchresult>
<query>Global</query>
<document id="1">
<title>Learning to understand: disentangling the outcomes of stakeholder participation in climate change governance</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.02.006</url>
<snippet>Stakeholder participation is increasingly seen as beneficial for short and long term responses to climate change risks. Past research highlights the role social networks play as both a key outcome of participation, as well as an important step towards other environmental governance goals. This paper focuses on the social relation of mutual understanding, which is often discussed in the environmental governance literature, but has yet to be studied as an empirical social network in its own right. Our paper builds and tests a conceptual framework linking participation to mutual understanding and social learning. We analyze three waves of network and perceptions data gathered on stakeholders participating in the Integrated Coastal Resiliency Assessment (ICRA) project, a 2.5 yearlong project aimed at developing a collaborative research assessment on the vulnerabilities to climate change experienced by an island community located in the Chesapeake Bay, USA. Our findings suggest that participation (measured as co-attendance in project events) leads to the formation of mutual understanding ties among stakeholders, but these ties do not necessarily lead to more similarity in stakeholders perceptions on climate change. We reflect on these findings, and the project more broadly, noting that our study lends support to scholars arguing that feelings of mutual understanding are potentially more important for certain forms of collective action, as opposed to whether or not stakeholders increase their shared beliefs or perceptions about the environmental problem in question.
WOS:001084257900001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="2">
<title>The interplay of structural features and observed dissimilarities among centrality indices</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2023.11.006</url>
<snippet>An abundance of centrality indices has been proposed which capture the importance of nodes in a network based on different structural features. While there remains a persistent belief that similarities in outcomes of indices is contingent on their technical definitions, a growing body of research shows that structural features affect observed similarities more than technicalities. We conduct a series of experiments on artificial networks to trace the influence of specific structural features on the similarity of indices which confirm previous results in the literature. Our analysis on 1163 real-world networks, however, shows that little of the observations on synthetic networks convincingly carry over to empirical settings. Our findings suggest that although it seems clear that (dis)similarities among centralities depend on structural properties of the network, using correlation type analyses do not seem to be a promising approach to uncover such connections.
WOS:001134369900001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="3">
<title>A network intervention for natural resource management in the context of climate change</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.03.003</url>
<snippet>As climate change impacts the Great Lakes region, the increased frequency and intensity of precipitation events are dramatically increasing the erosive effects of stormwater in the ravine ecosystem. Because formal governance structures may not be effective in providing coordination during turbulent and dynamic events, those seeking to manage natural resources during climate change may turn to resources located in their social networks. In this study network analysis was used to visualize collegial ties and self-reported consideration of climate change among those managing ravines along southwestern Lake Michigan. Professional development then leveraged the visualizations to modify the network, potentially increasing knowledge flows and coordination. Those who were targeted by the intervention increased their engagement in the network and contributed to bridging between subgroups to fill structural holes. This provides insight into the potential for interventions that leverage baseline network analysis for the management of natural resources in the context of climate change.
WOS:001084751800001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="4">
<title>Coming into relations: How communication reveals and persuades relational decisions</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2024.05.003</url>
<snippet>Coming into relations involves exiting a state of indecision and deciding whether to relate or not. Little research has focused on these initial moments, the communications involved, and the making of a relational decision. We study this process using 947 speed dating encounters, their minute-by-minute communications, and the reported timing of relational decisions. We show that certain forms of communication reveal an actors relational state of being undecided, desiring a relation, or not desiring a relation (revealing signals). For example, indecision corresponds with indirect and ambiguous communication (negative facework); desiring a relation entails positive, excited, and entraining communication (positive facework); and not desiring a relation involves routine talk. We also show that certain forms of communication persuade persons to transition relational states, moving beyond their indecision and coming to a relational decision (persuasive signals). Interestingly, only some revealing signals are persuasive and bring about corresponding relational decisions in others. These tend to be clear signals that cannot be attributed to the situation or politeness. Last, some signals persuade relational decisions without corresponding to a relational state. These performative signals are select forms of ambiguous communication that place the speaker in an advantaged position within social exchange.
WOS:001258877300001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="5">
<title>The coevolution of trade agreements and investment treaties: Some evidence from network analysis</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2019.08.005</url>
<snippet>Regional trade agreements (RTAs) and bilateral investment treaties (BITs) are expected to promote trade and investment relationships. One critical feature of such agreements is the network, so the multiplex coevolution of RTAs and BITs should be captured by the dynamics of their two networks. Although many studies have examined the roles of RTAs and BITs, most studies do not account for crucial network properties. This study explores how RTAs and BITs coevolve by applying a stochastic actor-oriented model of multiplex network evolution. In particular, we examine the roles of (i) cross-network dyadic interinfluences and (ii) within- and cross-network preferential attachments to discuss the dynamic relationships between RTAs and BITs. The results are as follows. First, our estimation supports cross-network dyadic interinfluences. Countries that sign a BIT are willing to establish an RTA, while those that sign an RTA are reluctant to establish a BIT. Second, concerning preferential attachments, countries prefer to sign BITs with partners that have more RTA and BIT links. However, countries tend to form RTAs with partners that have more BIT links but are reluctant to form RTAs with those that have more RTA links. We discuss possible justifications for these results, including arguments regarding the benefits and costs associated with the formation of RTAs and BITs.
WOS:000512481500004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="6">
<title>Co-evolution of a socio-cognitive scientific network: A case study of citation dynamics among astronomers</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2023.11.008</url>
<snippet>This paper aims to understand how a group of academics cite each others work through time, considering the simultaneous co-evolution of three networks representing their scientific collaboration, the journals in which they publish and institutional membership. It argues that both social and cognitive processes contribute to these dynamics. Two types of network mechanisms are considered specifically: closures by affiliation and closures by association. To assess whether these mechanisms generate the macro features of the network under study, we propose new features for three-mode multilevel networks such as the mixed geodesic distances, mixed degree distributions, and the mixed quadrilateral census. We investigate whether a micro-level model that considers the above-mentioned network mechanisms is able to correctly reproduce these features. We apply stochastic actororiented models (SAOMs) for one-mode and two-mode networks to link the micro-macro processes using a dataset of a scientific community of astronomers from 2013 to 2015. The results suggest that social relationships grounded on scientific collaboration and proximity based on institutional affiliation are more accurately suited to understanding the co-evolution of the network of citations than an alternative approach that merely considers cognitive-based networks measured as the similarity in publishing in the same journals.
WOS:001146582800001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="7">
<title>Generators or diffusers? Examining differences in the dynamic coupling of context and social ties across multiple types of foci</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.02.004</url>
<snippet>Felds focus theory is one of the most influential approaches in social network analysis. However, with very few exceptions, empirical assessments of the theory have only focused on a narrow range of its predictions premised on comparative statics. This paper restates classical focus theory in terms of dependence between multiple network layers as they co -evolve, yielding dynamic focus theory. Social foci serve as an ecology within which person -to -person relations form and as a mechanism via which tastes and behaviors diffuse within a population through interpersonal ties. We argue this is a type of "focus effect" distinct from the standard tie -generation process typically considered. In addition, we go beyond previous single -foci studies in considering multiple foci types, allowing us to ascertain which foci-e.g., clubs, activities, musical genres, or academic course areas-act more like tie generators or which ones as taste diffusers. Using rich data from the NetSense and NetHealth studies, we use recently developed Stochastic Actor -Oriented Models (SAOMs) for two -mode networks to estimate simultaneous foci effects across different foci types. We find that musical genres function primarily as taste -diffusers, club types exclusively as tie generators, and course areas and activities as both tie generators and taste diffusers. We conclude by discussing key implications of dynamic focus theory, including how foci properties can account for variability in foci effects and the role different types of social foci play in social influence and the diffusion of tastes and behaviors.
WOS:001188650300001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="8">
<title>Corruption dynamics in public procurement: A longitudinal network analysis of local construction contracts in Guatemala</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2024.07.001</url>
<snippet>Spending concentration, political influence, and collusion violate rules and principles of open and fair public procurement, leading to corrupt contract allocation. This study adopts stochastic actor-oriented models to test the evolution of these forms of procurement corruption risks in a longitudinal network study of 33579 construction contracts pertaining to Guatemalan local governments from 2012 to 2020. We identify a range of network configurations, based on past empirical research and theory, that capture different patterns of suspicious micro tendencies suggestive of corruption. We show how these micro tendencies shift in strength according to changes in electoral cycles and anti-corruption interventions, thus shedding light on how interventions may temporarily impact corrupt behavior, and how it may adapt and persist after a period of transition. The results indicate that collusion and spending concentration play significant roles in sustaining the risk of corrupt contract allocation, and that this behavior is able to rebound even after the introduction of anti-corruption interventions and new political regimes. The findings underscore the importance of local interventions and advocate for network approaches to enhance transparency, accountability, and long-term anti-corruption efforts.
WOS:001281511300001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="9">
<title>How do youth choose activities? Assessing the relative importance of the micro-selection mechanisms behind adolescent extracurricular activity participation</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.12.008</url>
<snippet>We investigate the network micro-selection mechanisms responsible for patterns of high school student extracurricular activity (ECA) participation, with a particular focus on those that can lead to ethnoracial segregation. We identify six types of mechanisms by which students select into activities (e.g., peer influence, homophily), which we test using a unique longitudinal dataset that combines student surveys with yearbook data on ECA involvement. These contexts represent two ethnoracially diverse U.S. high schools involving 2403 students and over 200 different activities spanning two school years. Using a stochastic actor-oriented model for two-mode networks, we find support for the hypothesized activity selection mechanisms. Follow-up analyses convey the relative importance of different mechanisms and inform our discussion of how ECA participation patterns develop and possible sources of segregation. Whereas selection is driven by mechanisms that include influence from friends and co-participants and similarity to fellow participants, no single overarching mechanism appears strong enough to fully account for ECA segregation
WOS:001188488100001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="10">
<title>Improving ERGM starting values using simulated annealing</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2023.10.002</url>
<snippet>Much of the theory of estimation for exponential family models, which include exponential-family random graph models (ERGMs) as a special case, is well-established and maximum likelihood estimates (MLEs) particular enjoy many desirable properties. However, in the case of many ERGMs, direct calculation of MLEs is impossible and therefore methods for approximating MLEs and/or alternative estimation methods must be employed. Many MLE approximation algorithms require an alternative estimate as a starting point. The maximum pseudo-likelihood estimator (MPLE) is frequently taken as this starting point. Here, we discuss potentially large class of such alternatives based on the fact that, unlike the MLE, the MPLE fails to satisfy the so-called "likelihood principle". This means that different networks may have different MPLEs even they have the same sufficient statistics. We exploit this fact here to search for improved starting values for approximation-based MLE methods. The method we propose has shown its merit in producing an MLE for network dataset and model that had defied estimation using all other known methods.
WOS:001109742300001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="11">
<title>How new is "New"? Who gets added in a panel study of personal networks?</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.02.011</url>
<snippet>Using longitudinal data from UCNets, we examined newly-listed alters and distinguished between truly new ties who were recently met (typically coworkers and acquaintances) and awakened ties who were previously known to ego (typically extended kin and friends). Half of the newly-listed ties among the younger respondents were truly new, whereas two-thirds among the older respondents were awakened. In both groups, however, most alters were previously listed. These ties mainly included kin, confidants, and advisors, suggesting stability in the network core. Methodological implications for the name-generating process and substantive implications for the understanding of network dynamics and structure are discussed.
WOS:000819930800016
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="12">
<title>Networks from culture: Mechanisms of tie-formation follow institutionalized rules in social fields</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.12.005</url>
<snippet>Tie-formation mechanisms like homophily, reciprocity, transitivity, and preferential attachment operate to varying degrees across contexts. Romantic ties tend to be homophilous by age, education, and ethnicity, and to remain dyadic. Scientific citations, in contrast, fall into highly unequal preferential attachment patterns. Triangulation is nearly absent in advice and patronage networks but features prominently in friendship ties. Building on relational sociology and field theory, we argue that such variation in patterns of connectivity derives from the meaning attached to relationships, which varies by context. Tie-formation logics are institutionalized rules-of-the-game and susceptible to change over time. Accordingly, the mechanisms of tie-formation behind empirical network patterns have to be connected to the cultural rules in particular fields.
WOS:001188848400001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="13">
<title>Gender homophily and gender distribution in social networks: The case of older adults in long term care settings</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.06.005</url>
<snippet>Distinctiveness theory suggests that numeric rarity is correlated with stronger homophily. In this paper, we examine this theory by studying gender homophily in social networks of older adults. We document subjective social networks in multiple long term care settings for older adults over several time points. Homophily for each gender is estimated using exponential random graph models. We find evidence for positive homophily across all networks, and show that it is correlated to the magnitude of the female majority or male minority. Our findings empirically verify distinctiveness theory and could improve interventions to promote tie formation in social networks.
WOS:000828391400002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="14">
<title>The Swiss StudentLife Study: Investigating the emergence of an undergraduate community through dynamic, multidimensional social network data (Reprinted from vol 65, pages 71-84, 2021)</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.01.012</url>
<snippet>The Swiss StudentLife Study (SSL Study) is a longitudinal social network data collection conducted in three undergraduate student cohorts (N-1 = 226, N-2 = 261, N-3 = 660) in 2016-2019. The main goal of the study was to understand the emergence of informal student communities and their effects on different individual outcomes, such as well-being, motivation, and academic success. To this end, multiple dimensions of social ties were assessed, combining computer-based surveys, social sensors, social media data, and field experiments. The dy-namics of these social networks were measured on various time scales. In this paper, we present the design and data collection strategy of the SSL Study. We discuss practical challenges and solutions related to the data collection in four areas that were key to the success of our project: study design, research ethics, communication, and population definition.
WOS:000777028500003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="15">
<title>Digital networks: Elements of a theoretical framework</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.12.002</url>
<snippet>The proliferation of new, digital communications technologies and platforms over the past few decades has transformed the way humans relate to one another. In turn, there has been an explosion of scientific research using data on these interactions to better understand how social networks emerge and evolve. Curiously, this agenda has proceeded with little theoretical foundation-typically assuming digital and face-to-face ties operate the same way. The purpose of this article is to interrogate this assumption: I identify when, how, and to what consequence digital networks are similar to and different from other kinds of social networks and thereby attempt to strengthen the available theoretical scaffolding for this important and rapidly growing body of work.
WOS:001188248400001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="16">
<title>Network formation in organizational settings: Exploring the importance of local social processes and team-level contextual variables in small groups using bayesian hierarchical ERGMs</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.07.001</url>
<snippet>Statistical models for social networks, such as exponential random graphs (ERGMs), have increasingly been used by organizational scholars to study the social interactions inside organizations, departments, and teams. While such models have been successful in providing insights about the local processes that underlie these interactions (such as homophily, reciprocity or transitivity), an additional interesting avenue for research focuses on the role of group -level contextual variables (such as the climate or composition of a team or organization) when considering a multitude of teams or organizations. In this paper we show how, in a team context, integrating team -level factors in a multilevel framework (i.e., a Bayesian hierarchical ERGM) enables us to answer questions about: 1) how team -level contextual factors might provide alternative explanations for the emergence of intra-team ties, and 2) whether any variation in local tendencies between teams might be dependent on such team -level variables (i.e., cross -level interactions). Using data collected among 103 MBA students who were grouped into 18 teams of 5-7 members to work on a project, we study the impact of members expertise and perceived psychological safety on advice seeking behavior. At a local level, we focus on the effect of these nodal attributes for homophily and differences in advice seeking and giving, while at the team level we incorporate the average expertise and the teams psychological safety climate. Our results show that expert members are more likely to be the recipient of advice ties, but also that this effect is more pronounced in teams where the overall level of expertise is high. For psychological safety, we find that a high psychological safety climate impacts the advice relations among all members in the group, not solely those who themselves perceive a high level of psychological safety, suggesting that the team climate has an impact on all its members. This illustrates how a Bayesian hierarchical ERGM allows us to obtain relevant results even when studying small -sized groups.
WOS:001188361400001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="17">
<title>How does socioeconomic homophily emerge? Testing for the contribution of different processes to socioeconomic segregation in adolescent friendships</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2023.09.002</url>
<snippet>Homophily - the fact that friendships happen at a higher rate among similar individuals - does not necessarily imply homophilic selection - the tendency to look for similar friends. This is particularly true for socioeconomic homophily: because individuals social class impacts most aspects of their lives, there are several ways in which it can favor homogeneity in friendship networks. Applying this view to the relationships of French middle-school students, the present article tries to unravel the contribution of various relational processes to the emergence of socioeconomic homophily. Stochastic Actor-Oriented Models, a class of generative models designed for network panel data, are applied to the friendship networks of 820 students surveyed over a year and a half. Simulations derived from the estimated models are then used to assess the impact of different processes on aggregated levels of homophily. To that aim, a new metric is proposed that help researchers decompose an observed property of a network into a set of contributions from low-order processes, called "contribution scores". Results suggest that direct homophilic selection can be important in explaining socioeconomic homophily, but not in all cases. Indirect inducers, such as residential propinquity or ethnic selection, also play a significant role. Moreover, endogenous network processes - namely reciprocation and transitive closure - strongly contribute to homophily by reinforcing other homophily-inducing processes.
WOS:001086139200001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="18">
<title>If you do not know who knows what: Advice seeking under changing conditions of uncertainty after an acquisition</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2019.08.006</url>
<snippet>In this study we develop a model to explain the dynamics of advice seeking after an acquisition. We build on a theory of advice seeking that draws from prospect theory and expectancy theory. We theorize that immediately after an acquisition there is uncertainty about who knows what, but over time individuals become more aware of the expertise within the organization and they change their advice networks based upon this increased awareness. Our model examines four micro-processes of advice seeking: reciprocity, preferential attachment, transitivity, and legacy-firm tie preferences. To test our hypotheses we use post-acquisition data over four time periods in a recruitment consulting firm. Our longitudinal analysis uses a stochastic actor-orientated model and our results indicate that immediately after the acquisition individuals have a tendency to seek advice based upon reciprocity and preferential attachment. However, over time these tendencies diminish. Surprisingly, transitivity does not play a significant role, which suggests that other micro-processes such as reciprocity are dominant. In addition, individuals in the acquired firm have a tendency to make more ties and there is a preference for same firm ties in both legacy firms, with the tendency being higher in the acquired firm. Our findings add to theories on the process of advice seeking under conditions of uncertainty, on knowledge transfer processes in mergers and acquisitions, and the knowledge based view of the firm.
WOS:000512481500005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="19">
<title>Cross-sectional social network study of adolescent peer group variation in substance use and mental wellbeing: The importance of the meso level</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2023.12.002</url>
<snippet>Adolescent health-related behaviours and outcomes are shaped by their peers through various social processes. Research using network data on friendship ties has uncovered evidence for processes such as peer influence and imitation. Much less is known about how the structure of small groups within a network, network communities that represents its meso level, affect individuals. The structure and composition of peer groups could play an important role in shaping health behaviour but knowledge of the effects of groups is limited. We used data from The Peers and Levels of Stress study, a cross-sectional social network study conducted in 2006 of 22 secondary schools in Glasgow, Scotland. Students from one year group (15-16 yrs., N = 3148; 50.8&#37; women) provided information on socio-demographics, health behaviour and friendships via a questionnaire. Dependent variables were substance use and general mental wellbeing measured via principal components. We used a series of multilevel models with students (level 1), network communities (peer groups) identified by the Walktrap algorithm (level 2), and schools (level 3). We found substantial and moderate clustering at the peer group level for substance use and mental wellbeing, respectively. Larger and more transitive groups were associated with less substance use, but worse mental wellbeing. Addressing the methodological gap regarding the influence of the choice of group detection method on findings, we repeated our analysis using nine additional methods. The choice of the method somewhat influenced peer group variance and greatly influenced association of peer group properties with health. This study makes two key contributions to school-health improvement research. Beyond describing peer group clustering health outcomes, this is the first demonstration that structural and compositional characteristics of peer groups are associated with individual health, while highlighting the sensitivity of findings to group detection method used.
WOS:001157689500001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="20">
<title>Who benefits from network intervention programs? TERGM analysis across ten Philippine low-income communities</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.12.008</url>
<snippet>Building social capital and strengthening social networks among members of low-income communities has been recommended as a potential pathway out of poverty. However, it is not clear how network-strengthening interventions and community-based programs interact with pre-existing networks and power structures. We examine the impact of one such intervention in ten low income communities in the Philippines. The intervention is a standardized program of a faith-based organization implemented in thousands of communities in multiple countries. It brings together low-income individuals in each community for 16 weekly sessions about health, income generation, and Christian values. An important but yet unmeasured goal of the intervention is the strengthening of social networks among the participants. We measured the social networks before and after the intervention and analysed their changes both separately and jointly for all ten communities with temporal exponential random graph models (TERGM). We modelled the post-intervention network structures conditioning on the pre-intervention networks, pre-intervention node attributes, and attribute changes through the intervention. We found social engagement (measured by social visits to others) to moderate most consistently the effects of the intervention across the ten communities. Those who were more socially engaged consistently strengthened their networks through the intervention. By contrast, some network mechanisms strongly diverged between the communities. In particular, religiosity was positively associated with gaining social links through this faith-based intervention in some communities and negatively in others. Similar communities may in some aspects react to the same intervention in opposite ways-a phenomenon that should be further explored through studies of larger numbers of comparable networks.
WOS:000614282000010
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="21">
<title>Evaluating heterogeneous brokerage: New conceptual and methodological approaches and their application to multi-level environmental governance networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2019.08.002</url>
<snippet>We present two new approaches for assessing the relative contributions of different types of actors to heterogeneous brokerage in networks. These approaches distinguish between the tendency of certain types of actors to (1) mediate between dissimilar actors (heterogeneous brokerage "activity"), and (2) be the sole mediators between dissimilar actors ("exclusivity"). We present methods for implementing these approaches, using baseline models of tie formation and node removal, respectively. To illustrate the value of both approaches, independently and in combination, we apply them to evaluate horizontal and vertical heterogeneous brokerage in two environmental governance networks. Our analysis reveals certain types of actors with high heterogeneous brokerage activity but low exclusivity (and vice versa), which has important implications for governance processes and outcomes. Likewise, results show many similarities across the evaluated networks, but also some notable differences, suggesting that the incentives and constraints for heterogeneous brokerage vary not only by actor type, but also by network-level contextual differences.
WOS:000512481500001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="22">
<title>Similarity and differences in age, gender, ethnicity, and education as explanatory factors of tie loss in the core discussion network</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2023.09.003</url>
<snippet>Individuals are more likely to interact with people who are similar in terms of socio-demographics and values than dissimilar people, which is often explained by a focus on selection effects. Yet, tie loss of dissimilar ties might also cause network homogeneity. Unfortunately, within the literature, there is a relative dearth of knowledge on the relationship between (dis)similarity and tie loss. Hence, we address this gap by theorizing and testing the relation between (dis)similarity and tie loss in the core discussion network (CDN) of Dutch citizens, also considering how ties are embedded in the CDN.
WOS:001083100300001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="23">
<title>Not all friends are created equal: Friendship ties across different social contexts in South Korea</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2024.02.002</url>
<snippet>This study explores variation in composition and strength of close friendship ties across timing and contexts of tie formation. Analyzing South Korean survey data and comparing it with existing U.S. and Korean network data, we find both similarities and differences between friendship and non -kin discussion networks in the two countries. We show that schools are a crucial source of close friendships for Koreans, shaping homophily patterns. Additionally, we uncover substantial variations in tie strength across timings and contexts of tie formation. We discuss the implications of these findings, highlighting the role of social and cultural contexts in shaping personal networks.
WOS:001208596500001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="24">
<title>A network centrality bias: Central individuals in workplace networks have more supportive coworkers</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.12.002</url>
<snippet>Combining the results of two empirical studies, we investigate the role of alters motivation in explaining change in egos network position over time. People high in communal motives, who are prone to supportive and altruistic behavior in their interactions with others as a way to gain social acceptance, prefer to establish ties with co-workers occupying central positions in organizational social networks. This effect results in a systematic network centrality bias: The personal network of central individuals (individuals with many incoming ties from colleagues) is more likely to contain more supportive and altruistic people than the personal network of in-dividuals who are less central (individuals with fewer incoming ties). This result opens the door to the possibility that the effects of centrality so frequently documented in empirical studies may be due, at least in part, to characteristics of the alters in an egos personal community, rather than to egos themselves. Our findings invite further empirical research on how alters motives affect the returns that people can reap from their personal networks in organizations.
WOS:000923259100001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="25">
<title>Writing into relationships</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.06.006</url>
<snippet>Social network change is often accomplished through communicative efforts but seldom studied as such. This article studies communicative efforts at tie change as expressed in interpersonal notes between adolescents. Communicative efforts bring about tie change by identifying perceived relational problems and social corroboration with surrounding actors, dyads and contiguous events. This pressures others to respond in ways that form, maintain, revise, or dissolve relationships. Social corroboration is sought through a process with several identifiable stages. First, writers describe a relational scene composed of perceived interpersonal stances between actors. Within the scene, some stances are clearly defined, enacted, felt, and/or socially confirmed, suggesting stable ties. Other stances are uncertain and reflect focal problems in need of relational work, becoming the focal story in the relational scene. Second, writers present stories in an attempt to motivate audience response by revealing the writers intention, by assigning undesirable identities to select actors, and by implicating some tie changes as (in)appropriate to the scene. Last, audiences respond to these notes with their own communication, either affirming and aligning relations in ways that move desired tie changes toward actualization, or redefining the story in ways that require additional exchanges. In this manner individuals write their way into relationships.
WOS:000932028700003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="26">
<title>Symbolic association networks: A case study of orchestral programming's effect on the reputation of composers</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2024.08.001</url>
<snippet>A type of symbolic association network for the development of reputation is described and tested. Associations between people in these networks are not based on individual interaction, but rather are created by "reputational entrepreneurs" based on perceived symbolic association between people. We argue the intent of this type of connection is to add to the reputational information about those connected and we test whether a network of such associations influence cultural recognition. To do this, we use dyadic connections between classical music composers created by conductors for orchestra performance and determine whether a composers symbolic association network (SAN) aids recognition in publications. We find SANs to have a significant impact on the extent of reputational recognition, even when holding a composers individual status achievements constant. Composers with a large symbolic association network and those who bridge unconnected composers tend to receive more recognition. We discuss the influence of symbolic association networks on perception of reputational significance. We suggest SANs may advance research in reputation and culture particularly when considering actors whose reputation is active beyond their work or lifetime, such as artists, writers, musicians, and historical figures.
WOS:001291702300001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="27">
<title>Network ecology: Tie fitness in social context(s)</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2023.11.002</url>
<snippet>Social relations are embedded in material, cultural, and institutional settings that affect network dynamics and the resulting topologies. For example, romantic entanglements are subject to social and cultural norms, interfirm alliances are constrained by country -specific legislation, and adolescent friendships are conditioned by classroom settings and neighborhood effects. In short, social contexts shape social relations and the networks they give rise to. However, how and when they do so remain to be established. This paper presents network ecology as a general framework for identifying how the proximal environment shapes social networks by focusing interactions and social relations, and how these interactions and relations in turn shape the environment in which social networks form. Tie fitness is introduced as a metric that quantifies how well particular dyadic social relations would align with the setting. Using longitudinal networks collected on two cohorts each in 18 North American schools, i.e., 36 settings, we develop five generalizable observations about the time -varying fitness of adolescent friendship. Across all 252 analyzed networks, tie fitness predicted new tie formation, tie longevity, and tie survival. Dormant fit ties cluster in relational niches, thereby establishing a resource base for social identities competing for increased representation in the relational system.
WOS:001188643200001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="28">
<title>Understanding networks with exponential-family random network models</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2023.07.003</url>
<snippet>The structure of many complex social networks is determined by nodal and dyadic covariates that are endogenous to the tie variables. While exponential-family random graph models (ERGMs) have been very successful in modeling social networks with exogenous covariates, they are often misspecified for networks where some covariates are stochastic. Exponential-family random network models (ERNMs) are an extension of ERGM that retain the desirable properties of ERGM, but allow the joint modeling of tie variables and covariates. We compare ERGM to ERNM to show how conclusions of ERGM modeling are improved by consideration of the ERNM framework. In particular, ERNM simultaneously represents the effects of social influence and social selection processes, while commonly used models do not.
WOS:001143302000001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="29">
<title>The development of stratification and segregation in a new scientific field: A study of collaboration among scientists in neuroblastoma research between 1975 and 2016</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.05.001</url>
<snippet>Using a new data set on scientific collaboration in neuroblastoma research over a period of 41 years, we study how the structure of collaboration ties in an evolving scientific field changes over time. Guided by concepts from the sociology of knowledge and status theories, we highlight the importance of a fields size and age for processes of stratification and segregation within it. Our findings suggest that stratification becomes stronger and di-versifies as the field of neuroblastoma research expands. Moreover, we find that the occurrence of collaboration between researchers with a similar status becomes more likely as the field matures. While previous work has primarily examined established fields, our study focuses on how scientific fields change their structure over time. More broadly, our article demonstrates the potential analytical merits of adopting a dynamic and relational perspective on the developmental trajectories of organizational and cultural fields.
WOS:000871117900002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="30">
<title>Structure in context: A morphological view of whole network performance</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.10.002</url>
<snippet>Network perspectives in organizational research have focused primarily on how the embeddedness of actors shapes individual, or nodal, outcomes. Against this backdrop, a growing number of researchers have begun to adopt a wider lens on organizational networks, shifting the focus to collective, or whole network, performance. Yet, efforts to understand the relationship between whole network structure and whole network performance have produced conflicting findings, which suggests that a different approach may be needed. Drawing on macrostructural sociology, we propose a "whole network morphology" framework, which argues the whole network structure-performance relationship is contingent on other fundamental-relational and cultural-whole network dimensions. Subsequently, we undertake an application of our framework, through which we demon-strate how a morphological view helps address conflicting findings on the structure-performance relationship. We study 250 whole interorganizational networks known as Accountable Care Organizations (ACOs), which collectively comprise more than 44,000 healthcare organizations and 250,000 physicians. Consistent with pre-vious work, we do not find a clear association between structural connectedness and performance. However, we find that a more disconnected network structure is associated with negative ACO performance when the rela-tional strength of network ties is high. We also find evidence of better ACO performance in the presence of a physician cultural orientation when the whole network is more connected.
WOS:000884837300002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="31">
<title>Social distance in France: Evolution of homogeneity within personal networks from 2001 to 2017</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.05.001</url>
<snippet>This article explores the evolution of homogeneity within personal networks in France over time and across several relational contexts, using two cross-sectional surveys conducted in 2001 (n = 399) and 2017 (n = 663). Personal networks have changed relatively little overall, but with a tendency toward more homogeneity among the most educated, 26-45 and 61-75 year-olds, singles, and childless individuals. Differences in rates of personal network homogeneity are only partly explained by demographic shifts in French society. These findings are mostly consistent with those of other studies in Hungary and the USA. We argue that the effects of rising education levels, the segmentation of social contexts in terms of age, and the transformation of family models - which can be observed in most western countries - reinforce relational spheres characterized by relatively similar lifestyles.
WOS:000700623500006
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="32">
<title>Kudos make you run! How runners influence each other on the online social network Strava</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.10.001</url>
<snippet>Strava is the largest online social network for athletes. We used Stravas big data to investigate how runners in the same virtual Strava club influenced each others running behavior. We hypothesized that receiving kudos on recorded activities would spur exercise rates, and that the running behavior of clubmates to whom ego gave kudos would serve as a motivational example. We focused on five different Strava clubs that functioned as a virtual extension of real-life Dutch running clubs with a total of 329 members. Using data on kudos and recorded activities, we constructed a longitudinal dataset of complete networks and behavior over 11 periods with a one -month time window. We tested our hypotheses using SIENA. We found that receiving kudos induced runners to run more and more often. Moreover, athletes tended to adjust their running behavior to that of their kudos -friends (i.e., those to whom they gave kudos). Contrary to our expectation, kudos-friends who ran more and more often than ego were not the most influential. If anything, the reverse was true; athletes were more likely to come to resemble the running behavior of their kudos-friends who ran less and less often.
WOS:000884837300001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="33">
<title>Farm size shapes friend choice amongst rice producers in China: Some evidence for the theory of network ecology'</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2019.10.001</url>
<snippet>Multiple dynamics jointly determine who we befriend, however, researchers have failed to systematically assess which processes matter most under different circumstances. Here I draw on observations around how the demands of paddy rice cultivation shape social interaction to demonstrate that the relative importance of reciprocity, transitivity and generalised exchange to who rice producers choose as friends varies with the amount of agricultural land under their control. In doing so, I use unique data on farm size and friendship amongst 4713 rice-growing smallholders in 162 rural villages in Jiangxi, China along with a new technique for measuring the relative importance of effects in Stochastic Actor-Oriented Models. In line with the micro-level component of the recently advanced "theory of network ecology", results suggest that features of an individuals proximal environment can powerfully moderate the relative expression of network-formation mechanisms such that for some individuals, a dynamic may be expected to hold substantial sway over the process of choosing social contacts and, for others, no sway at all.
WOS:000512481500010
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="34">
<title>Network dynamics and its impact on innovation outcomes: R&amp;D consortia in the Dutch water sector</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2023.02.004</url>
<snippet>In this study, we explore the relationship between inter-organizational network dynamics and innovation out-comes. We focus on node turnover and argue that both cluster and broker dynamics can range from low (stable) to high (volatile), resulting in differentiated outcomes. The data comprises 318 consortium members participating in 104 R&amp;D consortia forged in a 23-year period in the Dutch water sector. Our analysis reveals two equifinal combinations (stable brokers - volatile clusters and volatile brokers - stable clusters) that both generate significantly higher innovation outcomes compared to networks with low, moderate, or high dynamics across the entire network.
WOS:000946828500001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="35">
<title>Scaling bias in pooled exponential random graph models</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2023.02.003</url>
<snippet>Researchers often use pooled exponential random graph models (ERGM) to analyze samples of networks. However, pooled ERGM-here, understood to include both meta-regression and combined estimation on a stacked adjacency matrix-may be biased if there is heterogeneity in the latent error variance (scaling) of each lower-level model. This study explores the implications of scaling for pooled ERGM analysis. We illustrate that scaling can produce bias in pooled ERGM coefficients that is more severe than in single-network ERGM and we introduce two methods for reducing this bias. Simulations suggest that scaling bias can be large enough to alter conclusions about pooled ERGM coefficient size, significance, and direction, but can be substantially reduced by estimating the marginal effect within a block diagonal or random effects meta-regression framework. We illustrate each method in an empirical example using Add Health data on 15 in-school friendship networks. Results from the application illustrate that many substantive conclusions vary depending on choice of pooling method and interpretational quantity.
WOS:000974866700001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="36">
<title>Trust, quality, and the network collection experience: A tale of two studies on the Democratic Republic of the Congo (Reprinted from vol 68, pages 237-255, 2022)</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.01.003</url>
<snippet>Data collection in social network research has advanced to include online questionnaires, digital metadata mining of internet sites, and the use of remote-sensing technologies. Some scholars however call for more attention to nuanced understandings of ties and contexts in studies of social structure and relationships, evoking practices that characterise the fields foundational works. This articles two studies reference these earlier efforts, drawing on ethnography and primary data collection. Both were undertaken in conflict-affected eastern Democratic Republic of the Congo (DRC) and broadly aimed to refine understandings of public authority and governance. Such research strives to inform humanitarian interventions to support social structures and actors which benefit their communities - however unexpected and unconventional. The first study (2016) employed a novel link-tracing design to examine personal support networks entwining purportedly hostile sub-populations, from combatants to unaffiliated civilians. The second (2018-20) focussed on access to essential social services across different governance arrangements, areas dominated by tenuous alliances of domestic or foreign militias and other actors. Leveraging an egocentric network design, it yielded multilevel relational network chain data. Each study was rife with obstacles related to accessing participants, sampling, reliability, and validity. We reflect on this network collection experience, foregrounding the interdependence between trust and data quality brought into stark relief by the settings instability and insecurity. This interdependency impacts all social network research, especially when it involves precarious contexts or sensitive topics.
WOS:000777028500012
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="37">
<title>Social networks and anthropogenic climate change</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2023.03.002</url>
<snippet>
WOS:001085231200001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="38">
<title>Interaction dynamics in classroom group work</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2024.05.002</url>
<snippet>Group work in classrooms is employed by teachers across all levels of education. For group work to be effective, all students should participate equally. Why some students engage in interaction and how group size and composition influence interaction dynamics is a research gap. We employed dynamic actor-oriented models on a sample of 145 Czech lower-secondary students in 62 small groups and pooled the results from the groups with a meta-analytical procedure. We found bursty behavior resulting from endogenous structural mechanisms of reciprocity, transitivity, cyclicity, and preferential attachment. Students gave preference to initiating interactions with those they initiated interactions with before and off-task interaction contributed to the development of ontask interaction. Students strongly preferred interactions with friends. Those students who talked a lot during regular whole-classroom lessons and students with high levels of literacy tended to both initiate and receive more interactions in group work, and students similar in these attributes preferred to interact with each other. Group size did not affect preferential attachment tendencies in interaction, but smaller groups made the effect of friendship ties on interactions stronger, and communication group norms shifted with changing group composition. Our study shows the suitability of dynamic actor-oriented models for studying interaction in education and small groups.
WOS:001250013700001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="39">
<title>Dimensions of social networks: A taxonomy and operationalization</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.02.005</url>
<snippet>What are the basic types of social network ties captured by name generators? While there have been several classifications proposed, and a large proliferation of name generators capturing various tie content has emerged, there is no clear way to map a given name generator to a particular tie type. Building on previous research, this paper proposes a framework for doing so in a principled way based on two studies. Study 1 is a dimension reduction of 24 common name generators. We find two dimensions (Valence and Social Distance), three positive tie types (Admiration, Closeness, Socialize), and three negative tie types (Active Conflict, Passive Conflict, Contempt) and use Youdens J statistic as a metric to identify the name generator that best maximizes sensitivity and specificity for detecting our tie types. We find that the most common name generators used by researchers fall within just one tie type (Closeness). Study 2 models these six tie types as predictors and outcomes of important sociological variables and finds that each tie type is associated with distinct patterns of emotions, social support, social status, and social roles. Our taxonomy makes a contribution to network theory as well as study design. In particular, it advances our understanding of the nature of signed ties. We find that negative ties are both bipolar and orthogonal, and distinguish between two types of ambivalence. Moreover, the findings contribute to the further refinement and elaboration of a comprehensive taxonomy of network ties.
WOS:000861374000001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="40">
<title>Emergence of social support networks among breast cancer survivors through a community-based physical activity program in Colombia</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.12.007</url>
<snippet>Physical activity (PA), social networks, and social support have been associated with decreased mortality and improved quality of life among breast cancer survivors (BCS). This study used social network analysis to un-derstand the social co-benefits of a community-based PA program for BCS in Colombia. Two types of social support networks emerged from the program: friendship (the number of edges increased by 90 &#37;) and PA support (35 &#37; of participants practiced PA together after the program). Using egocentric and socio-centric analysis we show the presence of homophily for friendship and PA support relations and the BCSs roles in their networks.
WOS:000918760600001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="41">
<title>Knowing me, knowing you: Socio-economic status and (segregation in) peer and parental networks in primary school</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2023.03.003</url>
<snippet>Students of different socio-economic status (SES) backgrounds are sorted into different schools. While integrating schools seems an easy solution to enhance inter-group interaction, this is yet an empirical question as we know little about how networks structure along SES lines in school. We examine the tendency for friendship and parental networks in primary school to structure by SES. We furthermore explore the role of the local school context. To do so, we collected multiplex classroom network data among Dutch students in 68 classrooms (55 schools) in their final year of primary school (grade 6; age 11-12). We link these sociometric data to register data, and test our hypotheses using cross-sectional exponential random graph models and meta-analysis tech-niques. Findings show that the networks of primary school students and their parents display a tendency for same-SES over cross-SES ties, net of opportunity structures. We do not find evidence for SES differences in the strength of SES homophily. Descriptive analyses show SES disparities in the extent to which parents have ties with the parents of their childrens friends (i.e., intergenerational closure), but these disparities disappear when controlling for other tie-generating mechanisms using ERGMs.
WOS:000959431800001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="42">
<title>Collecting survey-based social network information in work organizations</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.04.003</url>
<snippet>Collecting social network data among organization members using surveys is challenging and requires a well considered strategy. Based on extensive past experience with collecting social network information in work organizations with surveys, we identify and discuss four major elements of the data collection process, all linked with and dependent on the specific research question and objective: 1) negotiating access to the organization; 2) identifying the networks boundary, the relevant formal organizational structures that affect social networks, and the sampling approach; 3) deciding how to approach research subjects and collect network data; and, 4) providing useful and ethically-sensitive feedback to the organization and its members. Decisions on each of these elements and their co-alignment, particularly with respect to the chosen research question, is crucial to a successful study. We offer guidelines and provide examples for each of these elements.
WOS:000700623500003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="43">
<title>Parameter estimation procedures for exponential-family random graph models on count-valued networks: A comparative simulation study</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2023.07.001</url>
<snippet>The exponential-family random graph models (ERGMs) have emerged as an important framework for modeling social networks for a wide variety of relational types. ERGMs for valued networks are less well-developed than their unvalued counterparts, and pose particular computational challenges. Network data with edge values on the non-negative integers (count-valued networks) is an important such case, with examples ranging from the magnitude of migration and trade flows between places to the frequency of interactions and encounters between individuals. Here, we propose an efficient parallelizable subsampled maximum pseudo-likelihood estimation (MPLE) scheme for count-valued ERGMs, and compare its performance with existing Contrastive Divergence (CD) and Monte Carlo Maximum Likelihood Estimation (MCMLE) approaches via a simulation study based on migration flow networks in two U.S. states. Our results suggest that edge value variance is a key factor in method performance, while network size mainly influences their relative merits in computational time. For small-variance networks, all methods perform well in point estimations while CD greatly overestimates uncertainties, and MPLE underestimates them for dependence terms; all methods have fast estimation for small networks, but CD and subsampled multi-core MPLE provides speed advantages as network size increases. For large-variance networks, both MPLE and MCMLE offer high-quality estimates of coefficients and their uncertainty, but MPLE is significantly faster than MCMLE; MPLE is also a better seeding method for MCMLE than CD, as the latter makes MCMLE more prone to convergence failure. The study suggests that MCMLE and MPLE should be the default approach to estimate ERGMs for small-variance and large-variance valued networks, respectively. We also offer further suggestions regarding choice of computational method for valued ERGMs based on data structure, available computational resources and analytical goals.
WOS:001051911800001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="44">
<title>Collecting experimental network data from interventions on critical links in workplace networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.02.004</url>
<snippet>This article describes and discusses challenges associated with interventionist network data gathering in organizational settings, with a special focus on dyadic interventions. While pointing out major risks of these approaches, we argue that collecting data in combination with dyadic network alteration methods can enable social network researchers to explore network mechanisms from a new angle and potentially benefit the members of the targeted social networks and the entire collectives, if certain research design and implementation principles are followed. We introduce a facilitated self-disclosure method for strengthening critical dyads in social networks in combination with longitudinal and retrospective network measurement. We assess the participants perceptions of the different stages of this process by qualitative interviews. The study illustrates that experimental network data collection includes some extra challenges in addition to the many challenges of observational network data collection but participants also reported practical benefits that would not be gained through observational network surveys alone. The results highlight the importance of early and continuous communication during the data collection process with all research participants, not just the management, and the benefits of sharing more of the preliminary results. The lessons learnt through this study can inform the design of experimental network data collection to prioritize the preferences of the participants and their benefits.
WOS:000648645200007
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="45">
<title>Lost in translation: Collecting and coding data on social relations from audio-visual recordings</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.02.006</url>
<snippet>Some of the constitutive features of social relations fade from view when information naturally produced by sequential social interaction is translated into network ties. Building on core concepts and ideas developed within conversation analysis, in this paper we argue that this happens because the sequential, multimodal and embodied character of social relations can be fully understood only with reference to the sequential constrains that are generated by - and at the same time shape the micro-dynamics of social interaction. We suggest that the translation of social interaction into social networks precludes analysis of the multiple interfaces that sustain social relations (multimodality), and the material resources around which social relations are organized (embodiment). We highlight audio-visual recording as a data collection technology that facilitates storage, retrieval, and analysis of complex information on social relations that is typically absent from social network data. An illustrative video-supported case study based on the observation of social and task-related interaction among members of surgical teams provides the empirical context that supports and motivates our general reflection on network data collection strategies and technologies to study social interaction. The analysis highlights the need for social networks research to return to the study of social relations.
WOS:000777556900010
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="46">
<title>Collecting network data from documents to reach non-participatory populations</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.09.004</url>
<snippet>Collecting social network data is challenging, not least because conventional approaches rely on human participation. However, there are instances where access to research subjects is restricted or non-existent, especially in the high-stakes commercial world. This paper outlines the collection of network data from a relatively obscure financial document - the offering circular. I consider the implications of dealing with a non participatory population and data that is not produced for social network research. In exploring the process of translating data into social network data I highlight the importance of retaining context and qualitative descriptions in the data. I also consider how different coding strategies impact the network. Finally, I discuss the triangulation, data anonymity and potential ethical-legal implications of collecting data from documents.
WOS:000777556900011
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="47">
<title>R&amp;D cooperation in collaborative consumption of research equipment: An ERGM approach</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2023.03.001</url>
<snippet>High-tech research infrastructure is essential for state-of-the-art research, but requires many resources. Relatively weak actors, such as SMEs, cannot secure enough of those. Applying the concept of collaborative consumption via digital platforms, we examine the cooperative behavior of Korean SMEs that share research equipment to overcome their lack of resources. Also, we analyze configurations of a collaborative consumption network using the Exponential Random Graph Model. Network structural factor analysis shows sufficient effects of network positive feedback through cooperative consumption with a variety of popular providers and attributes analysis shows that SMEs frequently engage in collaborative consumption with their counterparts in the same region. This new cooperative model can achieve a virtuous cycle of policies, as it increases the efficiency of research infrastructure, preventing the unnecessary building of new research equipment and enabling relocation of underutilized infrastructure and online reservation of equipment.
WOS:000954576700001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="48">
<title>Networks from archives: Reconstructing networks of official correspondence in the early modern Portuguese empire</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.08.008</url>
<snippet>Historical archives provide invaluable insights into societies of the past, including social networks. However, the required amount of traditional archival work makes historical network studies usually small-scaled. We consider the problem of processing a large corpus of unstructured textual information to extract network data. The corpus consists of almost 170,000 documents of administrative correspondence of the Portuguese Empire, from 1610 to 1833, catalogued in the Portuguese Overseas Archives of Lisbon. Our contribution is twofold: the method and the result. Firstly, grounded in the review of manual, semi-manual and automatic methods of network data extraction from natural language corpora, we propose and demonstrate an approach using modern natural language processing algorithms. This approach tries to mimic traditional archivists coding practices and is applicable to large corpora of texts, for which manual coding is infeasible because of scale. We believe our approach is generic and adaptable to other substantive contexts, languages, and types of historical archives. Secondly, the dataset created is rich in additional information such as occupation, administrative affiliation, and geographical location of senders and recipients. We provide a preliminary network analysis suggesting that the dataset is an attractive material for historians and social network researchers for addressing research questions about the political and social evolution of the early modern Portuguese Empire, spanning the reign of seven Portuguese monarchs.
WOS:000777556900012
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="49">
<title>Multilevel network interventions: Goals, actions, and outcomes</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.09.005</url>
<snippet>COVID-19 has resulted in dramatic and widespread social network interventions across the globe, with public health measures such as distancing and isolation key epidemiological responses to minimize transmission. Because these measures affect social interactions between people, the networked structure of daily lives is changed. Such largescale changes to social structures, present simultaneously across many different societies and touching many different people, give renewed significance to the conceptualization of social network interventions. As social network researchers, we need a framework for understanding and describing network interventions consistent with the COVID-19 experience, one that builds on past work but able to cast interventions across a broad societal framework. In this theoretical paper, we extend the conceptualization of social network interventions in these directions. We follow Valente (2012) with a tripartite categorization of interventions but add a multilevel dimension to capture hierarchical aspects that are a key feature of any society and implicit in any network. This multilevel dimension distinguishes goals, actions, and outcomes at different levels, from individuals to the whole of the society. We illustrate this extended taxonomy with a range of COVID-19 public health measures of different types and at multiple levels, and then show how past network intervention research in other domains can also be framed in this way. We discuss what counts as an effective network, an effective intervention, plausible causality, and careful selection and evaluation, as central to a full theory of network interventions.
WOS:000871117900003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="50">
<title>Name order effects in measuring adolescent social networks using rosters</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2023.07.002</url>
<snippet>Recent studies have found order effects in social network data collection, where later names on a roster receive fewer nominations. Some thus argue for randomizing name orders or sampling peer names for survey rosters. We model order effects as biases in nomination choices and demonstrate observational and experimental methods for assessing these biases and illuminating their mechanisms. Employing these lenses, we find little evidence of order effects on eight sociometric questions in four middle school cohorts over six waves. To inform future work, we investigate aspects of the survey situation that may amplify or attenuate order effects. Analyzing these moderating forces offers guidance for detecting, understanding, and mitigating order effects in future research.
WOS:001062856000001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="51">
<title>Network Canvas: Key decisions in the design of an interviewer-assisted network data collection software suite (Reprinted from vol 66, pages 114-124, 2021)</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.01.006</url>
<snippet>Self-reported social network analysis studies are often complex and burdensome, both during the interview process itself, and when conducting data management following the interview. Through funding obtained from the National Institute on Drug Abuse (NIDA/NIH), our team developed the Network Canvas suite of software - a set of complementary tools that are designed to simplify the collection and storage of complex social network data, with an emphasis on usability and accessibility across platforms and devices, and guided by the practical needs of researchers. The suite consists of three applications: Architect: an application for researchers to design and export interview protocols; Interviewer: a touch-optimized application for loading and administering interview protocols to study participants; and Server: an application for researchers to manage the interview deployment process and export their data for analysis. Together, they enable researchers with minimal tech-nological expertise to access a complete research workflow, by building their own network interview protocols, deploying these protocols widely within a variety of contexts, and immediately attaining the resulting data from a secure central location. In this paper, we outline the critical decisions taken in developing this suite of tools for the network research community. We also describe the work which guides our decision-making, including prior experiences and key discovery events. We focus on key design choices, taken for theoretical, philosophical, and pragmatic reasons, and outline their strengths and limitations.
WOS:000777028500009
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="52">
<title>Charting the hidden City: Collecting prison social network data</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2019.09.005</url>
<snippet>Penologists have long emphasized the importance of studying social relationships among prisoners to understand how people adapt to confinement. While several penological traditions clearly implicate social networks as an explanatory mechanism, network methods have rarely been applied in prison research. We suspect that prison scholars have been slow to incorporate social networks into their research because of the challenges-both real and perceived-of collecting social network data in the prison setting. In this article, we argue that successfully collecting network data from prisoners can be achieved by carefully adapting methods to the peculiarities and constraints of the prison setting. We draw upon experiences from the Prison Inmate Networks Study (PINS) and its associated projects in five Pennsylvania prisons to construct a framework for understanding and overcoming the obstacles to network data collection in prisons.
WOS:000777028500002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="53">
<title>She Must Be Seeing Things! Gender disparity in camera department networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2023.09.004</url>
<snippet>This paper reports on a network-based investigation of the gendered nature of work in the screen sector. Using nine years of Australian film and television production data, we explore how the networks of project-based collaboration might explain the disparities in the career trajectories of men and women. Our analysis finds that projects with men as directors tend to reproduce familiar teams to the exclusion of women, while projects led by women in key creative roles tend to make more space for women. Moreover, we find that there is a significant number of men who only work with men (regardless of whether they have worked with them before), but no corresponding group of women who only work with women. Our findings bear on proposed equity interventions, especially government policies designed to encourage women to enter the industry. Ultimately, even accounting for the statistical domination of men in the network, we argue that inequities in the organisation of the screen sector appear to be driven much more by the closed network behaviours of men than they are by the positioning or behaviour of women.
WOS:001081842800001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="54">
<title>Socio-economic segregation in a population-scale social network</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2024.02.005</url>
<snippet>We propose a social network -aware approach to study socio-economic segregation. The key question that we address is whether patterns of segregation are more pronounced in social networks than in the common spatial neighborhood -focused manifestations of segregation. We, therefore, conduct a population -scale social network analysis to study socio-economic segregation at a comprehensive and highly granular social network level. For this, we utilize social network data from Statistics Netherlands on 17.2 million registered residents of the Netherlands that are connected through around 1.3 billion ties distributed over five distinct tie types. We take income assortativity as a measure of socio-economic segregation, compare a social network and spatial neighborhood approach, and find that the social network structure exhibits two times as much segregation. As such, this work complements the spatial perspective on segregation in both literature and policymaking. While at a widely used unit of spatial aggregation (e.g., the geographical neighborhood), patterns of socioeconomic segregation may appear relatively minimal, they may in fact persist in the underlying social network structure. Furthermore, we discover higher social network segregation in larger cities, shedding a different light on the common view of cities as hubs for diverse socio-economic mixing. A population -scale social network perspective hence offers a way to uncover hitherto "hidden"segregation that extends beyond spatial neighborhoods and infiltrates multiple aspects of human life.
WOS:001232374700001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="55">
<title>Same but different A comparison of estimation approaches for exponential random graph models for multiple networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2023.05.003</url>
<snippet>The Exponential Random Graph family of models (ERGM) is a powerful tool for social science research as it allows for the simultaneous modeling of endogenous network characteristics and exogenous variables such as gender, age, and socioeconomic status. However, a major limitation of ERGM is that it is mainly used for descriptive analysis of a single network. This paper examines two methods for estimating multiple networks: hierarchical and integrated. We contrast the two approaches, evaluate their accuracy and discuss the advantages and drawbacks of each. Furthermore, we make recommendations for future researchers on how to proceed with multiple network analysis depending on various factors such as the number of networks and the hierarchical structure of the data. This research is important as it highlights the need for the analysis of multiple networks in order to gain a more comprehensive understanding of social phenomena and the potential for new discoveries.
WOS:001012428000001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="56">
<title>Bayesian nonparametric mixtures of Exponential Random Graph Models for ensembles of networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2023.03.005</url>
<snippet>Ensembles of networks arise in various fields where multiple independent networks are observed, for example, a collection of student networks from different classes. However, there are few models that describe both the variations and characteristics of networks in an ensemble at the same time. In this manuscript, we propose to model ensembles of networks using a Dirichlet Process Mixture of Exponential Random Graph Models (DPM-ERGMs), which divides an ensemble into different clusters and models each cluster of networks using a separate Exponential Random Graph Model (ERGM). By employing a Dirichlet process mixture, the number of clusters can be determined automatically and changed adaptively with the data provided. Moreover, in order to perform full Bayesian inference for DPM-ERGMs, we develop a Metropolis-within-slice sampling algorithm to address the problem of sampling from the intractable ERGMs on an infinite sample space. We also demonstrate the performance of DPM-ERGMs with both simulated and real datasets.
WOS:000969755400001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="57">
<title>Social network research in health care settings: Design and data collection</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2019.11.004</url>
<snippet>Social network research can help us understand intractable problems central to the challenges of todays health care system: silo-working, bottlenecks, gaps, poor communication, professional isolation, and other social processes with the propensity to compromise patient safety and quality care. In this paper, we discuss practical and ethical challenges to designing and collecting quality network data faced by health services researchers. The paper develops high-utility recommendations to address these challenges. Design decisions are discussed in light of the dynamism and complexity of health care and the need for more longitudinal, mixed-methods network studies.
WOS:000777556900003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="58">
<title>A network-based explanation of inequality perceptions</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.02.007</url>
<snippet>Across income groups and countries, individual citizens perceive economic inequality spectacularly wrong. These misperceptions have far-reaching consequences, as it might be perceived inequality, not actual inequality informing redistributive preferences. The prevalence of this phenomenon is independent of social class and welfare regime, which suggests the existence of a common mechanism behind public perceptions. The literature has identified several stylised facts on how individual perceptions respond to actual inequality and how these biases vary systematically along the income distribution. We propose a network-based explanation of perceived inequality building on recent advances in random geometric graph theory. The generating mechanism can replicate all of aforementioned stylised facts simultaneously. It also produces social networks that exhibit salient features of real-world networks; namely, they cannot be statistically distinguished from small-world networks, testifying to the robustness of our approach. Our results, therefore, suggest that homophilic segregation is a promising candidate to explain inequality perceptions with strong implications for theories of consumption and voting behaviour.
WOS:000793127500001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="59">
<title>Towards a general method to classify personal network structures</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2024.03.004</url>
<snippet>In this study, we present a method to uncover the fundamental dimensions of structural variability in Personal Networks (PNs) and develop a classification solely based on these structural properties. We address the limitations of previous literature and lay the foundation for a rigorous methodology to construct a Structural Typology of PNs. We test our method with a dataset of nearly 8,000 PNs belonging to high school students. We find that the structural variability of these PNs can be described in terms of six basic dimensions encompassing community and cohesive subgroup structure, as well as levels of cohesion, hierarchy, and centralization. Our method allows us to categorize these PNs into eight types and to interpret them structurally. We assess the robustness and generality of our methodology by comparing with previous results on structural typologies. To encourage its adoption, its improvement by others, and to support future research, we provide a publicly available Python class, enabling researchers to utilize our method and test the universality of our results.
WOS:001227794300001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="60">
<title>How adolescents' popularity perceptions change: Measuring interactions between popularity and friendship networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2023.10.004</url>
<snippet>Longitudinal multivariate social network analysis (N=3692 adolescents; 136 classrooms) showed that adolescents were more likely to perceive their friends as popular but did not choose peers that they perceived to be popular as friends. Adolescents aligned their perceptions of popularity with their friends. Adolescents who received many popularity nominations attracted more popularity but not more friendship. Friends of peers seen as popular by an individual were more likely to be seen as popular by that individual. These results highlight the importance of describing popularity as a network, exploring dyadic, triadic, and group processes separately.
WOS:001113555400001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="61">
<title>Stochastic actor oriented model with random effects</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2024.01.002</url>
<snippet>The stochastic actor oriented model (SAOM) is a method for modelling social interactions and social behaviour over time. It can be used to model drivers of dynamic interactions using both exogenous covariates and endogenous network configurations, but also the co -evolution of behaviour and social interactions. In its standard implementations, it assumes that all individual have the same interaction evaluation function. This lack of heterogeneity is one of its limitations. The aim of this paper is to extend the inference framework for the SAOM to include random effects, so that the heterogeneity of individuals can be modelled more accurately. We decompose the linear evaluation function that models the probability of forming or removing a tie from the network, in a homogeneous fixed part and a random, individual -specific part. We extend the algorithm so that the variance of the random parameters can be estimated with method of moments. Our method is applicable for the general random effect formulations. We illustrate the method with a random out -degree model and show the parameter estimation of the random components, significance tests and model evaluation. We apply the method to the Kapferers Tailor shop study. It is shown that a random out -degree constitutes a serious alternative to including transitivity and higher -order dependency effects.
WOS:001172463300001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="62">
<title>Limited opportunities: Adolescents' access to social capital in secondary schools in three European countries</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2023.05.001</url>
<snippet>While previous research indicates that students benefit from their peers resources, little is known about access to social capital in the school context. Therefore, this study examines differential access to social capital - measured by friends socioeconomic status (SES), the number of books they have at home, and their reading habits - in secondary schools in Germany, the Netherlands, and Sweden. Relying on a large-scale dataset, I investigate the association between socioeconomic status, minority status, and social capital using complete friendship network information. I argue that social capital access is connected to a two-stage process consisting of school sorting and friendship selection. To differentiate between these two processes, I apply within-between random effects (REWB). The models show that friendship selection is much less relevant for access to social capital than school sorting. Results indicate that while high-SES students have better access to social capital across dimensions, access patterns for minority students are more nuanced.
WOS:001001716400001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="63">
<title>Theorizing the concept of social tie using frames</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2024.01.001</url>
<snippet>In classical Social Network Analysis (SNA), what counted as a "social tie" was fixed by available data collection methods. The emergence of large-scale unobtrusive data collection techniques has sparked renewed interest in the very idea of what counts as a "social tie." Importantly, there has been an acknowledgment that the core issues raised by these developments are primarily conceptual. As a result, there is renewed interest in developing a scientifically grounded characterization of what is arguably the most central concept in social network analysis. This paper contributes to this conceptual effort. I rely on a technique of conceptual representation borrowed from cognitive psychology and cognitive linguistics in which frames for concepts are represented as directed graphs linking attributes to values. I show how the frame representation helps clarify the sort of claims that network theories make (e.g., imposing restrictions on attributes and values), how it helps specify both intra and inter -conceptual relations, how it illuminates seldom noted inter -theoretical commonalities and contrasts, and how it helps avoid common conceptual pitfalls.
WOS:001166388800001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="64">
<title>Trust, quality, and the network collection experience: A tale of two studies on the Democratic Republic of the Congo</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.08.002</url>
<snippet>Data collection in social network research has advanced to include online questionnaires, digital metadata mining of internet sites, and the use of remote-sensing technologies. Some scholars however call for more attention to nuanced understandings of ties and contexts in studies of social structure and relationships, evoking practices that characterise the fields foundational works. This articles two studies reference these earlier efforts, drawing on ethnography and primary data collection. Both were undertaken in conflict-affected eastern Democratic Republic of the Congo (DRC) and broadly aimed to refine understandings of public authority and governance. Such research strives to inform humanitarian interventions to support social structures and actors which benefit their communities - however unexpected and unconventional. The first study (2016) employed a novel link-tracing design to examine personal support networks entwining purportedly hostile sub-populations, from combatants to unaffiliated civilians. The second (2018-20) focussed on access to essential social services across different governance arrangements, areas dominated by tenuous alliances of domestic or foreign militias and other actors. Leveraging an egocentric network design, it yielded multilevel relational network chain data. Each study was rife with obstacles related to accessing participants, sampling, reliability, and validity. We reflect on this network collection experience, foregrounding the interdependence between trust and data quality brought into stark relief by the settings instability and insecurity. This interdependency impacts all social network research, especially when it involves precarious contexts or sensitive topics.
WOS:000702773800001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="65">
<title>Categorical closure: Transitivity and identities in longitudinal networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2024.06.004</url>
<snippet>This research examines whether categorical closure - an increased tendency for closure in homogeneous triads - matters for tie formation and tie persistence. We utilized 2019-2020 panel data on students networks at three law schools and employed separable temporal exponential random graph models to examine whether closed triads with shared identities were more likely to form and to persist over time. We also investigated whether closed triads based on shared organizational assignments were associated with lower likelihoods of tie formation and tie persistence over time. Results supported the notion that law students were more likely to form homogeneous closed triads based on shared categories, particularly family background, gender, and race, while closed triads based on organizational assignments were less likely. Closed triads tended to persist over time, but there was some support for the notion that homogeneous closed triads based on family background, college rank, and sexuality were more durable. This study highlights categorical closure as an additional network mechanism giving rise to homogenous groups.
WOS:001264836000001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="66">
<title>Network ecology: Tie fitness in social context(s)</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2023.09.005</url>
<snippet>Social relations are embedded in material, cultural, and institutional settings that affect network dynamics and the resulting topologies. For example, romantic entanglements are subject to social and cultural norms, interfirm alliances are constrained by country-specific legislation, and adolescent friendships are conditioned by classroom settings and neighborhood effects. In short, social contexts shape social relations and the networks they give rise to. However, how and when they do so remain to be established. This paper presents network ecology as a general framework for identifying how the proximal environment shapes social networks by focusing interactions and social relations, and how these interactions and relations in turn shape the environment in which social networks form. Tie fitness is introduced as a metric that quantifies how well particular dyadic social relations would align with the setting. Using longitudinal networks collected on two cohorts each in 18 North American schools, i.e., 36 settings, we develop five generalizable observations about the time-varying fitness of adolescent friendship. Across all 252 analyzed networks, tie fitness predicted new tie formation, tie longevity, and tie survival. Dormant fit ties cluster in relational niches, thereby establishing a resource base for social identities competing for increased representation in the relational system.
WOS:001089067400001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="67">
<title>Building trust and co-designing a study of trust and co-operation: Observations from a network study in a high-risk, high-security environment</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.06.005</url>
<snippet>As part of a larger project on trust and co-operation in IT-Security, the author collected network data from an international security team specialized in cyber-incident response, leading to the only dataset of its kind. Collecting these data involved a number of challenges. First, the team in question had recently been established and was based in a large international firm. Thus, the author had to navigate legal and procedural issues, and stay on top of a changing environment. Second, actors in IT-Security are acutely aware of how data can be misused, requiring the author to build trust and demonstrate appropriate data handling. Attaining support from security managers was a key step to build trust with participants and the host organization. Third, precautions were necessary due to the project's security implications, as the study data could be abused by adversaries. Consequentially, it was necessary to engage in a co-design process, negotiating technical and procedural precautions. Not all measures initially agreed upon were feasible in practice.
WOS:000777556900013
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="68">
<title>Multiple types of friends and life stage differences in friendship</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.06.001</url>
<snippet>Much research on the life-course measures friend ties using a single aspect of relationships. This measurement has enabled the delineation of friendship networks and the application of rigorous network analysis tools, but at the expense of neglecting the multidimensionality of friendships. As an alternative, this study suggests identi-fying and differentiating multiple types of friends based on friendships multifaceted nature. Analysis using the University of California, Berkeley, Social Networks Survey demonstrates that both young (20-30-year-old) and older (50-70-year-old) people have four distinct types of friends. The conventional "close and supportive friends" or "new friends" only account for half the friendship types. In addition, younger people, particularly married and low-income ones, have friends with whom they do not actively interact, despite the intimacy, proximity, and long tenure of the relationships. Among older people, many friends are not emotionally close despite knowing each other for a long time and living nearby. This type of friendship constitutes a higher proportion in sparse networks and the networks of married, retired, low-income, and non-white older adults. The age group differ-ences in friend types and their distribution are discussed, focusing on different social foci for friend activities between young and older adults.
WOS:000861374000002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="69">
<title>Routine action networks: An architectural study of spatial layouts and performativity in outpatient clinics</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.12.004</url>
<snippet>Social network analysis offers powerful ways to investigate personal relationships, however, to date little work has explored the more routinized, impersonal work processes present in bureaucratic organizations. Asking whether network analysis has insights to offer into routine work, this paper investigates a data set of direct observations of diagnostic care processes in ten outpatient clinics of two different hospitals. Instead of networks of agents, this study constructs so called action networks, tying together sequences of tasks into networks structures. Following the strong social networks tradition of considering contexts, this paper examines the architectural layout of a setting as key variable. Drawing in particular on ecological approaches to the study of networks by focusing on variability, it is hypothesized that the spatial configuration of clinics is associated with performativity, i.e., a more varied set of sequences to emerge within more open-plan layouts. Results indicate that this is the case, showing how different sets of routines emerge in different types of layout depending on their spatial openness. Variability in routinization is also found between doctors, nurses and clerks, highlighting ecological niches. Network density as well as edge-weighted centralization turned out to be useful metrics for performativity. The work presented contributes to the study of bureaucratic organizations, making a case that social network methods can be fruitfully applied to impersonal, routinized and rule-driven relations.
WOS:001188415900001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="70">
<title>Networks of context: Three-layer socio-cultural mapping for a &lt;i&gt;Verstehende&lt;/i&gt; network analysis</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.03.003</url>
<snippet>What social ties are and how they operate depends on the cultural context constitutive of their meaning. Pursuing an explanatory account for the cultural embeddedness of social ties, we draw on Verstehende sociology and rely on indepth insight into subjective perceptions developed by social network actors throughout their practice to represent symbolic and material contexts of social ties structurally. We put forward a new mixed data collection and processing approach that ethnographically maps interconnected three-layer socio-cultural networks of individuals, signs, and material objects. Opening cultural contexts to application of formal and statistical techniques, this approach allows for an interpretive explanation of social ties. Illustrating the approach with our own longitudinal study of five European art groups, we discuss the peculiarities of three-layer socio-cultural data collection and processing, the new discoveries enabled, the challenges encountered, the solutions we came up with, and the utility of this approach for conducting Verstehende network analysis in various fields of application.
WOS:000777556900009
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="71">
<title>Status, cognitive overload, and incomplete information in advice-seeking networks: An agent-based model</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2023.09.001</url>
<snippet>Advice-seeking typically occurs across organizational boundaries through informal connections. By using Stochastic Actor-Oriented Models (SAOM), previous research has tried to identify the micro-level mechanisms behind these informal connections. Unfortunately, these models assume perfect network information, require agents to perform too cognitively demanding decisions, and do not account for threshold-based critical events, such as simultaneous tie changes. In the context of knowledge-intensive organizations, the shortage of high skilled professionals could determine complex network effects given that many less-skilled professionals would seek advice from a few easily overloaded, selective high-skilled, who are also sensitive to status demotion. To capture these context-specific organizational features, we have elaborated on SAOM with an agent-based model that assumes local information, status-based tie selection, and simultaneous re-direction of multiple ties. By fitting our simulated networks to Lazegas advice network used in previous research, we reproduced the same set of macro-level network metrics with a parsimonious model based on more empirically plausible assumptions than previous research. Our findings show the advantage of exploring multiple generative paths of network formation with different models.
WOS:001084734900001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="72">
<title>Too many options: How to identify coalitions in a policy network?</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2024.06.005</url>
<snippet>For different currents in policy analysis as policy networks and the Advocacy Coalition Framework (ACF), identifying coalitions from policy beliefs and coordination between actors is crucial to a precise understanding of a policy process. Focusing particularly the relational dimension of ACF approaches linked with policy network analysis, determining policy subsystems from the actor collaborations and exchanges has recently begun offering fertile links with the network analysis. Studies in this way frequently apply Block Modeling and Community Detection (BMCD) strategies to define homogeneous political groups. However, the BMCD literature is growing quickly, using a wide variety of algorithms and interesting selection methods that are much more diverse than those used in the policy network analysis and particularly the ACF when this current focused on the collaboration networks before or after regarding the belief distance between actors. Identifying the best methodological option in a specific context can therefore be difficult and few ACF studies give an explicit justification. On the other hand, few BMCD publications offer a systematic comparison of real social networks and they are never applied to policy network datasets. This paper offers a new, relevant 5-Step selection method to reconcile advances in both the policy networks/ACF and BMCD. Using an application based on original African policy network data collected in Madagascar and Niger, we provide a useful set of practical recommendations for future ACF studies using policy network analysis: (i) the density and size of the policy network affect the identification process, (ii) the "best algorithm"can be rigorously determined by maximizing a novel indicator based on convergence and homogeneity between algorithm results, (iii) researchers need to be careful with missing data: they affect the results and imputation does not solve the problem.
WOS:001267164900001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="73">
<title>NETWORK IMPACT OF SOCIAL INNOVATION INITIATIVES IN MARGINALISED RURAL COMMUNITIES</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.04.001</url>
<snippet>The marginalised rural communities are characterised by societal challenges, such as isolation, lack of job opportunities, land abandonment, low quality of life and generally low education. Social Innovation (SI) initiatives may represent an opportunity to strengthen relationships among the members of rural community, by means of the alteration of the existing social networks. In this way, more exchange of information is expected, paving the way for the creation of professional collaborations among firms and other actors. This paper aims at proposing a short-term evaluation framework of effectiveness of a SI initiative in terms of reconfiguration of the social network structure. The described empirical case study is VaZapp, a rural hub located in Southern Italy, which provides innovative solutions to activate social relations amongst farmers, altering hence their network. A well-referenced SI theoretical model, developed within the H2020 project SIMRA (Social Innovation in Marginalised Rural Areas), and the methodology of Social Network Analysis (SNA) were used to verify and measure quantitative and qualitative indicators affected by network intervention activated by VaZapp initiative. Results show that this SI initiative worked effectively, leading to a +308&#37; in the number of relations and +250&#37; in social network density. In addition, an evident improvement in the quality of the social relations was found, especially in cases where there are direct engagements within VaZapp. Outcomes suggest that supporting and promoting SI initiatives could become a central discussion point for the rethinking of rural development policies focused on regeneration of social relations structure.
WOS:000563919700002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="74">
<title>Re-print of: Contextualizing oppositional cultures: A multilevel network analysis of status orders in schools</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2023.11.001</url>
<snippet>Different lines of research have argued that specific groups, such as boys or ethnic minorities, are more prone to develop an anti-school culture than others, leading to group differences in the social acceptance of high performers. Taking an ecological view, we ask to what extent the school context promotes or prevents the emergence of group-specific oppositional cultures. Theoretically, we argue that group-based oppositional cultures become more likely in schools with low socio-economic resources and in schools where socio-economic differences align with demographic attributes. We test our hypotheses based on data from a large-scale, four-wave network panel survey among more than 4000 students in Germany. Applying stochastic actor-oriented models for the coevolution of networks and behavior, we find that group-based oppositional cultures in which students like high performers less are very rare. However, in line with theoretical expectations, the less resourceful a school is, the more boys tend to evaluate high-performing peers less positively than girls do. Moreover, the more ethnic minority boys are socioeconomically disdvantaged in a school, the more they tend to evaluate high performers less positively than majority boys do.
WOS:001188248700001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="75">
<title>Imaginary network motifs: Structural patterns of false positives and negatives in social networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2023.11.005</url>
<snippet>We examine the structural patterns in the cognitive representation of social networks by systematically classifying false positives and negatives. Although existing literature on Cognitive Social Structures (CSS) has begun exploring false positives and negatives by comparing actual and perceived networks, it has not differentiated simultaneous occurrences of true and false positives and negatives on network motifs, such as reciprocity and triadic closure. Here, we propose a theoretical framework to categorize three classes of errors we call imaginary network motifs as combinations of accurately and erroneously perceived ties: (a) partially false, (b) completely false, and 
WOS:001138468100001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="76">
<title>Participant engagement in environmentally focused social network research</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.01.005</url>
<snippet>Environmentally focused social network analysis (Env. SNA) has increasingly benefited from engagement, which refers to the process of incorporating the individuals, organizations, actors, stakeholders or other study participants into the research process. Research about engagement in the wider field of environmental management shows that successful engagement often requires significant planning and exchange among researchers and stakeholders. While there is no one size fits all approach, several important guiding principles have been established. To date, this engagement literature has not focused specifically on SNA, even though several examples of engaged SNA exist in the literature and point to some specific challenges to engagement when working with relational data. Drawing upon data from a survey of researchers who have incorporated engagement into Env. SNA, we focus specifically on the goals, scope, effectiveness, benefits and challenges of doing engaged Env. SNA research. We additionally highlight four case studies and demonstrate that researchers and participants find engagement to be a valuable experience with benefits in the researchers understanding of the context and meaning of their findings. Finally, we provide recommendations to scholars looking to embark on engaged Env. SNA research.
WOS:000648645200011
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="77">
<title>Network sampling coverage III: Imputation of missing network data under different network and missing data conditions</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.05.002</url>
<snippet>Missing data is a common, difficult problem for network studies. Unfortunately, there are few clear guidelines about what a researcher should do when faced with incomplete information. We take up this problem in the third paper of a three-paper series on missing network data. Here, we compare the performance of different imputation methods across a wide range of circumstances characterized in terms of measures, networks and missing data types. We consider a number of imputation methods, going from simple imputation to more complex modelbased approaches. Overall, we find that listwise deletion is almost always the worst option, while choosing the best strategy can be difficult, as it depends on the type of missing data, the type of network and the measure of interest. We end the paper by offering a set of practical outputs that researchers can use to identify the best imputation choice for their particular research setting.
WOS:000700623500013
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="78">
<title>Down and out? the role of household income in students' friendship formation in school-classes</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2023.12.003</url>
<snippet>Research suggests that coming from a lower economic background compromises social integration at school, yet the precise mechanisms underlying this link remain unknown. Therefore, this study examined the effect of household income on friendship network dynamics among classmates in a large sample of Swedish youths (n = 4787 from 235 classes, m age = 14.65, 51&#37; girls, and 33&#37; immigrant background), using multilevel longitudinal social network analysis. Over time, students from poorer households were less often selected as a friend by classmates and they less often initiated or maintained friendship ties than students from higher income households. Furthermore, different conceptualizations of income relative to classmates did not impact friendship formation tendencies. The findings indicate that theories of relative income do not extend understanding of students friendship formation beyond processes related to absolute income. In addition, this study suggests that the social integration of students from low-income households could be boosted by both promoting their agency in forming friendships and preventing exclusion by classmates.
WOS:001154638300001
</snippet>
</document>

</searchresult>
