<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<searchresult>
<query>Global</query>
<document id="1">
<title>What's in the "old boys" network? Accessing social capital in gendered and racialized networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2011.10.002</url>
<snippet>Network processes have long been implicated in the reproduction of labor market inequality, but it remains unclear whether white male networks provide more social capital resources than female and minority networks. Analysis of nationally representative survey data reveals that people in white male networks receive twice as many job leads as people in female/minority networks. White male networks are also comprised of higher status connections than female/minority networks. The information and status benefits of membership in these old boy networks accrue to all respondents and not just white men. Furthermore, gender homophilous contacts offer greater job finding assistance than other contacts. The results specify how social capital flows through gendered and racialized networks. (C) 2011 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000298122200007
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="2">
<title>Social networks and labour market outcomes in a meritocracy</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2010.08.001</url>
<snippet>This paper examines the significance of personal contacts in job searches, in the context of Singapores meritocratic system. I show that in certain sectors, such as the state bureaucracy, social networking brings no distinct advantages as appointments are made exclusively on the basis of the academic credentials of the candidates. Thus, personal contacts are not always useful, especially in labour markets that rely heavily on the signalling role of academic credentials to match persons to jobs and allocate rewards. In contrast, personal contacts are more useful among less qualified job searchers in the private sector. (C) 2010 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000291962000001
</snippet>
</document>

</searchresult>
