<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<searchresult>
<query>Global</query>
<document id="1">
<title>Raising network resources while raising children? Access to social capital by parenthood status, gender, and marital status</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2011.12.005</url>
<snippet>Does raising non-adult children facilitate or restrict access to social capital as network resources? Using data from a national sample of adults in the United States, I do not find evidence for the direct effect of parenthood on the three dimensions of social capital (diversity, extensity, and quality), but instead I find evidence for its interaction effects on the quality of social capital. There is marginal evidence that parenthood status is associated with the quality of social capital positively for men but negatively for women. There is evidence that parenthood status is associated with the quality of social capital positively for the married but negatively for the unmarried. Also parenthood status is associated with the quality of social capital negatively for unmarried women but positively for the other three gender-marital groups, in particular unmarried men. These findings suggest the structural interplay of parenthood status with gender and marital status, and indicate the motherhood penalty, the fatherhood premium, the single-parenthood penalty, the married-parenthood premium, and the single-motherhood penalty in reaching higher-quality, rather than more diverse and extensive, social capital. (C) 2012 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000302394600009
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="2">
<title>A structured overview of 50 years of small-world research</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2008.12.004</url>
<snippet>This paper offers a structured overview of 50 years of small-world research. Initially formulated by Pool and Kochen in the mid-1950s, the small-world concept can be divided into six research foci, based on three dimensions (structural, process-related, psychological), and two process-related themes (diffusion, search). Building on this analytical distinction, the article provides a historical summary of the different phases of research on the small-world problem, and summarizes the empirical and theoretical progress on different facets of the small-world phenomenon. The paper concludes with a brief assessment of accomplishments and open questions, suggesting some possible future research areas. (C) 2009 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000267838900001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="3">
<title>Longitudinal analysis of personal networks. The case of Argentinean migrants in Spain</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2009.05.001</url>
<snippet>This paper discusses and illustrates various approaches for the longitudinal analysis of personal networks (multilevel analysis, regression analysis, and SIENA). We combined the different types of analyses in a study of the changing personal networks of immigrants. Data were obtained from 25 Argentineans in Spain, who were interviewed twice in a 2-year interval. Qualitative interviews were used to estimate the amount of measurement error and to isolate important predictors. Quantitative analyses showed that the persistence of ties was explained by tie strength, network density, and alters Country of origin and residence. Furthermore, transitivity appeared to be an important tendency, both for acquiring new contacts and for the relationships among alters. At the network level, immigrants networks were remarkably stable in composition and structure despite the high turnover. Clustered graphs have been used to illustrate the results. The results are discussed in light of adaptation to the host society. (C) 2009 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000274948700009
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="4">
<title>You are who remembers you. Detecting leadership through accuracy of recall</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2009.07.001</url>
<snippet>We measured interpersonal perception accuracy by focusing on the relationship between actors centrality and their ability to accurately report their social interactions. We used the network measures of actors betweenness centrality and degree centrality to identify the most prominent members by correlating ego-perception and alter-perception in a "non-reciprocity" type of misalignment. We found a positive correlation between actors centrality and their centrality as assessed by senior management, and a negative correlation between actors centrality and their accuracy in recalling interactions. Under-reporting social interactions may represent a third way of measuring the importance of members and finding the most influential actors. (C) 2009 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000269995400004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="5">
<title>Impact of methods for reducing respondent burden on personal network structural measures</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2006.12.005</url>
<snippet>We examine methods for reducing respondent burden in evaluating alter-alter ties on a set of network structural measures. The data consist of two sets, each containing 45 alters from respondent free lists: the first contains 447 personal networks, and the second 554. Respondents evaluated the communication between 990 alter pairs. The methods were (1) dropping alters from the end of the free-list, (2) randomly dropping alters, (3) randomly dropping links, and (4) predicting ties based on transitivity. For some measures network structure is captured with samples of less than 20 alters; other measures are less consistent. Researchers should be aware of the need to sample a minimum number of alters to capture structural variation. 
WOS:000246430600009
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="6">
<title>A small world on feet of clay? A comparison of empirical small-world studies against best-practice criteria</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2008.12.005</url>
<snippet>Small-world studies were introduced by Milgram and others in the 1960s and 1970s. These studies, and a majority of variants conducted by others, display a number of methodological weaknesses that bias their results. While no explicit methodological standard exists for these studies, here I derive a number of best-practice criteria for small-world studies by pointing out mistakes of previous studies, and by applying methodological standards from other empirical research areas. Improving the methodology of letter referral studies is important, because such studies could still be useful in a number of contexts today, especially for the exploration of factors affecting targeted search processes. (C) 2009 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000267838900002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="7">
<title>The structure of norms and relations in patronage systems</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2007.04.003</url>
<snippet>Patronage systems are composed of a social relation (between patron and client), the norms associated with this relation (support, defend, not attack), and network-formation rules (governing the creation of patronage ties). Actors in a patronage system face moral dilemmas when they become obligated to fight on both sides of a conflict, and patronage systems are normatively consistent when these dilemmas can never arise. This paper examines the structure of normatively consistent patronage systems, exploring the logical relationships among norms and between norms and network structure. The paper illustrates how sociologically relevant concerns from deontic logic can be incorporated into network analysis using algebraic methods familiar to network analysts. (C) 2007 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000250964800007
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="8">
<title>Don't mention it: Why people don't share job information, when they do, and why it matters</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2011.11.002</url>
<snippet>Network-based job search is especially likely to foster workplace segregation and limit status attainment when information flows through homophilous ties. This paper takes the perspective of information holders and examines how the use of strong versus weak ties - which tend to be homophilous and heterophilous, respectively - differs with characteristics of labour markets in which jobs are located. Using in-depth interviews with entry-level white collar workers I show that information holders with opportunities to mention specific jobs to specific people do so only 27&#37; of the time. Because they hesitate to share information if they are uncertain the information is specifically sought, information flows more commonly to strong ties, whose career goals are more likely to be known. Information is more likely to be shared with weak ties if it concerns occupations for which one may be specifically credentialed, since receiving relevant training serves as signal of interest in such jobs. These finding suggest that the homophily of referrals and their inequality-generating effects may vary across occupations. (C) 2011 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000302394600004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="9">
<title>Closeness, loneliness, support: Core ties and significant ties in personal communities</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2011.12.001</url>
<snippet>Past research has introduced further distinctions within the strong ties that form our personal communities. This work aimed at a comparison between core and significant ties in terms of their emotional closeness to ego, the social provisions that are exchanged, the relationship maintenance behaviours reported, and egos loneliness. Measures for all these variables were assessed in a survey study. Evidence for a trade-off between the number of ties and their level of intimacy was obtained such that having more core ties was associated with lower levels of intimacy. Distinct signatures for friends from both sets of ties emerged for friendship maintenance behaviours and social provisions exchanged. Further, social and emotional loneliness were differentially related to the number and the intimacy of core and significant ties. (C) 2011 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000302394600006
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="10">
<title>Inequalities in social capital and their longitudinal effects on the labour market entry</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2014.10.001</url>
<snippet>This study investigates socio-economic and ethnic inequalities in social capital and their effects on the process of the labour market entry. We use longitudinal data about the transition from school to work of lower- and middle educated young people in Belgium. Social capital is measured with three robust position generator measures. In line with previous studies, there are substantial socioeconomic and ethnic inequalities in the access to social capital. Ethnic differences in social capital are, however, due to the socio-economic deprivation of ethnic minority groups in Belgium. Among the specific population of lower- and middle educated youth, knowing more people from the working class leads to a higher likelihood of entering the labour market versus continuing in education, whereas knowing more people from the higher service class results in a lower likelihood of entering the labour market. Especially the resources of strong ties such as relatives and friends are important for these decisions. In addition, once entered the labour market, social capital has an impact on the likelihood of getting a job. Lower- and middle educated labour market entrants who know more people from the working class are more likely to find work, whereas knowing people from the lower service class decreases the job chances. However, there is no evidence for social capital effects on the occupational status of the job among our population. 
WOS:000347585500017
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="11">
<title>Immigrant children and their parents: Is there an intergenerational interdependence of integration into social networks?</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2014.11.002</url>
<snippet>The paper investigates the integration of immigrant children and their parents in different dimensions of social networks - referred to as multiplexity in social network terminology. These dimensions are childrens friendships, their attendance at birthday parties, and contact among their parents. By attending birthday parties, childrens friendships are publicly reinforced and membership in a social circle is signified. During these events, communication and social exchange drive the process of social integration at the micro-level, and ethnic boundaries can be shifted or blurred. It will be shown that a variety of homophily effects can be found in all three network dimensions. In addition, ethnic segregation in parents networks has an impact on childrens participation in these events and, thereby, on childrens integration in social networks. However, the causal effect in the other way around - childrens birthday party attendance on contact among their parents - is even stronger. A new approach is the non-recursive analysis of how ties in one network dimension effect ties in another dimension. Analyses are based on 76 social networks of 1266 children in school classes in the city state of Bremen, Germany. 
WOS:000347585500019
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="12">
<title>Mediatizing the network model of cultural capital: Network diversity, media use, and cultural knowledge along and across ethnic boundaries</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2014.10.003</url>
<snippet>Existing studies have paid limited attention to how media use and network diversity are related to cultural capital along or across ethnic boundaries. Extending the network model to a mediated network model of cultural capital, this research examines cultural knowledge as a function of media use and network diversity and whether media use moderates or mediates the relationship between network diversity and cultural knowledge. Data were drawn from a random sample survey on Chinese immigrant entrepreneurs in Toronto. Results showed that media use was a stronger predictor of cultural knowledge than network diversity. It also moderated and mediated the relationship between network diversity and cultural knowledge along and across ethnic boundaries. 
WOS:000347585500018
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="13">
<title>The analysis of multiple ties in longitudinal egocentric network data: A case study on bidirectional relationships between trust and drug use</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2012.08.005</url>
<snippet>We extend multi-level models to examine single egocentric network ties to the joint analysis of paired dynamic ties. Two analytic challenges are addressed. First, inference needs to account for multiple layers of nesting: ties are nested within pairs, pairs are nested within time points, and time points are nested within egos. Second, the focus is on the relationship between two dynamic ties; specification of outcome and predictor may be difficult. Instead, we treat both ties as outcomes. Our approach is used to analyze trust and reported drug use between egos and alters over time in a Bayesian framework. (C) 2012 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000313304100031
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="14">
<title>Shared contexts and triadic closure in core discussion networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2011.09.001</url>
<snippet>This paper inquires into structural explanations for triadic closure in networks of confidants with whom one discusses important personal matters. Building upon the assumption that meeting opportunities affect network characteristics, we primarily argue that the social contexts in which network members meet, substantially affect triadic closure. The main empirical findings are (a) that about sixty percent of the triads in core discussion networks are closed triads, which also means that a substantial part of ones strong relations is unconnected, and (b) that meeting network members in the same social contexts is an important condition for, but certainly does not guarantee triadic closure. Importantly, the specific characteristics of social contexts explain why sharing certain contexts positively affects triadic closure, while sharing other contexts does not. (C) 2011 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000298122200005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="15">
<title>Social network analysis with respondent-driven sampling data: A study of racial integration on campus</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2009.09.002</url>
<snippet>This paper presents respondent-driven sampling (RDS) as a viable method of sampling and analyzing social networks with survey data. RDS is a network based sampling and analysis method that provides a middle ground compliment to ego-centric and saturated methods of social network analysis. The method provides survey data, similar to ego-centric approaches, on individuals who are connected by behaviorally documented ties, allowing for macro-level analysis of network structure, similar to that supported by saturated approaches. Using racial interaction of university undergraduates as an empirical example, the paper examines whether and to what extent racial diversity at the institutional level is reflected as racial integration at the interpersonal level by testing hypotheses regarding the quantity and quality of cross-race friendships. The primary goal of this article, however, is to introduce RDS to the network community and to stimulate further research toward the goal of expanding the analytical capacity of RDS. Advantages, limitations, and areas for future research to network analysis using RDS are discussed. (C) 2009 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000276669100002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="16">
<title>Do resources of network members help in help seeking? Social capital and health information search</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2012.08.002</url>
<snippet>Does social capital as resources of network members affect health information search? Analyzing data from the 2004 General Social Survey in the United States, this study measures two social capital indicators (average education of network members and proportion of network members with a high school degree or higher) using the name generator. Most results are consistent using those two indicators. Both indicators are positively associated with frequency of health information seeking and seekers frequency of use of two sources (friends or relatives and the Internet). Also average education of network members is positively associated with seekers diversity of used sources and frequency of consultation with medical professionals. But neither indicator is associated with seekers frequency of use of other four sources (health-related magazines or newsletters, general magazines, daily newspapers, and radio or television programs). The findings demonstrate the theoretical utility of social capital in the social dynamics of medical help-seeking. 
WOS:000313304100028
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="17">
<title>How stable is the core discussion network?</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2014.09.001</url>
<snippet>Researchers have paid increasing attention to the core discussion network, the set of people we turn to when discussing important matters. Because the core discussion network is theorized to be composed of peoples closest ties, not fleeting acquaintances, it is expected to be largely stable, evolving slowly over the span of peoples lives. However, recent studies have shown that networks are strongly affected by the contexts in which people interact with others, and as people experience life course transitions, they also often enter new contexts - school, college, work, marriage, and retirement. We ask whether, as actors enter new social contexts, the core discussion network remains stable or changes rapidly. Based on original, longitudinal, qualitative and quantitative data on the experience of first-year graduate students in three academic departments in a large university, we examine the stability of the core discussion network over the first 6 and 12 months in this new context. We test four competing hypotheses that focus on strength of ties, new opportunities, obligations, and routine activity and predict, respectively, stasis, expansion, shedding, and substitution. We find that the core discussion network changes remarkably quickly, with little or no lag, and that it appears to do so because both the obligations that people face and the routine activities they engage in are transformed by new institutional environments. Findings suggest that core discussion network may be less a "core" network than a highly contextual support network in which people are added and dropped as actors shift from environment to environment. 
WOS:000347585500010
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="18">
<title>A comparative study of social network models: Network evolution models and nodal attribute models</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2009.06.004</url>
<snippet>This paper reviews, classifies and compares recent models for social networks that have mainly been published within the physics-oriented complex networks literature. The models fall into two categories: those in which the addition of new links is dependent on the (typically local) network structure (network evolution models, NEMs), and those in which links are generated based only on nodal attributes (nodal attribute models, NAMs). An exponential random graph model (ERGM) with structural dependencies is included for comparison. We fit models from each of these categories to two empirical acquaintance networks with respect to basic network properties. We compare higher order structures in the resulting networks with those in the data, with the aim of determining which models produce the most realistic network structure with respect to degree distributions, assortativity, clustering spectra, geodesic path distributions, and community structure (subgroups with dense internal connections). We find that the nodal attribute models successfully produce assortative networks and very clear community structure. However, they generate unrealistic clustering spectra and peaked degree distributions that do not match empirical data on large social networks. On the other hand, many of the network evolution models produce degree distributions and clustering spectra that agree more closely with data. They also generate assortative networks and community structure, although often not to the same extent as in the data. The ERGM model, which turned out to be near-degenerate in the parameter region best fitting our data, produces the weakest community structure. (C) 2009 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000269995400003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="19">
<title>Structural holes and managerial performance: Identifying the underlying mechanisms</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2009.11.002</url>
<snippet>Structural holes theory suggests a variety of possible explanations for the empirically observed relationship between structural holes and individual managerial performance. However, little has been done to disentangle one mechanism from another. This paper empirically tests a mediated moderation model that distinguishes between the five different theoretical mechanisms: autonomy, competition, information brokering, opportunity recognition and innovativeness. The findings suggest that of these five theoretical causal motors, innovativeness plays a key role in linking network structure and network content to performance. (C) 2009 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000279409000002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="20">
<title>Entropy as a measure of centrality in networks characterized by path-transfer flow</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2006.10.001</url>
<snippet>Recently, Borgatti [Borgatti, S.P., 2005. Centrality and network flow. Social Networks 27, 55-71] proposed a taxonomy of centrality measures based on the way that traffic flows through the network-whether over path, geodesic, trail, or walk, and whether by means of transfer, serial duplication, or parallel duplication. Most of the extant centrality measures assume that traffic propagates via parallel duplication or, alternatively, that it travels over geodesics. Few of the other flow possibilities have centrality measures associated with them. This article proposes an entropy-based measure of centrality appropriate for traffic that propagates by transfer and flows along paths. The proposed measure can be applied to most network types, whether binary or weighted, directed or undirected, connected or disconnected. The measure is illustrated on the gang alliance network of Kennedy et al. [Kennedy, D.M., Braga, A. A., Piehl, A.M., 1998. The (un)known universe: mapping gangs and gang violence in Boston. Crime Prevention Studies 8, 219-262]. 
WOS:000246430600006
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="21">
<title>Network social capital as an outcome of social movement mobilization: Using the position generator as an indicator of social network diversity</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2011.12.007</url>
<snippet>In the social mobility literature, the position generator (PG) has been used to examine the relationship between the structural location of individuals. and outcomes such as obtaining a high status job. Diversity of occupational ties (as measured by the PG) is also a significant predictor of an individuals cultural capital. A great deal of work has also been done in the field of social movements examining the relationship between networks and mobilization. However, only limited attention has been given to the position generator in this literature. Also, while past research has demonstrated that prior network ties to activists is one of the most important predictors of current activism, relatively little research has been devoted to examining network structure as an outcome of activism. The present paper builds upon these insights by utilizing data collected with the position generator on a sample of environmental movement members, and examining the relationship between individual activism (as an independent variable) and diversity of occupational ties (as a dependent variable). The result of key theoretical significance is that those who are more active in the environmental movement develop a greater diversity of occupational ties to other environmentalists. Results suggest that this process occurs over time. These findings provide evidence that social capital (as indicated by network diversity) is one outcome of social movement mobilization. (C) 2012 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000313304100003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="22">
<title>A note on measures of similarity based on centrality</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2006.04.004</url>
<snippet>This note presents a measure of similarity between connected nodes in terms of centrality based on Euclidean distances, and compares it to assortative mixing [Newman, M.E.J., 2002. Assortative mixing in networks. Physical Review Letters 89, 208701], which is based on Pearson correlation coefficient. This study suggests that the measure based on Euclidean distances may be more appropriate for relatively smaller (N &lt; 500) and denser networks. 
WOS:000244397100011
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="23">
<title>Good health and the bridging of structural holes</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2008.10.005</url>
<snippet>Bridges that span structural holes are often explained in terms of the entrepreneurial personalities or rational motivations of brokers, or structural processes that lead to the intersection of social foci. I argue that the existence and use of bridges in interpersonal networks also depends on individuals health. Poor health may make it more difficult to withstand the pressures and to execute some of the common tasks associated with bridging(e.g., brokerage). I examine this possibility using egocentric network data on over 2500 older adults drawn from the recent National Social Life, Health, and Aging Project (NSHAP). Multivariate regression analyses show that both cognitive and functional health are significantly positively associated with bridging, net of sociodemographic and life-course controls. The relationship between functional (kinesthetic) health and bridging appears to be partially mediated by network composition, as older adults who have poorer functional health also tend to have networks that are richer in strong ties. Several potential mediation mechanisms are discussed. Cognitive function remains significantly associated with bridging net of network composition, Suggesting that the inherent challenges of maintaining bridging positions may be more difficult to cope with for those who have cognitive impairments than for those who have functional impairments such as limited mobility. An alternative explanation is that cognitively impaired individuals have more difficulty recognizing (and thus strategically using) bridges in their networks. Theoretical implications and possibilities for future research are discussed. 
WOS:000262547600010
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="24">
<title>Changes in personal relationships: How social contexts affect the emergence and discontinuation of relationships</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2013.12.003</url>
<snippet>Although the average number of confidants and practical helpers in Dutch networks only slightly changes over seven years, we found considerable changes among these relationships over these years. To explain the stability of existing relationships as well as the emergence of new ones, we paid attention to meeting opportunities in specific social contexts, such as the work place, family, sports clubs, voluntary associations, and the neighborhood. Notably, we found that a lack of meeting opportunities is an important reason why many personal relationships are discontinued, and that a path-dependent use of social contexts makes new relationships more likely to emerge in a specific context if existing network members are already met in that context. Finally, it is proposed that care should be taken when interpreting changes in personal networks if one relies on information about networks that are delineated using only one name generating question. (C) 2014 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000334001400006
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="25">
<title>Equicentrality and network centralization: A micro-macro linkage</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2007.07.004</url>
<snippet>This paper investigates a linkage between micro- and macrostructures as an intrinsic property of social networks. In particular, it examines the linkage between equicentrality [Kang, S.M., 2007. A note on measures of similarity based on centrality. Social Networks 29, 137-142] as a conceptualization of a microstructural process (i.e., the likelihood of social actors to be connected with similarly central others) and network centralization as a macrostructural construct, and shows that they have a negative linear association. In other words, when actors are connected with similarly central alters (i.e., high equicentrality), the overall network centralization is low. Conversely, when highly central actors are connected with low-centrality actors (i.e., low equicentrality), the overall network centralization is high. The relationship between degree equicentrality and degree centralization is more significant in observed networks, especially those evolving over time, as compared to random networks. An application of this property is given by venture capital co-investment networks. (C) 2007 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000250964800008
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="26">
<title>Small networks and high isolation? A reexamination of American discussion networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2011.10.003</url>
<snippet>Recent findings from the General Social Survey suggest that discussion networks have shrunk, and social isolation has increased, since 1985. These data have been threatened by possible artifacts, however, and may be unreliable. This paper reports on a nationally representative experiment that estimates discussion network size and evaluates several proposed explanations for the shrinking networks finding. It finds that modern discussion networks have decreased in size, but that social isolation has not become more prevalent. It also disconfirms several explanations for shrinking networks, and validates a method for increasing the number of names provided in response to name generators. (C) 2011 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000298122200008
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="27">
<title>Does the online collection of ego-centered network data reduce data quality? An experimental comparison</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2009.08.002</url>
<snippet>We analyze whether differences in kind and quality of ego-centered network data are related to whether the data are collected online or offline. We report the results of two studies. In the first study respondents could choose between filling out ego-centered data through a web questionnaire and being probed about their network in a personalized interview. The second study used a design in which respondents were allocated at random to either online or offline data collection. Our results show that the data quality suffers from the online data collection and the findings indicate that this is the consequence of the respondents answering "mechanically". We conclude that network researchers should avoid to simply COPY traditional network items into a web questionnaire. More research is needed about how new design elements specific for web questionnaires can motivate respondents to fill out network questions properly. (C) 2009 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000276669100001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="28">
<title>The network is personal:: Introduction to a special issue of &lt;i&gt;Social Networks&lt;/i&gt;</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2007.01.006</url>
<snippet>
WOS:000248429500001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="29">
<title>Name generation in interpersonal political network data: Results from a series of experiments</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2013.02.002</url>
<snippet>We present results from three large scale survey experiments focused on the manipulation of political name generators. Using syntax that is widely employed outside of political science, we generate interpersonal political network data by varying the roles of alters, the time horizons of relationships, and the specific political nature of social exchanges. Across varying samples and electoral environments, we look for differences in these conditions on a wide range of common interpersonal network items, assess latency data on these treatments, and employ more detailed information on named discussants than most existing political ego-centric studies. We evaluate how well the now standard "compound" political name generator captures interpersonal political networks, finding that it does quite well save a few items of significant political importance. We discuss the implications of this research agenda for theories of social influence and the study of disagreement in democratic politics. (C) 2013 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000328803800012
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="30">
<title>Exploring variation in active network size: Constraints and ego characteristics</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2008.12.002</url>
<snippet>Studies of active personal networks have primarily focused on providing reliable estimates of the size of the network. In this study, we examine how compositional properties of the network and ego characteristics are related to Variation in network size. There was a negative relationship between mean emotional closeness and network size, for both related and unrelated networks. Further, there was a distinct upper bound on total network size. These results suggest that there are constraints both on the absolute number of individuals that ego can maintain in the network, and also on the emotional intensity of the relationships that ego can maintain with those individuals. (C) 2009 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000265325900004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="31">
<title>Network centralization with the Gil Schmidt power centrality index</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2009.04.004</url>
<snippet>Network centralization is a network index that measures the degree of dispersion of all node centrality scores in a network from the maximum centrality score obtained in the network. The Gil Schmidt power centrality index was developed for use in describing the political networks of Mexico, Gil and Schmidt [Gil. J.. Schmidt, S., 1996a. The origin of the Mexican network of power. In: International Social Network Conference, Charleston, SC, USA, pp. 22-25: Gil, J., Schmidt, S., 1996b. The political network in Mexico. Social Networks 18, 355-381]. Upper bounds for network centralization, using the Gil Schmidt power centrality index, are derived for networks of fixed order and for when the network is bipartite, such as can arise from two mode data. In each case the networks that have maximum network centralization are described. (C) 2009 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000267838900005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="32">
<title>The acquisition of perceived descriptive norms as social category learning in social networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2013.06.002</url>
<snippet>Descriptive norms-what people typically do in a certain setting play a significant role in peoples behavioural decisions. However, little is known about how people acquire descriptive norms in their community. We postulate that acquisition of descriptive norms can be construed as social category learning in social networks, where people learn social information relevant about community descriptive norms from others with whom they are associated through social network ties. We distinguish two routes to norm acquisition: experiential and conceptual. The experiential route suggests people observe the behaviours of their associates in their social networks, and infer what people typically do; the conceptual route suggests people learn about their community from what their associates say people typically do. We used a novel statistical method of autologistic actor attribute models (ALAAM) on survey responses collected by snow ball sampling in a rural city in Australia, and found that people experientially learn descriptive norms about community engagement. Implications of this finding and the limitations of the current study are discussed. (C) 2013 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000328713500017
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="33">
<title>Question-order effects in social network name generators</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2009.06.001</url>
<snippet>Social network surveys are an important tool for empirical research in a variety of fields, including the study of social capital and the evaluation of educational and social policy. A growing body of methodological research sheds light on the validity and reliability of social network survey data regarding a single relation, but much less attention has been paid to the measurement of multiplex networks and the validity of comparisons among criterion relations. In this paper, we identify ways that surveys designed to collect multiplex social network data might be vulnerable to question-order effects. We then test several hypotheses using a split-ballot experiment embedded in an online Multiple name generator survey of teachers advice networks, collected for a study of complete networks. We conclude by discussing implications for the design of multiple name generator social network surveys. (C) 2009 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000269995400001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="34">
<title>The strength of family ties: A meta-analysis and meta-regression of self-reported social support and mortality</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2013.08.004</url>
<snippet>Perceived social support has long been recognized as associated with better health and longevity. However, important factors that may moderate this relationship have not been sufficiently explored. The authors used meta-analyses and meta-regressions to examine 178 all-cause mortality risk estimates from 50 publications, providing data on more than 100,000 persons. The mean hazard ratio (HR) for mortality among those with lower levels of perceived social support was 1.11(95&#37; confidence interval [CI]: 1.05, 1.17) among multivariate-adjusted HRs. Meta-regressions suggest that support from family members was more beneficial than support provided by friends, and that a moderate level of support may be enough to achieve positive results. The results also show that the importance of having support increases with age. No substantial difference was found between men and women with respect to the relationship between support and mortality. (C) 2013 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000328713500011
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="35">
<title>The accuracy of small world chains in social networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2005.06.001</url>
<snippet>We analyse 10,920 shortest path connections between 105 members of an interviewing bureau, together with the equivalent conceptual, or small world routes, which use individuals selections of intermediaries. This permits the first study of the impact of accuracy within small world chains. The mean small world path length (3.23) is 40&#37; longer than the mean of the actual shortest paths (2.30), showing that mistakes are prevalent. A Markov model with a probability of simply guessing an intermediary of 0.52 gives an excellent fit to the observations, suggesting that people make the wrong small world choice more than half the time. 
WOS:000235101000005
</snippet>
</document>

</searchresult>
