<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<searchresult>
<query>Global</query>
<document id="1">
<title>A sexual affiliation network of swingers, heterosexuals practicing risk behaviours that potentiate the spread of sexually transmitted infections: A two-mode approach</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2013.02.006</url>
<snippet>Using the example of the sexual affiliation networks of swingers, this paper examines how the analysis of sexual affiliation networks can contribute to the development of sexually transmitted infection (STI) prevention strategies. Two-mode network methodology and ERGMs are applied to describe the structural composition of the affiliation network and analyse attribute effects. Swingers were found to recruit their sex partners through one large, moderately cohesive network component. Swingers who used drugs or had a longer history of swinging tended to frequent websites instead of clubs. This study confirms the relevance of studying sexual affiliation networks and its additional value for STI epidemiology. (C) 2013 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000320479500008
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="2">
<title>Exponential random graph model specifications for bipartite networks A dependence hierarchy</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2011.12.004</url>
<snippet>In this paper, we review the development of dependence structures for exponential random graph models for bipartite networks, and propose a hierarchy of dependence structures within which different dependence assumptions may be located. Based on this hierarchy, we propose a new set of model specifications by including bipartite graph configurations involving more than four nodes. We discuss the theoretical significance of the various effects that the extended models afford, and illustrate application of this hierarchy of models to several bipartite networks related to the political mobilization in Brazil in the early 1990s (Mische, 2007). (C) 2011 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000320479500007
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="3">
<title>Networks and geography: Modelling community network structures as the outcome of both spatial and network processes</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2010.12.001</url>
<snippet>This paper focuses on how to extend the exponential random graph models to take into account the geographical embeddedness of individuals in modelling social networks. We develop a hierarchical set of nested models for spatially embedded social networks, in which, following Butts (2002), an interaction function between tie probability and Euclidean distance between nodes is introduced. The models are illustrated by an empirical example from a study of the role of social networks in understanding spatial clustering in unemployment in Australia. The analysis suggests that a spatial effect cannot solely explain the emergence of organised network structure and it is necessary to include both spatial and endogenous network effects in the model. (C) 2010 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000300131600002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="4">
<title>Longitudinal analysis of personal networks. The case of Argentinean migrants in Spain</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2009.05.001</url>
<snippet>This paper discusses and illustrates various approaches for the longitudinal analysis of personal networks (multilevel analysis, regression analysis, and SIENA). We combined the different types of analyses in a study of the changing personal networks of immigrants. Data were obtained from 25 Argentineans in Spain, who were interviewed twice in a 2-year interval. Qualitative interviews were used to estimate the amount of measurement error and to isolate important predictors. Quantitative analyses showed that the persistence of ties was explained by tie strength, network density, and alters Country of origin and residence. Furthermore, transitivity appeared to be an important tendency, both for acquiring new contacts and for the relationships among alters. At the network level, immigrants networks were remarkably stable in composition and structure despite the high turnover. Clustered graphs have been used to illustrate the results. The results are discussed in light of adaptation to the host society. (C) 2009 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000274948700009
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="5">
<title>Measuring 'neighborhood': Constructing network neighborhoods</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2011.05.002</url>
<snippet>This study attempts to measure neighborhood boundaries in a novel way by creating network neighborhoods based on the density of social ties among adolescents. We create valued matrices based on social ties and physical distance between adolescents in the county. We then perform factor analyses on these valued matrices to detect these network neighborhoods. The resulting network neighborhoods show considerable spatial contiguity. We assess the quality of these aggregations by comparing the degree of agreement among residents assigned to the same network neighborhood when assessing various characteristics of their "neighborhood", along with traditional definitions of neighborhoods from Census aggregations. Our findings suggest that these network neighborhoods are a valuable approach for "neighborhood" aggregation. (C) 2011 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000300131600011
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="6">
<title>The microstructures of network recall: How social networks are encoded and represented in human memory</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2014.11.003</url>
<snippet>A growing number of studies indicate that aspects of psychology and cognition influence network structure, but much remains to be learned about how network information is stored and retrieved from memory. Are networks recalled as dyads, as triads, or more generally as sub-groups? We employ an experimental design coupled with exponential random graph models to address this issue. We find that respondents flexibly encode social information as triads or groups, depending on the network, but not as dyads. This supports prior research showing that networks are stored using "compression heuristics", but also provides evidence of cognitive flexibility in the process of encoding relational information. (C) 2014 The Authors. Published by Elsevier B.V. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/).
WOS:000351979100010
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="7">
<title>Measuring segregation in social networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2014.04.001</url>
<snippet>Network homophily is a pattern in which ties are more likely to exist between nodes similar to each other. It is frequently observed for various types of social relations. At the same time, segregation is often encountered in urban areas as a tendency of families to occupy neighborhoods inhabited by other families similar to them. In this paper we conceptualize both phenomena as in the language of networks of interlinked positions occupied by a population of actors characterized by some node-level attribute. We review existing indexes and approaches to measuring the extent of homophily/segregation in social networks. We pursue an approach of, first, specifying a set of properties that a generic segregation measure might possess, and which, in our view, are relevant in substantial contexts. Second, we check which measures satisfy which properties. The use of measures is illustrated with four empirical examples. Given the particular application and the need for some descriptive measure of segregation, the results presented in this paper can help in selecting an optimal measure for the task at hand. We conclude that the most crucial aspects for the choice of a particular segregation measure include (1) whether the network ties or actors attributes are assumed to be subject to change, and (2) how one should treat the presence of network isolates. (C) 2014 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000340338600003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="8">
<title>Judgment of distributional inequality in networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2011.10.004</url>
<snippet>Why is income inequality perceived and judged differently across a society? Following the social comparison theory, one reasonable explanation suggests that individuals are exposed to different local reference groups in social networks. We design a vignette experiment to study how income distributions are judged by individuals structured in networks. The experiment shows that perceptions of distributional inequality are high when network ties are unequally distributed across individuals, suggesting that network inequality contributes to distributional inequality. Beyond the network effect, inequality judgment is found to be driven by a mix of self-interest and other-regarding preference: people are in favor of group-beneficial income distributions wherein they rank high, but not extremely high, in the group. It shows that people care about not only their relative affluence, but also where others stand in the distribution. (C) 2011 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000298122200009
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="9">
<title>Introduction to stochastic actor-based models for network dynamics</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2009.02.004</url>
<snippet>Stochastic actor-based models are models for network dynamics that can represent a wide variety of influences on network change, and allow to estimate parameters expressing such influences, and test corresponding hypotheses. The nodes in the network represent social actors, and the collection of ties represents a social relation. The assumptions posit that the network evolves as a stochastic process driven by the actors, i.e., the model lends itself especially for representing theories about how actors change their outgoing ties. The probabilities of tie changes are in part endogenously determined, i.e., as a function of the current network structure itself, and in part exogenously, as a function of characteristics of the nodes (actor covariates) and of characteristics of pairs of nodes (dyadic covariates). In an extended form, stochastic actor-based models can be used to analyze longitudinal data on social networks jointly with changing attributes of the actors: dynamics of networks and behavior. This paper gives an introduction to stochastic actor-based models for dynamics of directed networks, using only a minimum of mathematics. The focus is on understanding the basic principles of the model, understanding the results, and on sensible rules for Model selection. Crown Copyright (C) 2009 Published by Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000274948700005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="10">
<title>Board interlocking network and the design of executive compensation packages</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2014.12.002</url>
<snippet>The standard approach used to model interlocks in the business and management literature is to treat each interlock of a network as an independent data point. However, such an approach ignores the complex inter-dependencies among the common director interlocks. We propose that an interlocking board network is an important inter-corporate setting that has bearing on how company boards make corporate decisions. Using a sample of 725 large U.S.-based public companies over the period 2007-2010, board member information, executive compensation information, and exponential random graph modeling (ERGM) techniques for social networks, we present evidence that board interlocks are positively linked with similarities in the design of executive compensation packages in interlocked firms, particularly the proportions of the options component. We also find evidence that board interlocks are positively linked with similarities in a number of board characteristics. (C) 2014 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000351979100008
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="11">
<title>Adolescent aggression: The role of peer group status motives, peer aggression, and group characteristics</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2010.06.003</url>
<snippet>Recent studies of youth aggression have emphasized the role of network-based peer influence processes. Other scholars have suggested that aggression is often motivated by status concerns. We integrate these two veins of research by considering the effects of peer status motivations on subsequent adolescent aggression, net of their own status motivations, prior aggression, and peer behavior. We also explore different levels at which peer effects may occur, considering the effects of reciprocated and unreciprocated friendships as well as larger, meso-level peer groups. We anticipate that peer group effects are magnified by both size and boundedness as measured by Freemans (1972) segregation index. We find that, net of the adolescents aggression at time 1, both the aggressive behaviors and the status valuations of friends independently increase the likelihood of aggression at time 2, 6 months later. The aggressive behavior of friends who do not reciprocate the adolescents friendship nomination has particular impact. The average status valuation of peer groups increases their members likelihood of aggression, even after controlling for their own attitudes about status, their friends attitudes, and their friends aggressive behavior. This effect is magnified in large groups and groups with high Freeman segregation scores. (C) 2010 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000313304100001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="12">
<title>Exponential random graph (p*) models for affiliation networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2008.08.002</url>
<snippet>Recent advances in Exponential Random Graph Models (ERGMs), or p* models, include new specifications that give a much better chance of model convergence for large networks compared with the traditional Markov models. Simulation based MCMC maximum likelihood estimation techniques have been developed to replace the pseudolikelihood method. To date most work on ERGMs has focused on one-mode networks, with little done in the case of affiliation networks with two or more types of nodes. This paper proposes ERGMs for two-mode affiliation networks drawing on the recent advances for one-mode networks, including new two-mode specifications. We investigate features of the models by simulation, and compared the goodness of fit results obtained using the maximum likelihood and pseudolikelihood approaches. We introduce a new approach to goodness of fit for network models, using a heuristic based on Mahalanobis distance. The classic Southern Women data and Australian Interlocking Director data are used as examples to show that the ERGM with the newly specified statistics is a powerful tool for statistical analysis of affiliation networks. 
WOS:000262547600002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="13">
<title>Spectral goodness of fit for network models</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2015.04.004</url>
<snippet>We introduce a new statistic, spectral goodness of fit (SGOF) to measure how well a network model explains the structure of the pattern of ties in an observed network. SGOF provides a measure of fit analogous to the standard R-2 in linear regression. Additionally, as it takes advantage of the properties of the spectrum of the graph Laplacian, it is suitable for comparing network models of diverse functional forms, including both fitted statistical models and algorithmic generative models of networks. After introducing, defining, and providing guidance for interpreting SGOF, we illustrate the properties of the statistic with-a number of examples and comparisons to existing techniques. We show that such a spectral approach to assessing model fit fills gaps left by earlier methods and can be widely applied. (C) 2015 The Authors. Published by Elsevier B.V.
WOS:000358626400002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="14">
<title>Double-embeddedness: Spatial and relational contexts of tie persistence and re-formation</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2015.02.005</url>
<snippet>Personal relationships are embedded in both spatial and relational contexts. Using data on 60 intentional communities from the Urban Communes Data Set, we examine how such embedding is related to the persistence and re-formation of close personal ties over a thirteen year period, beginning from when most members had been out of their group environments more than a decade. We find that local network structure-the pattern of dyads immediately surrounding any dyad is extremely weighty in which ties persist, which lapse, and which are re-initiated, but that the precise ways in which local structure affects contact are bound up with the distance between dyad members. We also find asymmetries in these processes that other studies have been unable to uncover that processes that lead ties to be dropped are not the same as those that lead them to be renewed; that increases in local embeddedness are not opposite of decreases; that change in contact is not the same as change in friendship. Finally, there is evidence of hierarchical effects influencing the retention of friendships more than twenty-five years after most respondents left their groups. (C) 2015 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000355050600004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="15">
<title>Bayesian inference for exponential random graph models</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2010.09.004</url>
<snippet>Exponential random graph models are extremely difficult models to handle from a statistical viewpoint, since their normalising constant, which depends on model parameters, is available only in very trivial cases. We show how inference can be carried out in a Bayesian framework using a MCMC algorithm, which circumvents the need to calculate the normalising constants. We use a population MCMC approach which accelerates convergence and improves mixing of the Markov chain. This approach improves performance with respect to the Monte Carlo maximum likelihood method of Geyer and Thompson (1992). (C) 2010 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000291962000005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="16">
<title>Relationship patterns in the 19th century: The friendship network in a German boys' school class from 1880 to 1881 revisited</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2013.11.001</url>
<snippet>The article presents a friendship network from 1880 to 1881 in a school class, which goes back to the exceptional mixed-methods study of the German primary school teacher Johannes Delitsch. The re-analysis of the historic network gives insights into what characteristics defined the friendship networks in school classes in Germany at the end of the 19th century. ERGMs of the so far unmarked data show structural patterns of friendship networks similar to today (reciprocity, transitive triadic closure). Moreover we test the influence of the class ranking order (Lokationsprinzip), which allocates the pupils in the class room according to their school performance. This ranking order produces a hierarchy in the popularity of pupils, through hierarchy-congruent friendship ties going upwards in the hierarchy. In this respect, concerning the effect of school achievement on popularity, we find a strong stratification, which is not always prevalent today. (C) 2013 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000334001400001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="17">
<title>Actor-based analysis of peer influence in &lt;i&gt;A Stop Smoking In Schools Trial&lt;/i&gt; (ASSIST)</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2010.07.001</url>
<snippet>As shown by the success of network intervention studies that exploit the occurrence of peer influence in their target group, the reliable assessment of peer influence processes can be important for informing public health policy and practice. A recently developed tool for assessing peer influence in longitudinal social network data is stochastic actor-based modeling. The body of the literature in which this method is applied is growing, but how reliable are the results? In this paper, we identify two shortcomings in this literature: the questionable assumption of temporal homogeneity, and the potential dependence of results on the inclusion of nuisance parameters in the model specification. These issues are resolved by analyzing the data of three schools selected from ASSIST, a large UK-based trial of a school-based smoking prevention intervention. Results show that the co-evolution of friendship and smoking is a time heterogeneous process, and that results are sensitive to specification details. However, the peer influence parameter is not affected by either, but emerges as surprisingly stable over time and robust to model variation. This establishes confidence in the method and encourages detailed future investigations of peer influence in ASSIST. (C) 2010 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000305495600007
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="18">
<title>Avoidance in negative ties: Inhibiting closure, reciprocity, and homophily</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2016.07.003</url>
<snippet>Theorising of negative ties has focused on simplex negative tie networks or multiplex signed tie networks. We examine the fundamental differences between positive and negative tie networks measured on the same set of actors. We test six mechanisms of tie formation on face-to-face positive (affect/esteem) and negative (dislike/disesteem) networks of 282 university students. While popularity, activity, and entrainment are present in both networks, closure, reciprocity, and homophily are largely absent from negative tie networks. We argue this arises because avoidance is inherent to negative sentiments. Avoidance reduces information transfer through negative ties and short-circuits cumulative causation. (C) 2016 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000389730200011
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="19">
<title>Ethnic segregation of friendship networks in school: Testing a rational-choice argument of differences in ethnic homophily between classroom- and grade-level networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2015.02.002</url>
<snippet>Adolescents school-based friendship networks tend to be segregated along ethnic lines. But few studies have examined whether variation in network boundaries affects the degree of ethnic friendship segregation. We use rational-choice theory to argue that ethnic homophily is more pronounced for friendships between classrooms than for those within classrooms. We empirically test this hypothesis using two-wave German panel data (N=1258) and stochastic actor-oriented models (RSiena). In line with our theoretical argument, we find that the tendency to form same-ethnic friendships is indeed stronger at the grade level, which translates into stronger ethnic segregation in friendship networks at the grade level than at the classroom level. Implications for research on ethnic segregation in school-based friendship networks are discussed. (C) 2015 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000355050600003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="20">
<title>Exponential random graph models of preschool affiliative networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2012.11.002</url>
<snippet>Exponential random graph models were used to assess the relevance of reciprocity, popularity, transitivity controlling for effects based upon ego and alter sex, and sex homophily, on the formation of affiliative ties in 19 Portuguese preschool peer groups. The number of times two children were recorded as nearest neighbors in focal samples was used as an indicator of the relationships strength. Independent parameter estimates of the different models (one for each group) were summarized, separately for the three age groups ("3-year-olds", "4-year-olds" and "5-year-olds") using a multi-level approach to meta-analysis. Results showed that affiliative ties between children were sex segregated, highly reciprocal, more likely to be directed to a restricted number of children and with a tendency to create transitive triads. The structural processes underlying the formation of affiliative ties were quite stable between classrooms. 
WOS:000317943100003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="21">
<title>"It must be me" or "It could be them?": The impact of the social network position of bullies and victims on victims' adjustment</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2010.07.002</url>
<snippet>It was examined in this study whether the association between victimization and psychological adjustment (depression and self-esteem) is moderated by the classroom network position of bullies and victims. Multivariate multilevel regression analysis was used on a large sample representative of grades three to five in Finland (N=7192 children from 376 classrooms). Consistent with the person-group (dis)similarity model and attributional mechanisms, it was found that victims were better adjusted in classrooms when others shared their plight and when they could attribute the blame to bullies. The results indicate that victimization consequences might be partly generated by person-environment interactions. (C) 2010 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000313304100002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="22">
<title>The efficacy of tables versus graphs in disrupting dark networks: An experimental study</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2013.04.008</url>
<snippet>An agent tasked with disrupting a dark (covert and illegal) network must first be presented with information about the organization's structure. This paper uses a behavioral experiment to test in a stylized dark network disruption setting whether an agent makes a better disruption choice when the information is displayed in a table or a graph format. We find that subjects make decisions more quickly when presented with graphs, but that subjects perform weakly better with tables. An important lesson is that the display should explicitly distinguish non-existent links from potential links of unknown status. 
WOS:000322692600013
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="23">
<title>One-shot exchange networks and the shadow of the future</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2009.02.001</url>
<snippet>From the Prisoners Dilemma and other games, it is well known that strategy selection in one-shot games can be very different from that in iterated games. Because exchange structures were studied only as iterated games, whether one-shot structures differ was not known. Nor have exchange theories previously considered whether events in structures Would be different if studied as one-shot games. This paper offers new theory to predict one-shot exchange structures and one-shot experiments to test that theory. As predicted, the experiments found that processes and Outcomes of one-shot exchange structures are quite different from those of iterated exchange structures. For example, certain relations that are strategically used as threats in iterated exchange Structures occur very rarely in one-shot structures. It follows that power differences in one-shot structures regress from those observed for repeated structures. (C) 2009 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000265325900005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="24">
<title>The co-evolution of gossip and friendship in workplace social networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2012.07.002</url>
<snippet>This study investigates the co-evolution of friendship and gossip in organizations. Two contradicting perspectives are tested. The social capital perspective predicts that friendship causes gossip between employees, defined as informal evaluative talking about absent colleagues. The evolutionary perspective reverses this causality claiming that gossiping facilitates friendship. The data comprises of three observations of a complete organizational network, allowing longitudinal social network analyses. Gossip and friendship are modeled as both explanatory and outcome networks with RSiena. Results support the evolutionary perspective in that gossip between two individuals increases the likelihood of their future friendship formation. However, individuals with disproportionately high gossip activity have fewer friends in the network, suggesting that the use of gossiping to attract friends has a limit. (C) 2012 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000313304100025
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="25">
<title>Network social capital as an outcome of social movement mobilization: Using the position generator as an indicator of social network diversity</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2011.12.007</url>
<snippet>In the social mobility literature, the position generator (PG) has been used to examine the relationship between the structural location of individuals. and outcomes such as obtaining a high status job. Diversity of occupational ties (as measured by the PG) is also a significant predictor of an individuals cultural capital. A great deal of work has also been done in the field of social movements examining the relationship between networks and mobilization. However, only limited attention has been given to the position generator in this literature. Also, while past research has demonstrated that prior network ties to activists is one of the most important predictors of current activism, relatively little research has been devoted to examining network structure as an outcome of activism. The present paper builds upon these insights by utilizing data collected with the position generator on a sample of environmental movement members, and examining the relationship between individual activism (as an independent variable) and diversity of occupational ties (as a dependent variable). The result of key theoretical significance is that those who are more active in the environmental movement develop a greater diversity of occupational ties to other environmentalists. Results suggest that this process occurs over time. These findings provide evidence that social capital (as indicated by network diversity) is one outcome of social movement mobilization. (C) 2012 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000313304100003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="26">
<title>Norms, status and the dynamics of advice networks: A case study</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2009.12.001</url>
<snippet>The issue of the influence of norms on behavior is as old as sociology itself. This paper explores the effect of normative homophily (i.e. "sharing the same normative choices") on the evolution of the advice network among lay judges in a courthouse. Blaus (1955, 1964) social exchange theory suggests that members select advisors based on the status of the advisor. Additional research shows that members of an organization use similarities with others in ascribed, achieved or inherited characteristics, as well as other kinds of ties, to mitigate the potentially negative effects of this strong status rule. We elaborate and test these theories using data on advisor choice in the Commercial Court of Paris. We use a jurisprudential case about unfair competition (material and "moral" damages), a case that we submitted to all the judges of this court, to test the effect of normative homophily on the selection of advisors, controlling for status effects. Normative homophily is measured by the extent to which two judges are equally "punitive" in awarding damages to plaintiffs. Statistical analyses combine longitudinal advice network data collected among the judges with their normative dispositions. Contrary to what could be expected from conventional sociological theories, we find no pure effect of normative homophily on the choice of advisors. In this case, therefore, sharing the same norms and values does not have, by itself, a mitigating effect and does not contribute to the evolution of the network. We argue that status effects, conformity and alignments on positions of opinion leaders in controversies still provide the best insights into the relationship between norms, structure and behavior. (C) 2009 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000305495600004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="27">
<title>Extended structures of mediation: Re-examining brokerage in dynamic networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2013.02.001</url>
<snippet>In this paper we revisit the concept of brokerage in social networks. We elaborate on the concept of brokerage as a process, identifying three distinct classes of brokerage behavior. Based on this process model, we develop a framework for measuring brokerage opportunities in dynamic relational data. Using data on emergent inter-organizational collaborations, we employ the dynamic brokerage framework to examine the relationship between organizational attributes and coordination in the evolving network. Comparing the findings of our process-based definition with traditional, static approaches, we identify important dimensions of organizational action that would be missed by the latter approach. (C) 2013 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000317943100012
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="28">
<title>Who speaks up to whom? A relational approach to employee voice</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2011.10.001</url>
<snippet>We adopt a relational approach to examine the effects of social relations and formal structure on who speaks up to whom about problems at work. Data were collected in a two-wave employee survey in three Dutch preschools. Using exponential random graph modeling, we found significant positive effects of formal structure (recipients hierarchical level; team co-membership) and good relations between speaker and recipient on the likelihood of voice in a dyad. Speakers hierarchical level had positive effects. significant in Wave 1. Speakers degree centrality significantly reduced the likelihood of voice, whereas recipients degree centrality had no effect. (C) 2011 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000298122200006
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="29">
<title>The network autocorrelation model using two-mode data: Affiliation exposure and potential bias in the autocorrelation parameter</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2011.06.001</url>
<snippet>The network autocorrelation model has been a workhorse for modeling network influences on individual behavior. The standard network approaches to mapping social influence using network measures, however, are limited to specifying an influence weight matrix (W) based on a single mode network. Additionally, it has been demonstrated that the estimate of the autocorrelation parameter rho of the network effect tends to be negatively biased as the density in W matrix increases. The current study introduces a two-mode version of the network autocorrelation model. We then conduct simulations to examine conditions under which bias might exist. We show that the estimate for the affiliation autocorrelation parameter (rho) tends to be negatively biased as density increases, as in the one-mode case. Inclusion of the diagonal of W, the count of the number of events participated in, as one of the variables in the regression model helps to attenuate such bias, however. We discuss the implications of these results. (C) 2011 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000294520200006
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="30">
<title>Social network engineering and race in a police academy: A longitudinal analysis</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2009.08.001</url>
<snippet>This research examined an attempt to facilitate racial integration by populating squads (i.e., workgroups) in a police academy with mixes of recruits that reflected the racial demographics of the larger cohort. This was part of the social infrastructure of the academy. Additionally, a fixed seating arrangement was considered as a second element of academy infrastructure capable of impacting racial integration. We examined the consequences of these academy components over time with regard to race by combining ethnographic accounts With social network data collected throughout the academy and using a variety of network analytic tools. These consequences with regard to race were examined as a part of social network evolution. The academys social arrangements did accelerate the creation of social knowledge of recruits about each other and the formation of friendship ties both within and between races. However. our results point to cleat limitations to such infrastructural engineering and have implications for both recruitment to police academies and dealing with race. They shed light also oil processes of homophily and group composition over time and have implications for Studying social networks. (C) 2009 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000274948700004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="31">
<title>Measuring social dynamics in a massive multiplayer online game</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2010.06.001</url>
<snippet>Quantification of human group-behavior has so far defied an empirical, falsifiable approach. This is due to tremendous difficulties in data acquisition of social systems. Massive multiplayer online games (MMOG) provide a fascinating new way of observing hundreds of thousands of simultaneously socially interacting individuals engaged in virtual economic activities. We have compiled a data set consisting of practically all actions of all players over a period of 3 years from a MMOG played by 300,000 people. This large-scale data set of a socio-economic unit contains all social and economic data from a single and coherent source. Players have to generate a virtual income through economic activities to survive and are typically engaged in a multitude of social activities offered within the game. Our analysis of high-frequency log files focuses on three types of social networks, and tests a series of social-dynamics hypotheses. In particular we study the structure and dynamics of friend-, enemy- and communication networks. We find striking differences in topological structure between positive (friend) and negative (enemy) tie networks. All networks confirm the recently observed phenomenon of network densification. We propose two approximate social laws in communication networks, the first expressing betweenness centrality as the inverse square of the overlap, the second relating communication strength to the cube of the overlap. These empirical laws provide strong quantitative evidence for the Weak ties hypothesis of Granovetter. Further, the analysis of triad significance profiles validates well-established assertions from social balance theory. We find overrepresentation (underrepresentation) of complete (incomplete) triads in networks of positive ties, and vice versa for networks of negative ties. Empirical transition probabilities between triad classes provide evidence for triadic closure with extraordinarily high precision. For the first time we provide empirical results for large-scale networks of negative social ties. Whenever possible we compare our findings with data from non-virtual human groups and provide further evidence that online game communities serve as a valid model for a wide class of human societies. With this setup we demonstrate the feasibility for establishing a socio-economic laboratory which allows to operate at levels of precision approaching those of the natural sciences. All data used in this study is fully anonymized: the authors have the written consent to publish from the legal department of the Medical University of Vienna. (C) 2010 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000283402000006
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="32">
<title>Different relationships for coping with ambiguity and uncertainty in organizations</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2008.09.001</url>
<snippet>This study seeks to shed light oil the relationship between the Situation and the activation of specific relationships. We hypothesized that the type of uncertainty present in a situation would prompt people to call upon different relationships based on different types of trust: cognitive trust for expertise and affective trust for friendship. We elaborated vignettes as name generators to test whether the colleagues called upon in different situations were perceived as being more friends or more experts. The perceived level of expertise and friendship were evaluated with Likert-style scales. The results support our theoretical argument to the effect that the "activation" of a relationship is influenced by the type of uncertainty a person is confronted to. Situations of information uncertainty elicit recourse to relationships based on expertise While ambiguous Situations call for friendship. 
WOS:000262547600004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="33">
<title>The stability of exchange networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2008.12.001</url>
<snippet>Economic and sociological exchange theories predict divisions of exchange benefits given an assumed fixed network of exchange relations. Since network structure has been found to have a large impact on actors payoffs, actors have strong incentives for network change. We answer the question what happens to both the network structure and actor payoffs when myopic actors change their links in order to maximize their payoffs. We investigate the networks that are stable, the networks that are efficient or egalitarian with varying tie costs, and the occurrence of social dilemmas. Only few networks are stable over a wide range of tie costs, and all of them can be divided into two types: efficient networks consisting of only dyads and at most one isolate, and Pareto efficient and egalitarian cycles with an odd number of actors. Social dilemmas are observed in even-sized networks at low tie costs. (C) 2008 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000265325900002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="34">
<title>Gender homophily from spatial behavior in a primary school: A sociometric study</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2013.08.003</url>
<snippet>We investigate gender homophily in the spatial proximity of children (6-12 years old) in a French primary school, using time-resolved data on face-to-face proximity recorded by means of wearable sensors. For strong ties, i.e., for pairs of children who interact more than a defined threshold, we find statistical evidence of gender preference that increases with grade. For weak ties, conversely, gender homophily is negatively correlated with grade for girls, and positively correlated with grade for boys. This different evolution with grade of weak and strong ties exposes a contrasted picture of gender homophily. (C) 2013 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000328713500009
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="35">
<title>Topologies of strategically formed social networks based on a generic value function-Allocation rule model</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2010.10.004</url>
<snippet>A wide variety of game theoretic models have been proposed in the literature to explain social network formation. Topologies of networks formed under these models have been investigated, keeping in view two key properties, namely efficiency and stability. Our objective in this paper is to investigate the topologies of networks formed with a more generic model of network formation. Our model is based on a well known model, the value function - allocation rule model. We choose a specific value function and a generic allocation rule and derive several interesting topological results in the network formation context. A unique feature of our model is that it simultaneously captures several key determinants of network formation such as (i) benefits from immediate neighbors through links, (ii) costs of maintaining the links, (iii) benefits from non-neighboring nodes and decay of these benefits with distance, and (iv) intermediary benefits that arise from multi-step paths. Based on this versatile model of network formation, our study explores the structure of the networks that satisfy one or both of the properties, efficiency and pairwise stability. The following are our specific results: (1) we first show that the complete graph and the star graph are the only topologies possible for non-empty efficient networks: this result is independent of the allocation rule and corroborates the findings of more specific models in the literature. (2) We then derive the structure of pairwise stable networks and come up with topologies that are richer than what have been derived for extant models in the literature. (3) Next, under the proposed model, we state and prove a necessary and sufficient condition for any efficient network to be pairwise stable. (4) Finally, we study topologies of pairwise stable networks in some specific settings, leading to unravelling of more specific topological possibilities. (C) 2010 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000291962000006
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="36">
<title>Structural effects of network sampling coverage I: Nodes missing at random</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2013.09.003</url>
<snippet>Network measures assume a census of a well-bounded population. This level of coverage is rarely achieved in practice, however, and we have only limited information on the robustness of network measures to incomplete coverage. This paper examines the effect of node-level missingness on 4 classes of network measures: centrality, centralization, topology and homophily across a diverse sample of 12 empirical networks. We use a Monte Carlo simulation process to generate data with known levels of missingness and compare the resulting network scores to their known starting values. As with past studies (Borgatti et al., 2006; Kossinets, 2006), we find that measurement bias generally increases with more missing data. The exact rate and nature of this increase, however, varies systematically across network measures. For example, betweenness and Bonacich centralization are quite sensitive to missing data while closeness and in-degree are robust. Similarly, while the tau statistic and distance are difficult to capture with missing data, transitivity shows little bias even with very high levels of missingness. The results are also clearly dependent on the features of the network. Larger, more centralized networks are generally more robust to missing data, but this is especially true for centrality and centralization measures. More cohesive networks are robust to missing data when measuring topological features but not when measuring centralization. Overall, the results suggest that missing data may have quite large or quite small effects on network measurement, depending on the type of network and the question being posed. (C) 2013 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000328713500013
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="37">
<title>Popularity trajectories and substance use in early adolescence</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2010.10.001</url>
<snippet>This paper introduces new longitudinal network data from the "Promoting School-Community-University Partnerships to Enhance Resilience" or "PROSPER" peers project. In 28 communities, grade-level sociometric friendship nominations were collected from two cohorts of middle school students as they moved from 6th, to 9th grade. As an illustration and description of these longitudinal network data, this paper describes the school popularity structure, changes in popularity position, and suggests linkages between popularity trajectory and substance use. In the cross-section, we find that the network is consistent with a hierarchical social organization, but exhibits considerable relational change in both particular friends and position at the individual level. We find that both the base level of popularity and the variability of popularity trajectories effect substance use. (C) 2010 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000291175400001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="38">
<title>Network-building behavioral tendencies, range, and promotion speed</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2014.03.006</url>
<snippet>We studied 459 Ukrainian civil servants to determine how career network-building behavioral tendencies relate to network range and promotion speed. We identify two main behavioral tendencies for initiating social relationships: (a) networking within formal structured groups organized around activities created specifically to encourage members to form personal bonds (structured foci) and (b) individually driven networking outside these structured foci. The study shows that individually driven networking is related to broader network range, while structured foci networking has an inverted-U relationship to network range. The optimal networking for range involves a moderate level of structural foci networking and high levels of individually driven networking. Broad network range is related to faster promotion speed to higher organizational levels. Extroverts have a tendency toward individually driven networking, while high Machiavellians have a tendency toward both individually driven and structured foci networking. (C) 2014 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000340338600007
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="39">
<title>Introduction to the special issue on advances in two-mode social networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2013.03.002</url>
<snippet>
WOS:000320479500001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="40">
<title>Similarity in friendship networks: Selection or influence? The effect of constraining contexts and non-visible individual attributes</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2009.06.003</url>
<snippet>Most research on similarity in friendship networks focuses oil clearly visible individual attributes (i.e. attitudes and behaviors) in contexts where choices whom to befriend are relatively unconstrained. These studies often reveal that social selection rather than social influence is the dominant cause of similarity among friends. We argue that in a setting where social collaboration is crucial and friendship choices are more constrained, influence might be the main reason for similarity found among friends. In addition, we examined whether social categorization and peer control amplifies the social influence process among friends. Using a stochastic actor-based model for network dynamics, we analyzed a three-wave dataset of first year Royal Netherlands Naval College officer students oil friendship formation and military discipline. The data Supports our first hypothesis that students adjust their own military discipline to that of their friends. Contrary to our expectations, we did not find Support for the idea that individuals adjust their discipline more to friends who are of the same military specialty, and neither more to friends who exert peer control. We elaborate oil these findings in the discussion. (C) 2009 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000274948700008
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="41">
<title>Who are the objects of positive and negative gossip at work? A social network perspective on workplace gossip</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2011.11.003</url>
<snippet>Gossip is informal talking about colleagues. Taking a social network perspective, we argue that group boundaries and social status in the informal workplace network determine who the objects of positive and negative gossip are. Gossip networks were collected among 36 employees in a public child care organization, and analyzed using exponential random graph modeling (ERGM). As hypothesized, both positive and negative gossip focuses on colleagues from the own gossipers work group. Negative gossip is relatively targeted, with the objects being specific individuals, particularly those low in informal status. Positive gossip, in contrast, is spread more evenly throughout the network. (C) 2011 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000302394600005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="42">
<title>Networks and collective action</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2012.06.003</url>
<snippet>This paper proposes a new measure for a groups ability to lead society to adopt their standard of behavior, which in particular takes account of the time the group takes to convince the whole society to adopt their position. This notion of a groups power to initiate action is computed as the reciprocal of the resistance against it, which is in turn given by the expected absorption time of a related finite state partial Markov chain that captures the social dynamics. The measure is applicable and meaningful in a variety of models where interaction between agents is formalized through (weighted) binary relations. Using Percolation Theory, it is shown that the group power is monotonic as a function of groups of agents. We also explain the differences between our measure and those discussed in the literature on Graph Theory, and illustrate all these concerns by a thorough analysis of two particular cases: the Wolfe Primate Data and the 11S hijackers network. (C) 2012 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000313304100021
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="43">
<title>Modelling a disease-relevant contact network of people who inject drugs</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2013.06.003</url>
<snippet>This study uses social network analysis to model a contact network of people who inject drugs (PWID) relevant for investigating the spread of an infectious disease (hepatitis C). Using snowball sample data, parameters for an exponential random graph model (ERGM) including social circuit dependence and four attributes (location, age, injecting frequency, gender) are estimated using a conditional estimation approach that respects the structure of snowball sample designs. Those network parameter estimates are then used to create a novel, model-dependent estimate of network size. Simulated PWID contact networks are created and compared with Bernoulli graphs. Location, age and injecting frequency are shown to be statistically significant attribute parameters in the ERGM. Simulated ERGM networks are shown to fit the collected data very well across a number of metrics. In comparison with Bernoulli graphs, simulated networks are shown to have longer paths and more clustering. Results from this study make possible simulation of realistic networks for investigating treatment and intervention strategies for reducing hepatitis C prevalence. (C) 2013 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000328713500016
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="44">
<title>Geodesic based centrality: Unifying the local and the global</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2016.09.005</url>
<snippet>A variety of node-level centrality measures, including purely structural measures (such as degree and closeness centrality) and measures incorporating characteristics of actors (such as the Blaus measure of heterogeneity) have been developed to measure a persons access to resources held by others. Each of these node-level measures can be placed on a continuum depending on whether they focus only on egos direct contacts (e.g. degree centrality and Blaus measure of heterogeneity), or whether they also incorporate connections to others at longer distances in the network (e.g. closeness centrality or betweenness centrality). In this paper we propose generalized measures, where a tuning parameter 8 regulates the relative impact of resources held by more close versus more distant others. We first show how, when a specific 8 is chosen degree-centrality and reciprocal closeness centrality are two specific instances of this more general measure. We then demonstrate how a similar approach can be applied to node-level measures that incorporate attributes. When more or less weight is given to other nodes at longer distances with specific characteristics, a generalized measure of resource-richness and a generalized measure for diversity among ones connections can be obtained (following Blaus measure of heterogeneity). Finally, we show how this approach can also be applied to betweenness centrality to focus on more local (ego) betweenness or global (Freeman) betweenness. The importance of the choice of 8 is illustrated on some classic network datasets. (C) 2016 Published by Elsevier B.V.
WOS:000395601700002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="45">
<title>"Trust Me": Differences in expressed and perceived trust relations in an organization</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2012.01.004</url>
<snippet>The possibility of resolving the tension between trust as a psychological condition and trust as a general organizing principle depends on assumptions about the convergence of expressed and perceived trust relations. In empirical organizational research these assumptions are frequently left implicit and only rarely modeled directly. Using data that we have collected on trust relations within the top management team of a multiunit industrial group we specify and estimate multivariate exponential random graph models (ERGMs) that reveal important differences in the structural logics underlying networks of expressed and perceived trust relations. Results confirm that trust induces awareness and produces expectations of reciprocity - features that are consistent with the view of trust as a general organizing principle. Results also show that networks of perceived trust relations are characterized by tendencies toward reciprocity and generalized giving of trust. When multivariate network effects are introduced, however, expressed trust relations no longer show a significant tendency toward reciprocation. Interpreted together these results suggest that: (i) the distribution of expressed and perceived trust relations differs; (ii) expressed trust relations in organizations are more hierarchical than are perceived trust relations, and (iii) expressed and perceived trust relations need to be modeled jointly. These findings suggest caution in the adoption and interpretation of trust only as a general organizing principle, and suggest that psychological mechanisms also play an important role in the making and breaking of trust relations within organizations. (C) 2012 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000313304100005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="46">
<title>Advances in exponential random graph (&lt;i&gt;p&lt;/i&gt;*) models</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2006.08.004</url>
<snippet>
WOS:000246430600001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="47">
<title>Uncovering the role of emotional abilities in leadership emergence. A longitudinal analysis of leadership networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2012.02.001</url>
<snippet>The aim of this paper is to investigate how different emotional abilities affect the emergence of task and relationship leaders in a group of 41 students. To conduct this investigation, leadership is envisioned as a dynamic network of leadership perceptions. The emergence of leadership and the role played by emotional abilities in this process are analyzed using Stochastic Actor Oriented Models (SAOMs). The results suggest that emotional abilities play complementary roles in emergent leadership. Whereas the abilities to perceive and manage emotions facilitate the emergence of relationship leaders, the abilities to use and understand them facilitate the emergence of task leaders. 
WOS:000313304100007
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="48">
<title>Analyzing event stream dynamics in two-mode networks: An exploratory analysis of private communication in a question and answer community</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2011.07.004</url>
<snippet>Information about social networks can often be collected as event stream data. However, most methods in social network analysis are defined for static network snapshots or for panel data. We propose an actor oriented Markov process framework to analyze the structural dynamics in event streams. Estimated parameters are similar to what is known from exponential random graph models or stochastic actor oriented models as implemented in SIENA. We apply the methodology on a question and answer web community and show how the relevance of different kinds of one- and two-mode network structures can be tested using a new software. (C) 2011 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000298122200002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="49">
<title>The game of contacts: Estimating the social visibility of groups</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2010.10.006</url>
<snippet>Estimating the sizes of hard-to-count populations is a challenging and important problem that occurs frequently in social science, public health, and public policy. This problem is particularly pressing in HIV/AIDS research because estimates of the sizes of the most at-risk populations-illicit drug users, men who have sex with men, and sex workers-are needed for designing, evaluating, and funding programs to curb the spread of the disease. A promising new approach in this area is the network scale-up method, which uses information about the personal networks of respondents to make population size estimates. However, if the target population has low social visibility, as is likely to be the case in HIV/AIDS research, scale-up estimates will be too low. In this paper we develop a game-like activity that we call the game of contacts in order to estimate the social visibility of groups, and report results from a study of heavy drug users in Curitiba, Brazil (n = 294). The game produced estimates of social visibility that were consistent with qualitative expectations but of surprising magnitude. Further, a number of checks suggest that the data are high-quality. While motivated by the specific problem of population size estimation, our method could be used by researchers more broadly and adds to long-standing efforts to combine the richness of social network analysis with the power and scale of sample surveys. (C) 2010 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000291962000007
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="50">
<title>Network structure and team performance: The case of English Premier League soccer teams</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2012.08.004</url>
<snippet>A defining feature of a work group is how its individual members interact. Building on a dataset of 283,259 passes between professional soccer players, this study applies mixed-effects modeling to 76 repeated observations of the interaction networks and performance of 23 soccer teams. Controlling for unobserved characteristics, such as the quality of the teams, the study confirms previous findings with panel data: networks characterized by high intensity (controlling for interaction opportunities) and low centralization are indeed associated with better team performance. 
WOS:000313304100030
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="51">
<title>A puzzle concerning triads in social networks: Graph constraints and the triad census</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2010.03.004</url>
<snippet>Evidence from many sources shows that triadic tendencies are important structural features of social networks (e.g. transitivity or triadic closure) and triadic configurations are the basis for both theoretical claims and substantive outcomes (e.g. strength of weak ties, tie stability, or trust). A contrasting line of research demonstrates that triads in empirical social networks are well predicted by lower order graph features (density and dyads), accounting for around 90&#37; of the variability in triad distributions when comparing different social networks (Faust, 2006, 2007, 2008). These two sets of results present a puzzle: how can substantial triadic tendencies occur when triads in empirical social networks are largely explained by lower order graph features? This paper provides insight into the puzzle by considering constraints that lower order graph features place on the triad census. Taking a comparative perspective, it shows that triad censuses from 159 social networks of diverse species and social relations are largely explained by their lower order graph features (the dyad census) through formal constraints that force triads to occur in narrow range of configurations. Nevertheless, within these constraints, a majority of networks exhibit significant triadic patterning by departing from expectation. (C) 2010 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000279409000007
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="52">
<title>Adjustment of issue positions based on network strategies in an election campaign: A two-mode network autoregression model with cross-nested random effects</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2011.03.002</url>
<snippet>During election campaigns, political parties deliver statements on salient issues in the news media, which are called issue positions. This article conceptualizes issue positions as a valued and longitudinal two-mode network of parties by issues. The network is valued because parties pronounce pro or con positions on issues in more or less extreme ways. It is longitudinal because the media report new statements of parties on issues each new day. In political science, issue positions are often assumed to be stable throughout the election campaign but this article shows that parties adjust their issue positions systematically to the issue positions of other parties. Applying concepts from social network analysis, notably structural balance and transitivity, we analyze the evolution of the network of issue positions showing that issue positions adopted previously by other parties as well as previous reports on support and criticism among parties have substantial and statistically significant effects on subsequent issue positions. Our dynamic adjustment model is estimated by means of a two-mode network autoregression model with cross-nested random effects. The data about issue positions and support and criticism among parties come from a daily content analysis of newspaper and television news during the Dutch national election campaign in 2006. (C) 2011 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000320479500004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="53">
<title>Representing degree distributions, clustering, and homophily in social networks with latent cluster random effects models</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2009.04.001</url>
<snippet>Social network data often involve transitivity, homophily on observed attributes, community structure, and heterogeneity of actor degrees. We propose a latent cluster random effects model to represent all of these features, and we develop Bayesian inference for it. The model is applicable to both binary and non-binary network data. We illustrate the model using two real datasets: liking between monks and coreaderships between Slovenian publications. We also apply it to two simulated network datasets with very different network structure but the same highly skewed degree sequence generated from a preferential attachment process. One has transitivity and community structure while the other does not. Models based solely on degree distributions. such as scale-free, preferential attachment and power-law models, cannot distinguish between these very different situations, but the latent cluster random effects model does. (C) 2009 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000267838900004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="54">
<title>Modelling the evolution of a bipartite network-Peer referral in interlocking directorates</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2010.03.001</url>
<snippet>A central part of relational ties between social actors is constituted by shared affiliations and events. The action of joint participation reinforces personal ties between social actors as well as mutually shared values and norms that in turn perpetuate the patterns of social action that define groups. Therefore the study of bipartite networks is central to social science. Furthermore, the dynamics of these processes suggests that bipartite networks should not be considered static structures but rather be studied over time. In order to model the evolution of bipartite networks empirically we introduce a class of models and a Bayesian inference scheme that extends previous stochastic actor-oriented models for unimodal graphs. Contemporary research on interlocking directorates provides an area of research in which it seems reasonable to apply the model. Specifically, we address the question of how tie formation, i.e. director recruitment, contributes to the structural properties of the interlocking directorate network. For boards of directors on the Stockholm stock exchange we propose that a prolific mechanism in tie formation is that of peer referral. The results indicate that such a mechanism is present, generating multiple interlocks between boards. (C) 2010 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000305495600003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="55">
<title>Visualization methods for longitudinal social networks and stochastic actor-oriented modeling</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2011.06.002</url>
<snippet>As a consequence of the rising interest in longitudinal social networks and their analysis, there is also an increasing demand for tools to visualize them. We argue that similar adaptations of state-of-the-art graph-drawing methods can be used to visualize both, longitudinal networks and predictions of stochastic actor-oriented models (SAOMs), the most prominent approach for analyzing such networks. The proposed methods are illustrated on a longitudinal network of acquaintanceship among university freshmen. (C) 2011 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000305495600002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="56">
<title>Getting funded. Multi-level network of physicists in Italy</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2011.12.002</url>
<snippet>Much of the work in the sociology of science observes scientific communities from a micro perspective, focusing on interactions in laboratories in order to uncover the impact of social and cultural norms in the everyday production of scientific results. Other studies approach the topic from a macro perspective, analysing scientific organizations and the reciprocal influence they have with wider society, or uncovering the invisible colleges that become apparent through the analysis of co-authorship and citations' patterns. Less attention has been paid to the meso level of interaction within and between scientists and the institutions they work in. This paper extends the structural approach of Lazega et al. (2008. Catching up with big fish in the big pond? Multi-level network analysis through linked design. Social Networks 30, 157-176) and analyses the local system of public funding to physics in Italy using bipartite networks. Data cover 10 years of funding of Projects of National Interest (Prin) from the Italian Ministry of University and Research. The micro level (collaborations between scientists), macro level (collaborations between institutions) and meso level (the combination of network measures at a micro and macro level) of interactions are independently analysed, and results are used to model the total amount of money physicists have received over the 10 years against the variables that meaningfully describe the network structure of collaborations. Results show that in order to be successfully funded what counts more than being a big fish (a scientist with a lot of connections) working in a big pond (a large University), is being in a brokerage position interacting over the years with different research groups. (C) 2011 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000302394600007
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="57">
<title>Social network analysis with respondent-driven sampling data: A study of racial integration on campus</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2009.09.002</url>
<snippet>This paper presents respondent-driven sampling (RDS) as a viable method of sampling and analyzing social networks with survey data. RDS is a network based sampling and analysis method that provides a middle ground compliment to ego-centric and saturated methods of social network analysis. The method provides survey data, similar to ego-centric approaches, on individuals who are connected by behaviorally documented ties, allowing for macro-level analysis of network structure, similar to that supported by saturated approaches. Using racial interaction of university undergraduates as an empirical example, the paper examines whether and to what extent racial diversity at the institutional level is reflected as racial integration at the interpersonal level by testing hypotheses regarding the quantity and quality of cross-race friendships. The primary goal of this article, however, is to introduce RDS to the network community and to stimulate further research toward the goal of expanding the analytical capacity of RDS. Advantages, limitations, and areas for future research to network analysis using RDS are discussed. (C) 2009 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000276669100002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="58">
<title>Online collective identity: The case of the environmental movement</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2011.03.001</url>
<snippet>Social movements are making extensive communicative and organizational use of the Internet in order to identify social problems and bring about change. We present a model of an online social movement, where actors exchange practical and symbolic resources through hyperlink and online frame networks. Our positioning of these exchanges within a continuum of conscious and unconscious expressive behavior informs our framework for the empirical analysis of online collectives. An application using data collected from the websites of over 160 environmental activist organizations reveals significant fragmentation in this field of contentious activity, which we suggest reflects offline social divisions. Crown Copyright (C) 2011 Published by Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000294520200001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="59">
<title>A comparative study of social network models: Network evolution models and nodal attribute models</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2009.06.004</url>
<snippet>This paper reviews, classifies and compares recent models for social networks that have mainly been published within the physics-oriented complex networks literature. The models fall into two categories: those in which the addition of new links is dependent on the (typically local) network structure (network evolution models, NEMs), and those in which links are generated based only on nodal attributes (nodal attribute models, NAMs). An exponential random graph model (ERGM) with structural dependencies is included for comparison. We fit models from each of these categories to two empirical acquaintance networks with respect to basic network properties. We compare higher order structures in the resulting networks with those in the data, with the aim of determining which models produce the most realistic network structure with respect to degree distributions, assortativity, clustering spectra, geodesic path distributions, and community structure (subgroups with dense internal connections). We find that the nodal attribute models successfully produce assortative networks and very clear community structure. However, they generate unrealistic clustering spectra and peaked degree distributions that do not match empirical data on large social networks. On the other hand, many of the network evolution models produce degree distributions and clustering spectra that agree more closely with data. They also generate assortative networks and community structure, although often not to the same extent as in the data. The ERGM model, which turned out to be near-degenerate in the parameter region best fitting our data, produces the weakest community structure. (C) 2009 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000269995400003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="60">
<title>Predictors of short-term decay of cell phone contacts in a large scale communication network</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2011.07.002</url>
<snippet>Under what conditions is an edge present in a social network at time t likely to decay or persist by some future time t + Delta t? Previous research addressing this issue suggests that the network range of the people involved in the edge, the extent to which the edge is embedded in a surrounding structure, and the age of the edge all play a role in edge decay. This paper uses weighted data from a large-scale social network built from cell-phone calls in an 8-week period to determine the importance of edge weight for the decay/persistence process. In particular, we study the relative predictive power of directed weight, embeddedness, newness, and range (measured as outdegree) with respect to edge decay and assess the effectiveness with which a simple decision tree and logistic regression classifier can accurately predict whether an edge that was active in one time period continues to be so in a future time period. We find that directed edge weight, weighted reciprocity and time-dependent measures of edge longevity are highly predictive of whether we classify an edge as persistent or decayed, relative to the other types of factors at the dyad and neighborhood level. (C) 2011 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000298122200001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="61">
<title>Micro-structure in micro-neighborhoods: A new social distance measure, and its effect on individual and aggregated perceptions of crime and disorder</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2009.11.001</url>
<snippet>This study links social network methodology with the social disorganization literature to test the effect of block-level social distance on neighborhood perceived crime and disorder. Employing a unique study design that allows creating matrices of social distance (based on demographic characteristics) between 11 residents on each of over 650 blocks at three time points, we find that more socially distant residents perceive more disorder than their neighbors. Consistent with the bridging social capital literature, overall social distance in the block has a curvilinear relationship with perceived crime. And blocks with two cohesive subgroups, based on social distance, have lower levels of perceived disorder. (C) 2009 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000276669100005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="62">
<title>Critical phenomena in complex contagions</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2012.02.003</url>
<snippet>Why do some contagions "go viral" and others do not? Research on "small world" networks (Watts and Strogatz, 1998) shows how a very small number of long-range ties that bridge between clusters can allow contagions to spread almost as rapidly as on a random network of equal density. Recent research shows how long-range ties that accelerate the spread of information and disease can impede the spread of complex contagions-behaviors, beliefs and preferences that diffuse via contact with multiple adopters (Centola and Macy, 2007). In confirming this result analytically and extending the analysis from small world to power law networks, we discovered that complex contagions require a critical mass of infected nodes that corresponds to a phase transition in the ability of the contagion to take advantage of the "shortcuts" created by long-range ties. We demonstrate how this critical mass is related to the dynamics of the contagion process and identify implications for modeling behaviors that spread via social influence, such as viral marketing and social movements. 
WOS:000313304100009
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="63">
<title>Good health and the bridging of structural holes</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2008.10.005</url>
<snippet>Bridges that span structural holes are often explained in terms of the entrepreneurial personalities or rational motivations of brokers, or structural processes that lead to the intersection of social foci. I argue that the existence and use of bridges in interpersonal networks also depends on individuals health. Poor health may make it more difficult to withstand the pressures and to execute some of the common tasks associated with bridging(e.g., brokerage). I examine this possibility using egocentric network data on over 2500 older adults drawn from the recent National Social Life, Health, and Aging Project (NSHAP). Multivariate regression analyses show that both cognitive and functional health are significantly positively associated with bridging, net of sociodemographic and life-course controls. The relationship between functional (kinesthetic) health and bridging appears to be partially mediated by network composition, as older adults who have poorer functional health also tend to have networks that are richer in strong ties. Several potential mediation mechanisms are discussed. Cognitive function remains significantly associated with bridging net of network composition, Suggesting that the inherent challenges of maintaining bridging positions may be more difficult to cope with for those who have cognitive impairments than for those who have functional impairments such as limited mobility. An alternative explanation is that cognitively impaired individuals have more difficulty recognizing (and thus strategically using) bridges in their networks. Theoretical implications and possibilities for future research are discussed. 
WOS:000262547600010
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="64">
<title>The influence of friends on adolescents' behavior problems at school: The role of ego, alter and dyadic characteristics</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2013.08.002</url>
<snippet>This paper deals with the influence of friends in class on adolescents problematic school behavior (i.e. inattention in class and not doing homework). We examine whether this influence is moderated by ego (i.e. the adolescents indegree), alter (i.e. friends indegree) and dyadic characteristics (i.e. friendship reciprocity). Influence processes are analyzed with a stochastic actor-based model (SIENA), while controlling for friendship selection. Using a 4-wave panel dataset, we find that friends influence adolescents problematic school behavior. Adolescents with a higher indegree are less likely to be influenced. The influence of friends is not significantly moderated by friends indegree and friendship reciprocity. (C) 2013 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000328713500007
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="65">
<title>Does proximity matter? Distance dependence of adolescent friendships</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2011.01.002</url>
<snippet>Geographic proximity is a determinant factor of friendship. Friendship datasets that include detailed geographic information are scarce, and when this information is available, the dependence of friendship on distance is often modelled by pre-specified parametric functions or derived from theory without further empirical assessment. This paper aims to give a detailed representation of the association between distance and the likelihood of friendship existence and friendship dynamics, and how this is modified by a few basic social and individual factors. The data employed is a three-wave network of 336 adolescents living in a small Swedish town, for whom information has been collected on their household locations. The analysis is a three-step process that combines (1) nonparametric logistic regressions to unravel the overall functional form of the dependence of friendship on distance, without assuming it has a particular strength or shape; (2) parametric logistic regressions to construct suitable transformations of distance that can be employed in (3) stochastic models for longitudinal network data, to assess how distance, individual covariates, and network structure shape adolescent friendship dynamics. It was found that the log-odds of friendship existence and friendship dynamics decrease smoothly with the logarithm of distance. For adolescents in different schools the dependence is linear, and stronger than for adolescents in the same school. Living nearby accounts, in this dataset, for an aspect of friendship dynamics that is not explicitly modelled by network structure or by individual covariates. In particular, the estimated distance effect is not correlated with reciprocity or transitivity effects. (C) 2011 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000300131600003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="66">
<title>Ethnic segregation in context: Social discrimination among native Dutch pupils and their ethnic minority classmates</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2009.06.002</url>
<snippet>Social discrimination, defined as the relative preference for intra-ethnic over inter-ethnic relationships, was studied in pupils networks in Dutch secondary school classes. While native Dutch pupils (ethnic majority members) mainly named fellow majority members, ethnic minority members reported ties with as many majority as minority members. Considering the ethnic composition of the classroom, however. majority members discriminated less than minorities. No strong effect of classroom ethnic composition on social discrimination was found, whereas neighborhood composition was shown to clearly influence social discrimination: ethnic minority members were more, and majority members less inclined to discriminate in neighborhoods with more ethnic presence. (C) 2009 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000269995400002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="67">
<title>Old friends and new acquaintances: Tie formation mechanisms in an interorganizational network generated by employee mobility</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2013.02.005</url>
<snippet>This study investigates mechanisms of tie formation in an interorganizational network generated by the mobility of employees between organizations. We analyze a data set that contains information on all organizations in the Stockholm metropolitan area between 1990 and 2003. We show that the formation of new ties is contingent upon the direction of past ties, and that most connections occur at an intermediate geodesic distance of 2 and 3. The findings highlight the importance of tie direction and indirect connections in research on network dynamics and knowledge exchanges stemming from the mobility of employees across organizations. 
WOS:000322692600002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="68">
<title>Fundamental principles of network formation among preschool children</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2009.04.003</url>
<snippet>The goal of this research was to investigate the origins of social networks by examining the form at ion of childrens peer relationships in 11 preschool classes throughout the school year. We investigated whether several fundamental processes of relationship formation were evident at this age, including reciprocity, popularity, and triadic closure effects. We expected these mechanisms to change in importance over time as the network crystallizes, allowing more complex Structures to evolve from simpler ones in a process we refer to as structural cascading. We analyzed intensive longitudinal observational data of childrens interactions Using the SIENA actor-based model. We found evidence that reciprocity, popularity, and triadic closure all shaped the formation of preschool childrens networks. The influence of reciprocity remained consistent, whereas popularity and triadic closure became increasingly important over the course of the school year. Interactions between age and endogenous network effects were non-significant, suggesting that these network formation processes were not moderated by age in this sample of young children. We discuss the implications of our longitudinal network approach and findings for the study of early network developmental processes. (C) 2009 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000274948700006
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="69">
<title>The local and global structure of knowledge production in an emergent research field: An exponential random graph analysis</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2010.09.001</url>
<snippet>Previous research has characterized knowledge networks by diffuse connectivity and/or clusters and the absence of centrality. In contrast, exponential random graph models used in this article demonstrate that the uncertainty and centralized influence typical of an emerging area of research leads to the creation of a densely interconnecting core that acts to cohere the network. Moreover, eclecticism and innovativeness, also characteristic of a developing area, lead to a diffusely connected structure. The data, comprising 2200 authors and 76 papers have been manually coded from articles on the feminization of the labor force in Asia. (C) 2010 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000291962000003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="70">
<title>Multiplex networks and interest group influence reputation: An exponential random graph model</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2012.11.003</url>
<snippet>Interest groups struggle to build reputations as influential actors in the policy process and to discern the influence exercised by others. This study conceptualizes influence reputation as a relational variable that varies locally throughout a network. Drawing upon interviews with 168 interest group representatives in the United States health policy domain, this research examines the effects of multiplex networks of communication, coalitions, and issues on influence reputation. Using an exponential random graph model (ERGM), the analysis demonstrates that multiple roles of confidant, collaborator, and issue advocate affect how group representatives understand the influence of those with whom they are tied, after accounting for homophily among interest groups. (C) 2012 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000328803800006
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="71">
<title>A generalized model of relational similarity</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2010.02.001</url>
<snippet>This paper introduces two principles for relational similarity, and based on these principles it proposes a novel geometric representation for similarity. The first principle generalizes earlier measures of similarity such as Pearson-correlation and structural equivalence: while correlation and structural equivalence measure similarity by the extent to which the actors have similar relationships to other actors or objects, the proposed model views two actors similar if they have similar relationships to similar actors or objects. The second principle emphasizes consistency among similarities: not only are actors similar if they have similar relationships to similar objects, but at the same time objects are similar if similar actors relate to them similarly. We examine the behavior of the proposed similarity model through simulations, and re-analyze two classic datasets: the Davis et al. (1941) data on club membership and the roll-call data of the U.S. Senate. We find that the generalized model of similarity is especially useful if (1) the dimensions of comparison are not independent, or (2) the data are sparse, or (3) the boundaries between clusters are not clear. (C) 2010 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000279409000005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="72">
<title>An introduction to exponential random graph (&lt;i&gt;p*&lt;/i&gt;) models for social networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2006.08.002</url>
<snippet>This article provides an introductory summary to the formulation and application of exponential random graph models for social networks. The possible ties among nodes of a network are regarded as random variables, and assumptions about dependencies among these random tie variables determine the general form of the exponential random graph model for the network. Examples of different dependence assumptions and their associated models are given, including Bernoulli, dyad-independent and Markov random graph models. The incorporation of actor attributes in social selection models is also reviewed. Newer, more complex dependence assumptions are briefly outlined. Estimation procedures are discussed, including new methods for Monte Carlo maximum likelihood estimation. We foreshadow the discussion taken up in other papers in this special edition: that the homogeneous Markov random graph models of Frank and Strauss [Frank, O., Strauss, D., 1986. Markov graphs. Journal of the American Statistical Association 81, 832-842] are not appropriate for many observed networks, whereas the new model specifications of Snijders et al. [Snijders, T.A.B., Pattison, P., Robins, G.L., Handock, M. New specifications for exponential random graph models. Sociological Methodology, in press] offer substantial improvement. 
WOS:000246430600002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="73">
<title>Social networkers: Measuring and examining individual differences in propensity to connect with others</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2008.04.003</url>
<snippet>The research examined individual differences in peoples propensity to connect with others (PCO). A measure of PCO, with components for making friends (strong ties), making acquaintances (weak ties), and joining others (bridging ties), was developed and tested in two studies involving 144 undergraduates and 197 health-care employees. PCO and its components were significantly positively associated with social network characteristics (including size, betweenness centrality, and brokerage) and indicators of personal adjustment including support received. attainment, well-being, influence, and suggestion-making. PCO had effects beyond those of major personality traits, and PCO components displayed distinctive relationships with work network characteristics. (C) 2008 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000260367400002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="74">
<title>A study of sign adjustment in weighted signed networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2011.12.006</url>
<snippet>We analyse the adjustment of networks comprising of weighted positive (P) and negative (N) symmetric relations under the impact of various balancing rules. Five kinds of rules are studied: (1) a local minimal edge adjustment which is a special case of, (2) a local pressure based rule, (3) a local sign based rule, (4) a global rule and (5) rules varying on a local to global dimension. The convergence and convergent proportions of different 3-cycles and, thus the impact upon beta(3) balance, under the different kinds of adjustment rule are studied both analytically and through simulation. The effects of network size (n), density (d) and the initial proportion of positive edges (an) upon the convergence of 3-cycles and, thus, balance and the eventual implications for the process of group formation are explored. (C) 2012 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000302394600010
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="75">
<title>Basic notions for the analysis of large two-mode networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2007.04.006</url>
<snippet>Many large real-world networks actually have a two-mode nature: their nodes may be separated into two classes, the links being between nodes of different classes only. Despite this, and despite the fact that many ad hoc tools have been designed for the study of special cases, very few exist to analyse (describe, extract relevant information) such networks in a systematic way. We propose here an extension of the most basic notions used nowadays to analyse large one-mode networks (the classical case) to the two-mode case. To achieve this, we introduce a set of simple statistics, which we discuss by comparing their values on a representative set of real-world networks and on their random versions. This makes it possible to evaluate their relevance in capturing properties of interest in two-mode networks. (C) 2007 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000253735700003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="76">
<title>Curved exponential family models for social networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2006.08.005</url>
<snippet>Curved exponential family models are a useful generalization of exponential random graph models (ERGMs). In particular, models involving the alternating k-star, alternating k-triangle, and alternating k-twopath statistics of Snijders et al. [Snijders, T.A.B., Pattison, P.E., Robins, G.L., Handcock, M.S., in press. New specifications for exponential random graph models. Sociological Methodology] may be viewed as curved exponential family models. This article unifies recent material in the literature regarding curved exponential family models for networks in general and models involving these alternating statistics in particular. It also discusses the intuition behind rewriting the three alternating statistics in terms of the degree distribution and the recently introduced shared partner distributions. This intuition suggests a redefinition of the alternating k-star statistic. Finally, this article demonstrates the use of the statnet package in R for fitting models of this sort, comparing new results on an oft-studied network dataset with results found in the literature. 
WOS:000246430600004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="77">
<title>Social networks and spatial configuration-How office layouts drive social interaction</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2011.05.005</url>
<snippet>This paper analyzes the spatial dimensions of office layouts in diverse knowledge-intensive workplace environments based on the theoretical and methodological propositions of Space Syntax, and brings this together with the analysis of intra-organizational interaction networks. Physical distances between agents are modeled in different ways and used as explanatory variables in exponential random graph modeling. The paper shows that spatial configuration in offices can be considered an important but not sole rationale for tie formation. Furthermore, it is shown that spatial distance measures based on detailed configurational analysis outperform simple Euclidean distance metrics in predicting social ties. (C) 2011 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000300131600005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="78">
<title>Introduction to the special issue on network dynamics</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2009.12.002</url>
<snippet>
WOS:000274948700001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="79">
<title>Social and spatial networks: Kinship distance and dwelling unit proximity in rural Thailand</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2011.04.003</url>
<snippet>We address a long hypothesized relationship between the proximity of individuals dwelling units and their kinship association. Better understanding this relationship is important because of its implications for contact and association among members of a society. In this paper, we use a unique dataset from Nang Rong, Thailand which contains dwelling unit locations (GPS) and saturated kinship networks of all individuals living in 51 agricultural villages. After presenting arguments for a relationship between individuals dwelling unit locations and their kinship relations as well as the particulars of our case study, we introduce the data and describe our analytic approach. We analyze how kinship - considered as both a system linking collections of individuals in an extended kinship network and as dyadic links between pairs of individuals - patterns the proximity of dwelling units in rural villages. The results show that in general, extended kin live closer to one another than do unrelated individuals. Further, the degree of relatedness between kin correlates with the distance between their dwelling units. Close kin are more likely to co-reside, a fact which drives much of the relationship between kinship relatedness and dwelling unit proximity within villages. There is nevertheless suggestive evidence of a relationship between kinship association and dwelling unit proximity among kin who do not live together. (C) 2011 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000300131600010
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="80">
<title>Advances in exponential random graph (&lt;i&gt;p*&lt;/i&gt;) models applied to a large social network</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2006.08.001</url>
<snippet>Recent advances in statistical network analysis based on the family of exponential random graph (ERG) models have greatly improved our ability to conduct inference on dependence in large social networks [Snijders, T.A.B., 2002. Markov Chain Monte Carlo Estimation of Exponential Random Graph Models. Journal of Social Structure 3, 2; Pattison, RE., Robins, G.L., 2002. Neighbourhood-based models for social networks. Sociological Methodology 32, 301-337; Handcock, M.S., 2002. Statistical models for social networks: degeneracy and inference. In: Breiger, R., Carley, K., Pattison, P. (Eds.), Dynamic Social Network Modeling and Analysis. National Academies Press, Washington, DC, pp. 229-240; Handcock, M.S., 2003. Assessing Degeneracy in Statistical Models of Social Networks. Center for Statistics and the Social Sciences, University of Washington, Working Paper No. 39; Snijders, T.A.B., Pattison, R, Robins, G.L., Handcock, M., in press. New specifications for exponential random graph models. Sociological Methodology; Hunter, DR., Goodreau, S.M. Handcock, M.S., 2005. Goodness of Fit of Social Network Models. Center for Statistics and the Social Sciences, University of Washington, Working Paper No. 47; Goodreau, S.M., Hunter, D.R., Morris, M., 2005. Statistical Modeling of Social Networks: Practical Advances and Results. Center for Studies in Demography and Ecology, University of Washington, Working Paper No. 05-01, previous papers this issue]. This paper applies advances in both model parameterizations and computational algorithms to an examination of the structure observed in an adolescent friendship network of 1681 actors from the National Longitudinal Study of Adolescent Health (AddHealth). ERG models of social network structure are fit using the R package statnet, and their adequacy assessed through comparison of model predictions with the observed data for higher-order network statistics. For this friendship network, the commonly used model of Markov dependence leads to the problems of degeneracy discussed by Handcock [Handcock, M.S., 2002. Statistical models for social networks: degeneracy and inference. In: Breiger, R., Carley, K., Pattison, R (Eds.), Dynamic Social Network Modeling and Analysis. National Academic Press, Washington, DC, pp. 229-240; Handcock, M.S., 2003. Assessing Degeneracy in Statistical Models of Social Networks. Center for Statistics and the Social Sciences, University of Washington, Working Paper No. 39]. On the other hand, model parameterizations introduced by Snijders et al. [Snijders, T.A.B., Pattison, R, Robins, G.L., Handcock, M., in press. New specifications for exponential random graph models. Sociological Methodology] and Hunter and Handcock [Hunter, D.R., Handcock, M.S., in press. Inference in curved exponential family models for networks. Journal of Computational and Graphical Statistics] avoid degeneracy and provide reasonable fit to the data. Degree-only models did a poor job of capturing observed network structure; those that did best included terms both for heterogeneous mixing on exogenous attributes (grade and self-reported race) as well as endogenous clustering. Networks simulated from this model were largely consistent with the observed network on multiple higher-order network statistics, including the number of triangles, the size of the largest component, the overall reachability, the distribution of geodesic distances, the degree distribution, and the shared partner distribution. The ability to fit such models to large datasets and to make inference,about the underling processes generating the network represents a major advance in the field of statistical network analysis. 
WOS:000246430600005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="81">
<title>Bringing the owners back in: An analysis of a 3-mode interlock network</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2012.01.005</url>
<snippet>This paper examines the association between ownership and director interlocks in Swedish big business during the period 1990-2005. By analyses of the 3-mode network of owners, firms, and directors, multiple director assignments are shown to be highly dependent on owner interlocks. The findings provide a new understanding of the mechanisms behind the formation of director interlocks. Furthermore, the association between the interlock types suggests that the ownership network may potentially (co-)produce some of the phenomena that have been attributed to the director network. Future analyses of director interlocks have to bring the owners back in. (C) 2012 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000302394600012
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="82">
<title>Immigrant children and their parents: Is there an intergenerational interdependence of integration into social networks?</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2014.11.002</url>
<snippet>The paper investigates the integration of immigrant children and their parents in different dimensions of social networks - referred to as multiplexity in social network terminology. These dimensions are childrens friendships, their attendance at birthday parties, and contact among their parents. By attending birthday parties, childrens friendships are publicly reinforced and membership in a social circle is signified. During these events, communication and social exchange drive the process of social integration at the micro-level, and ethnic boundaries can be shifted or blurred. It will be shown that a variety of homophily effects can be found in all three network dimensions. In addition, ethnic segregation in parents networks has an impact on childrens participation in these events and, thereby, on childrens integration in social networks. However, the causal effect in the other way around - childrens birthday party attendance on contact among their parents - is even stronger. A new approach is the non-recursive analysis of how ties in one network dimension effect ties in another dimension. Analyses are based on 76 social networks of 1266 children in school classes in the city state of Bremen, Germany. 
WOS:000347585500019
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="83">
<title>Ethnic ingroup friendships in schools: Testing the by-product hypothesis in England, Germany, the Netherlands and Sweden</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2014.04.003</url>
<snippet>This study set out to examine to what extent ethnic ingroup friendship in secondary school classes are a by-product of cultural and socioeconomic ingroup friendship. Based on homophily theory, we expected similar opinions, leisure activities, religion, risk behaviour and socioeconomic factors to (partly) explain ethnic ingroup preferences. Multilevel p(2) models on 13,272 pupils in 625 secondary school classes in England, Germany, the Netherlands and Sweden showed that adolescents tend to have friends similar in ethnicity, cultural and socioeconomic characteristics. We find no evidence, however, that ethnic homophily is explained by cultural and socioeconomic homophily. (C) 2014 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000340338600004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="84">
<title>The analysis of multiple ties in longitudinal egocentric network data: A case study on bidirectional relationships between trust and drug use</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2012.08.005</url>
<snippet>We extend multi-level models to examine single egocentric network ties to the joint analysis of paired dynamic ties. Two analytic challenges are addressed. First, inference needs to account for multiple layers of nesting: ties are nested within pairs, pairs are nested within time points, and time points are nested within egos. Second, the focus is on the relationship between two dynamic ties; specification of outcome and predictor may be difficult. Instead, we treat both ties as outcomes. Our approach is used to analyze trust and reported drug use between egos and alters over time in a Bayesian framework. (C) 2012 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000313304100031
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="85">
<title>Comparative configurational analysis as a two-mode network problem: A study of terrorist group engagement in the drug trade</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2013.04.002</url>
<snippet>We generalize a form of two-mode network analysis to make it applicable to a cases-by-variables data format, and apply our approach for the study of terrorist group engagement in the drug trade, emphasizing the implications of our approach for policy in a study of 395 terrorist organizations. Based on the organizations levels of resources, network connectivity to other groups, ideological emphasis, and participation in multiple illicit economies, we identify several distinctive configurations of factors that lead to multiple types of drug activity. We also demonstrate a technique for assessing sampling variability in configurational models. (C) 2013 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000328803800003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="86">
<title>Youth co-offending networks: An investigation of social and spatial effects</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2011.02.001</url>
<snippet>This research tests the relative contribution of social distance and spatial distance to the presence of ties between neighborhoods based on youth co-offending. Using official court data from a large U.S. metropolitan area, a set of dyad independence and exponential random graph models are estimated in order to investigate the characteristics of neighborhoods that foster co-offending. Results reveal significant effects of both social and spatial distance. Social distance contributes to network structure net of spatial proximity, though spatial factors better explain the overall network structure. These results have methodological implications for the analysis of spatial effects and criminal behavior. (C) 2011 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000300131600012
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="87">
<title>Triadic closure in two-mode networks: Redefining the global and local clustering coefficients</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2011.07.001</url>
<snippet>As the vast majority of network measures are defined for one-mode networks, two-mode networks often have to be projected onto one-mode networks to be analyzed. A number of issues arise in this transformation process, especially when analyzing ties among nodes' contacts. For example, the values attained by the global and local clustering coefficients on projected random two-mode networks deviate from the expected values in corresponding classical one-mode networks. Moreover, both the local clustering coefficient and constraint (structural holes) are inversely associated to nodes' two-mode degree. To overcome these issues, this paper proposes redefinitions of the clustering coefficients for two-mode networks. (C) 2011 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000320479500003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="88">
<title>Movement without mobility: Adolescent status hierarchies and the contextual limits of cumulative advantage</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2014.10.004</url>
<snippet>This paper develops a theory of interpersonal status hierarchies that builds on and challenges traditional models of cumulative advantage. Cumulative advantage models predict stability in interpersonal status hierarchies, where status is defined by asymmetries in social relationships. According to strict cumulative advantage, initial status differences are exaggerated over time, making upward or downward mobility unlikely. We argue that interpersonal status hierarchies are instead quite fluid, with individuals regularly moving up or down the hierarchy. Individual status gains do not, however, disrupt the status order as the upwardly mobile are often pulled back to their original positions. This drag of the past generates the same long run status outcomes as cumulative advantage models, but through very different means: sustained upward mobility is rare because the upwardly mobile fail to maintain their status gains, and not because initial gains are impossible. More generally, the effect of the past limits sustained mobility in most, but not all, status hierarchies, and we expect sustained mobility where ties are stable and the expectations for reciprocity are low. We test our model using longitudinal data on adolescents, finding strong support for the theory. We end the paper with a reflexive discussion about measurement error, hypothesis testing, and "messy" longitudinal network data. 
WOS:000347585500014
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="89">
<title>The rationality of social structure: Cooperation in social dilemmas through investments in and returns on social capital</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2013.05.006</url>
<snippet>We develop a game-theoretic model of how social structure in the sense of a network of relations between actors helps to mitigate social dilemmas. We simultaneously endogenize the network by modeling actors incentives to establish the network. Since the network of relations helps to mitigate social dilemmas, it constitutes social capital. We thus analyze investments in and returns on social capital in social dilemmas and characterize the value of social capital. Our model covers a class of social dilemma games including the Trust Game, the Investment Game, the Prisoners Dilemma, the two-actor Public Goods Game, and others. (C) 2013 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000328713500018
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="90">
<title>Networks of action and events over time. A multilevel discrete-time event history model for longitudinal network data</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2010.09.003</url>
<snippet>Longitudinal network data recording the moment at which ties appear, change, or disappear are increasingly available. Event history models can be used to analyze the dynamics of time-stamped network data. This paper adapts the discrete-time event history model to social network data. A discrete-time event history model can easily incorporate a multilevel design and time-varying covariates. A multilevel design is needed to account for dependencies among ties and vertices, which should not be ignored in a small longitudinal network. Time-varying covariates are required to analyze network effects, that is, the impact of previous ties. In addition, a discrete-time event history model handles constraints on who can act or who can be acted upon in a straightforward way. The model can be estimated with multilevel logistic regression analysis, which is illustrated by an application to book reviews, so network evolution can be analyzed with a fairly standard statistical tool. (C) 2010 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000291962000004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="91">
<title>Discovery of anomalous behaviour in temporal networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2014.12.001</url>
<snippet>In this work we consider the problem of detecting anomalous behaviour and present a novel approach that allows 'behaviour' to be classified as either to be normal or abnormal by checking the p-value associated with the occurrence of the behaviour which is modelled following a binomial distribution within a discrete time model. We investigate the problem of detecting anomalous behaviour by looking at how communication evolves over time in a social network graph. Under the assumption that some nodes of the network could be labelled qualitatively, we present a novel approach that allows us to infer a subset of nodes of the social network which might share the same qualitative connotation. In other words, assuming one or more members belong to some criminal organisation, we wish to investigate how many other persons belong to the same organisation. We have tested our method in two datasets, VAST2008 and a Twitter Dataset (data collected in 2012), with encouraging results. (C) 2014 The Authors. Published by Elsevier B.V. This is an open access article under the CC BY license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/).
WOS:000351979100002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="92">
<title>Social context and network formation: An experimental study</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2008.10.001</url>
<snippet>Recently, there has been increasing interest in determining which social network structures emerge as a consequence of the conscious actions of actors. Motivated by the belief that "networks matter" in reaching personal objectives, it is a natural assumption that actors try to optimize their network position. Starting from the notion that an optimal network position depends on the social context, we examine how actors change their networks to reach better positions in various contexts. Distinguishing between three social contexts (a neutral context, a context in which closed triads are costly, and a context in which closed triads are beneficial), theoretical results predict that emerging networks are contingent on the incentives that are present in these contexts. Experiments are used to test whether networks that are theoretically predicted to be stable are also stable experimentally. We find that emerging networks correspond to a large extent with the predicted networks. Consequently, they are contingent on the incentives present in various social contexts. In addition, we find that subjects tend to form specific stable networks with a higher probability than predicted, namely, efficient networks and networks in which everyone is equally well off. 
WOS:000262547600007
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="93">
<title>Considering clustering measures: Third ties, means, and triplets</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2013.02.007</url>
<snippet>Measures that estimate the clustering coefficients of ego and overall social networks are important to social network studies. Existing measures differ in how they define and estimate triplet clustering with implications for how network theoretic properties are reflected. In this paper, we propose a novel definition of triplet clustering for weighted and undirected social networks that explicitly considers the relative strength of the tie connecting the two alters of the ego in the triplet. We argue that our proposed definition better reflects theorized effects of the important third tie in the social network literature. We also develop new methods for estimating triplet, local and global clustering. Three different types of mathematical means, i.e. arithmetic, geometric, and quadratic, are used to reflect alternative theoretical assumptions concerning the marginal effect of tie substitution. 
WOS:000322692600003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="94">
<title>Explaining the power-law degree distribution in a social commerce network</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2009.07.002</url>
<snippet>Social commerce is an emerging trend in which online shops create referral hyperlinks to other shops in the same online marketplace. We study the evolution of a social commerce network in a large online marketplace. Our dataset starts before the birth of the network (at which points shops were not linked to each other) and includes the birth of the network. The network under study exhibits a typical power-law degree distribution. We empirically compare a set of edge formation mechanisms (including preferential attachment and triadic closure) that may explain the emergence of this property. Our results suggest that the evolution of the network and the emergence of its power-law degree distribution are better explained by a network evolution mechanism that relies on vertex attributes that are not based on the structure of the network. Specifically, Our analysis suggests that the power-law degree distribution emerges because shops prefer to connect to shops with more diverse assortments, and assortment diversity follows a power-law distribution. Shops with more diverse assortments are more attractive to link to because they are more likely to bring traffic from consumers browsing the WWW. Therefore, our results also imply that social commerce networks should not be studied in isolation, but rather in the context of the broader network in which they are embedded (the WWW). (C) 2009 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000269995400005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="95">
<title>A model for the multiplex dynamics of two-mode and one-mode networks, with an application to employment preference, friendship, and advice</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2012.05.005</url>
<snippet>We propose a new stochastic actor-oriented model for the co-evolution of two-mode and one-mode networks. The model posits that activities of a set of actors, represented in the two-mode network, co-evolve with exchanges and interactions between the actors, as represented in the one-mode network. The model assumes that the actors, not the activities, have agency. The empirical value of the model is demonstrated by examining how employment preferences co-evolve with friendship and advice relations in a group of seventy-five MBA students. The analysis shows that activity in the two-mode network, as expressed by number of employment preferences, is related to activity in the friendship network, as expressed by outdegrees. Further, advice ties between students lead to agreement with respect to employment preferences. In addition, considering the multiplexity of advice and friendship ties yields a better understanding of the dynamics of the advice relation: tendencies to reciprocation and homophily in advice relations are mediated to an important extent by friendship relations. The discussion pays attention to the implications of this study in the broader context of current efforts to model the co-evolutionary dynamics of social networks and individual behavior. (C) 2012 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000320479500011
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="96">
<title>Opening the black box of link formation: Social factors underlying the structure of the web</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2009.07.003</url>
<snippet>Links play a twofold role on the web: they open the channels through which users access information, and they determine the centrality of sites and their visibility. This paper adds two factors to the analysis of links that aim to draw a parallel between the web and other offline interorganisational networks: the resources that the organisations publishing online are able to mobilise, and the status or public recognition of those organisations. Exponential random graph models (ERGMs) are used to analyse a sample of the web of about one thousand sites, showing that both the economic resources of the producers of the sites (a proxy to their wider pool of resources) and their presence in traditional news media (a proxy to their status) significantly increase their probability of receiving more links, and therefore, their centrality. This adds a sociologically relevant dimension to the analysis of the web that has been disregarded so far but that is crucial to understand the way it distributes visibility. (C) 2009 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000269995400006
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="97">
<title>Measurement error in network data: A re-classification</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2012.01.003</url>
<snippet>Research on measurement error in network data has typically focused on missing data. We embed missing data, which we term false negative nodes and edges, in a broader classification of error scenarios. This includes false positive nodes and edges and falsely aggregated and disaggregated nodes. We simulate these six measurement errors using an online social network and a publication citation network, reporting their effects on four node-level measures - degree centrality, clustering coefficient, network constraint, and eigenvector centrality. Our results suggest that in networks with more positively-skewed degree distributions and higher average clustering, these measures tend to be less resistant to most forms of measurement error. In addition, we argue that the sensitivity of a given measure to an error scenario depends on the idiosyncracies of the measures calculation, thus revising the general claim from past research that the more global a measure, the less resistant it is to measurement error. Finally, we anchor our discussion to commonly-used networks in past research that suffer from these different forms of measurement error and make recommendations for correction strategies. (C) 2012 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000313304100004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="98">
<title>Influentials, novelty, and social contagion The viral power of average friends, close communities, and old news</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2012.02.005</url>
<snippet>What is the effect of (1) popular individuals, and (2) community structures on the retransmission of socially contagious behavior? We examine a community of Twitter users over a five month period, operationalizing social contagion as retweeting, and social structure as the count of subgraphs (small patterns of ties and nodes) between users in the follower/following network. We find that popular individuals act as 'inefficient hubs' for social contagion: they have limited attention, are overloaded with inputs, and therefore display limited responsiveness to viral messages. We argue this contradicts the 'law of the few' and influentials hypothesis'. We find that community structures, particularly reciprocal ties and certain triadic structures, substantially increase social contagion. This contradicts the theory that communities display lower internal contagion because of the inherent redundancy and lack of novelty of messages within a community. Instead, we speculate that the reasons community structures show increased social contagion are, first, that members of communities have higher similarity (reflecting shared interests and characteristics. increasing the relevance of messages), and second, that communities amplify the social bonding effect of retransmitted messages. (C) 2012 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000313304100011
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="99">
<title>Social context, spatial structure and social network structure</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2010.09.002</url>
<snippet>Frequently, social networks are studied in their own right with analyses devoid of contextual details. Yet contextual features - both social and spatial - can have impacts on the networks formed within them. This idea is explored with five empirical networks representing different contexts and the use of distinct modeling strategies. These strategies include network visualizations, QAP regression, exponential random graph models, blockmodeling and a combination of blockmodels with exponential random graph models within a single framework. We start with two empirical examples of networks inside organizations. The familiar Bank Wiring Room data show that the social organization (social context) and spatial arrangement of the room help account for the social relations formed there. The second example comes from a police academy where two designed arrangements, one social and one spatial, powerfully determine the relational social structures formed by recruits. The next example is an inter-organizational network that emerged as part of a response to a natural disaster where features of the improvised context helped account for the relations that formed between organizations participating in the search and rescue mission. We then consider an anthropological example of signed relations among sub-tribes in the New Guinea highlands where the physical geography is fixed. This is followed by a trading network off the Dalmatian coast where geography and physical conditions matter. Through these examples, we show that context matters by shaping the structure of networks that form and that a variety of network analytic tools can be mobilized to reveal how networks are shaped, in part, by social and spatial contexts. Implications for studying social networks are suggested. (C) 2010 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000300131600004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="100">
<title>Short- and long-term stability in organizational networks: Temporal structures of project teams</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2013.07.001</url>
<snippet>Network research focuses on patterns of stable relationships, where stability represents the unfolding of social processes over long time frames. We argue that social interactions exhibit important regularities in different time frames (short and long term), reflecting distinct social processes. We illustrate the value of this distinction through a comparative case study of technology-mediated communication, within two project teams in a digital marketing agency. We examine how the embedding of interpersonal interactions in processes of reciprocity and closure over different time horizons enables the emergence of cohesion in the face of constant compositional changes. We propose that the time frames in which stable patterns of interactions develop are the key to understanding the nature of the underlying social processes with short-term patterns of closure and reciprocity representing adaptation to change while longer term patterns indicate cohesion. Our results are supportive of this argument and show that the two teams exhibit the same regularities in interactions but across different time horizons. We discuss the implication of our findings and argue that distinguishing between short- and long-term stability of social networks offers a novel and promising avenue for network research. (C) 2013 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000328713500003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="101">
<title>An agent-based random-utility-maximization model to generate social networks with transitivity in geographic space</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2013.05.002</url>
<snippet>Stochastic actor-based approaches receive increasing interest in the generation of social networks for simulation in time and space. Existing models however cannot be readily integrated in agent-based models that assume random-utility-maximizing behavior of agents. We propose an agent-based model to generate social networks explicitly in geographic space which is formulated in the random-utility-maximizing (RUM) framework. The proposed model consists of a friendship formation mechanism and a component to simulate social encounters in a population. We show how transitivity can be incorporated in both components and how the model can be estimated based on data of personal networks using likelihood estimation. In an application to the Swiss context, we demonstrate the estimation and ability of the model to reproduce relevant characteristics of networks, such as geographic proximity, attribute similarity (homophily), size of personal networks (degree distribution) and clustering (transitivity). We conclude that the proposed social-network model fits seamlessly in existing large-scale micro-simulation systems which assume RUM behavior of agents. 
WOS:000322692600016
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="102">
<title>The development of adolescents' friendships and antipathies: A longitudinal multivariate network test of balance theory</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2015.05.003</url>
<snippet>We examined the interplay between friendship (best friend) and antipathy (dislike) relationships among adolescents (N=480; 11-14 years) in two US middle schools over three years (grades 6, 7, and 8). Using longitudinal multivariate network analysis (RSiena), the effects of friendships on antipathies and vice versa were tested, while structural network effects (e.g., density, reciprocity, and transitivity) and individual (age, gender, and ethnicity) and behavioral (prosocial and antisocial behavior) dispositions were controlled for. Based on (structural) balance theory, it was expected that friendships would be formed or maintained when two adolescents disliked the same person (shared enemy hypothesis), that friends would tend to agree on whom they disliked (friends agreement hypothesis), that adolescents would tend to dislike the friends of those they disliked (reinforced animosity hypothesis), and, finally, that they would become or stay friends with dislikes of dislikes (enemys enemy hypothesis). Support was found for the first three hypotheses, and partially for the fourth hypothesis. Results are discussed in light of adolescents peer relationships. (C) 2015 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000358626400015
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="103">
<title>Co-evolution of conventions and networks: An experimental study</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2009.04.002</url>
<snippet>We study the emergence of conventions in dynamic networks experimentally. Conventions are modeled in terms of coordination games in which actors call choose both their behavior and their interaction partners. We Study how macro-level outcomes of the process in terms of Pareto-efficiency and heterogeneity depend on initial conditions. Moreover, we examine the underlying processes at the microlevel. Predictions are derived from a game-theoretic model which is applied to Our experimental conditions by means of computer simulation. The results provide mixed Support for the macro-level hypotheses, and indicate possible directions to improve the model at the micro level. (C) 2009 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000274948700002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="104">
<title>Clustering in weighted networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2009.02.002</url>
<snippet>In recent years, researchers have investigated a growing number of weighted networks where ties are differentiated according to their strength or capacity. Yet, most network measures do not take weights into consideration, and thus do not fully capture the richness of the information contained in the data. In this paper, we focus on a measure originally defined for unweighted networks: the global clustering coefficient. We propose a generalization of this coefficient that retains the information encoded in the weights of ties. We then undertake a comparative assessment by applying the standard and generalized coefficients to a number of network datasets. (C) 2009 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000265325900006
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="105">
<title>Relational collaboration among spatial multipoint competitors</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2010.10.005</url>
<snippet>The presence of network ties between multipoint competitors is frequently assumed but rarely examined directly. The outcomes of multipoint competition, therefore, are better understood than their underlying relational mechanisms. Using original fieldwork and data that we have collected on an interorganizational network of patient transfer relations within a regional community of hospitals, we report and interpret estimates of Exponential Random Graph Models (ERGM) that specify the probability of observing network ties between organizations as a function of the degree of their spatial multipoint contact. We find that hospitals competing more intensely for patients across multiple geographical segments of their market (spatial multipoint competitors) are significantly more likely to collaborate. This conclusion is robust to alternative explanations for the formation of network ties based on organizational size differences, resource complementarities, performance differentials, and capacity constraints. We show that interorganizational networks between spatial multipoint competitors are characterized by clear tendencies toward clustering and a global core-periphery structure arising as consequences of multiple mechanisms of triadic closure operating simultaneously. We conclude that the effects of competition on the structure of interorganizational fields depends on how markets as physical and social settings are connected by cross-cutting network ties between competitors. (C) 2010 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000300131600009
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="106">
<title>A comparison of email networks and off-line social networks: A study of a medium-sized bank</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2012.02.004</url>
<snippet>Recently there has been a surge in the availability of online data concerning the connections between people, and these online data are now widely used to map the social structure of communities. There has been little research, however, on how these new types of relational data correspond to classical measures of social networks. To fill this gap, we contrast the structure of an email network with the underlying friendship, communication, and advice seeking networks. Our study is an explorative case study of a bank, and our data contains emails among employees and a survey of the ego networks of the employees. Through calculating correlations with QAP standard errors and estimating exponential random graph (ERG) models, we find that although the email network is related to the survey-based social networks, email networks are also significantly different: while off-line social networks are strongly shaped by gender, tenure, and hierarchical boundaries, the role of these boundaries are much weaker in the email network. 
WOS:000313304100010
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="107">
<title>A framework for the comparison of maximum pseudo-likelihood and maximum likelihood estimation of exponential family random graph models</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2008.10.003</url>
<snippet>The statistical modeling of social network data is difficult due to the complex dependence structure of the tie variables. Statistical exponential families of distributions provide a flexible way to model such dependence. They enable the statistical characteristics of the network to be encapsulated within an exponential family random graph (ERG) model. For a longtime, however, likelihood-based estimation was only feasible for ERG models assuming dyad independence. For more realistic and complex models inference has been based on the pseudo-likelihood. Recent advances in computational methods have made likelihood-based inference practical, and comparison of the different estimators possible. In this paper, we present methodology to enable estimators of ERG model parameters to be compared. We use this methodology to compare the bias, standard errors, coverage rates and efficiency of maximum likelihood and maximum pseudo-likelihood estimators. We also propose an improved pseudo-likelihood estimation method aimed at reducing bias. The comparison is performed using simulated social network data based on two versions of an empirically realistic network model, the first representing Lazega's law firm data and the second a modified version with increased transitivity. The framework considers estimation of both the natural and the mean-value parameters. The results clearly show the superiority of the likelihood-based estimators over those based on pseudo-likelihood, with the bias-reduced pseudo-likelihood out-performing the general pseudo-likelihood. The use of the mean-value parameterization provides insight into the differences between the estimators and when these differences will matter in practice. 
WOS:000262547600006
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="108">
<title>The role of reciprocation in social network formation, with an application to LiveJournal</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2013.03.003</url>
<snippet>This paper deals with the role of reciprocation in the formation of individuals social networks. We follow the activity of a panel of bloggers over more than a year and investigate the extent to which initiating a relation brings about its reciprocation. We adapt a standard capital investment model to study how reciprocation affects the build-up of the individual social capital of bloggers, as measured by their links and interactions with others. This allows us to measure the role of content production and relationship building in the dynamics of online social networks and to distinguish between the social networking and media aspects of blogging. 
WOS:000322692600005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="109">
<title>One-mode projection analysis and design of covert affiliation networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2012.07.001</url>
<snippet>Within the field of national security and counterterrorism a great need exists to understand covert organizations. To better understand these cellular structures we model and analyze these cells as a collection of subsets of all participants in the covert organization, i.e., as hypergraphs or affiliation networks. Such a covert affiliation network structure is analyzed by evaluating the one-mode projection of the corresponding hypergraph. First we provide a characterization of the total distance in the one-mode projection using its corresponding cell-shrunken version. Secondly we evaluate the one-mode projection with respect to the secrecy versus information tradeoff dilemma every covert organization has to solve. We present and analyze affiliation networks representing common covert organizational forms: star, path and semi-complete hypergraphs. In addition we evaluate an example of a covert organization wishing to conduct an attack and compare its performance to that of the common covert organizational forms. Finally we investigate affiliation networks that are optimal in the sense of balancing secrecy and information. We show how any affiliation tree can be improved by altering its structure. Finally we prove that among covert organizational forms in the class of hypertrees with the same number of cells uniform star affiliation networks are optimal. (C) 2012 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000313304100024
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="110">
<title>Dyadic regression in the presence of heteroscedasticity-An assessment of alternative approaches</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2010.04.002</url>
<snippet>Although the problem of heteroscedasticity has been the subject of much discussion in other areas of applied statistics the problem has received scant attention in the social network literature. This study attempts to remedy this situation by considering how traditional methods for significance testing in dyadic regression models, such as standard QAP tests, perform under conditions of heteroscedasticity. Moreover, the article presents two alternative methods to deal with heteroscedasticity that are both shown to perform rather well with typical social network data under conditions of both heteroscedasticity and homoscedasticity. Overall, the results of the study suggest that applied researchers using regression techniques to study dyadic data are well advised to correct for heteroscedasticity, by either of the two methods discussed here, whenever there is a reason to suspect heteroscedasticity. (C) 2010 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000283402000003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="111">
<title>Introduction to the special issue on Network Dynamics (Part 2)</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2012.05.001</url>
<snippet>
WOS:000305495600001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="112">
<title>Where do intra-organizational advice relations come from? The role of informal status and social capital in social exchange</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2011.04.002</url>
<snippet>Social status and social capital frameworks are used to derive competing hypotheses about the emergence and structure of advice relations in organizations. Although both approaches build on a social exchange framework, they differ in their behavioral micro-foundations. From a status perspective, advice giving is a means to generate prestige, whereas asking advice decreases ones relative standing. At a structural level these motivations are expected to result in an overrepresentation of non-reciprocal dyads and non-cyclical triadic structures in the advice network, as well as in active advice seekers being unlikely to be approached for advice, especially by active advice givers. From a social capital perspective, advice seeking creates obligations for the advice seeker. At the structural level, this results in an overrepresentation of reciprocal dyads and cyclical triads, and active advice seekers to be unpopular as targets of advice seeking, especially for active advice givers. Analyses of four waves of a longitudinal sociometric study of 57 employees of a Dutch Housing Corporation provide partial support for both approaches. In line with the social capital perspective, we find reciprocal advice relations to be overrepresented at the dyad level. Results at the triad level support the social status arguments, according to which high status individuals will avoid asking advice from low status individuals. The implications for macro-structural properties of intra-organizational advice network are discussed. (C) 2011 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000305495600005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="113">
<title>Models and methods in social network analysis.</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2007.02.001</url>
<snippet>
WOS:000250964800009
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="114">
<title>Covert social movement networks and the secrecy-efficiency trade off: The case of the UK suffragettes (1906-1914)</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2012.07.004</url>
<snippet>This paper formulates and empirically tests a number of hypotheses regarding the impact of covertness upon network structure. Specifically, hypotheses are deduced from theoretical arguments regarding a secrecy-efficiency trade off which is said to shape covert networks. The paper draws upon data concerning the UK suffragettes. It is taken from a publicly archived UK Home Office document listing 1992 court appearances (for suffrage related activities), involving 1214 individuals and 394 court sessions, between 1906 and 1914. Network structure at earlier phases of suffragette activism, when the movement was less covert, is compared with that during the final phase, when it was more covert and meets the definitional criteria of what we call a covert social movement network (CSMN). Support for the various hypotheses tested is variable but the key claims derived from the idea of the secrecy-efficiency trade off are supported. Specifically, the suffragettes network becomes less dense and less degree centralised as it becomes more covert. 
WOS:000313304100026
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="115">
<title>Recent developments in exponential random graph (&lt;i&gt;p&lt;/i&gt;*) models for social networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2006.08.003</url>
<snippet>This article reviews new specifications for exponential random graph models proposed by Snijders et al. [Snijders, T.A.B., Pattison, P., Robins, G.L., Handcock, M., 2006. New specifications for exponential random graph models. Sociological Methodology] and demonstrates their improvement over homogeneous Markov random graph models in fitting empirical network data. Not only do the new specifications show improvements in goodness of fit for various data sets, but they also help to avoid the problem of near-degeneracy that often afflicts the fitting of Markov random graph models in practice, particularly to network data exhibiting high levels of transitivity. The inclusion of a new higher order transitivity statistic allows estimation of parameters of exponential graph models for many (but not all) cases where it is impossible to estimate parameters of homogeneous Markov graph models. The new specifications were used to model a large number of classical small-scale network data sets and showed a dramatically better performance than Markov graph models. We also review three current programs for obtaining maximum likelihood estimates of model parameters and we compare these Monte Carlo maximum likelihood estimates with less accurate pseudo-likelihood estimates. Finally, we discuss whether homogeneous Markov random graph models may be superseded by the new specifications, and how additional elaborations may further improve model performance. 
WOS:000246430600003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="116">
<title>Reciprocity, transitivity, and the mysterious three-cycle</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2014.10.005</url>
<snippet>Reciprocity and transitivity are the two most important structural mechanisms underlying friendship network evolution. While on their own they are understood in great detail, the relation between them is rarely studied systematically. Are friendships outside of social groups more or less likely to be reciprocated than friendships embedded in a group? Using a theoretical framework that focusses on the situations in which friends interact and the social structures that stabilise one-sided friendships, I propose that the tendency towards reciprocation of friendships within transitive groups is usually lower than outside of transitive groups. In a meta-analysis of two datasets including 29 friendship networks using stochastic actor-oriented models (SAOMs), the interaction between reciprocity and transitivity is analysed. Supporting the theoretical reasoning, the interaction is consistently negative. Second, the tendency against forming three-cycles in friendship networks, which was consistently found in previous studies, is shown to be spurious and a result of neglecting to control for the tendency against reciprocation in transitive groups. The tendency against three-cycles is commonly seen as an indicator that unreciprocated friendships indicate local hierarchy differences between individuals; this proposition has to be re-evaluated in light of the findings of this study. Future studies that analyse the evolution of friendship networks should consider modelling reciprocation in transitive triplets and potentially omit modelling three-cycles. 
WOS:000347585500016
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="117">
<title>A comparison of various approaches to the exponential random graph model: A reanalysis of 102 student networks in school classes</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2007.03.002</url>
<snippet>This paper describes an empirical comparison of four specifications of the exponential family of random graph models (ERGM), distinguished by model specification (dyadic independence, Markov, partial conditional dependence) and, for the Markov model, by estimation method (Maximum Pseudolikelihood, Maximum Likelihood). This was done by reanalyzing 102 student networks in 57 junior high school classes. At the level of all classes combined, earlier substantive conclusions were supported by all specifications. However, the different specifications led to different conclusions for individual classes. PL produced unreliable estimates (when ML is regarded as the standard) and had more convergence problems than ML. Furthermore, the estimates of covariate effects were affected considerably by controlling for network structure, although the precise specification of the structural part (Markov or partial conditional dependence) mattered less. (C) 2007 Elsevier BX All rights reserved.
WOS:000250964800002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="118">
<title>The evolution and formation of amicus curiae networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2012.07.003</url>
<snippet>This paper sheds light on two age-old questions of interest group behavior: how have interest group coalition strategies changed over time and which factors determine whether interest groups work together? Through the creation of a new network measure of interest group coalitions based on cosigner status to United States Supreme Court amicus curiae briefs, we illuminate the central players and overall characteristics of this dynamic network from 1930 to 2009. We present evidence of an increasingly transitive network resembling a host of tightly grouped factions and leadership hub organizations employing mixed coalition strategies. We also model the attribute homophily and structure of the present-day network. We find assortative mixing of interest groups based on industry area, budget, sales and membership. (C) 2012 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000328803800007
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="119">
<title>How stable is the core discussion network?</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2014.09.001</url>
<snippet>Researchers have paid increasing attention to the core discussion network, the set of people we turn to when discussing important matters. Because the core discussion network is theorized to be composed of peoples closest ties, not fleeting acquaintances, it is expected to be largely stable, evolving slowly over the span of peoples lives. However, recent studies have shown that networks are strongly affected by the contexts in which people interact with others, and as people experience life course transitions, they also often enter new contexts - school, college, work, marriage, and retirement. We ask whether, as actors enter new social contexts, the core discussion network remains stable or changes rapidly. Based on original, longitudinal, qualitative and quantitative data on the experience of first-year graduate students in three academic departments in a large university, we examine the stability of the core discussion network over the first 6 and 12 months in this new context. We test four competing hypotheses that focus on strength of ties, new opportunities, obligations, and routine activity and predict, respectively, stasis, expansion, shedding, and substitution. We find that the core discussion network changes remarkably quickly, with little or no lag, and that it appears to do so because both the obligations that people face and the routine activities they engage in are transformed by new institutional environments. Findings suggest that core discussion network may be less a "core" network than a highly contextual support network in which people are added and dropped as actors shift from environment to environment. 
WOS:000347585500010
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="120">
<title>The dual network structure of organizational problem solving: A case study on open source software development</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2012.12.003</url>
<snippet>We reconstruct the dual network structure generated by the association between 72 contributors and 737 software bugs engaged during a full development cycle of the free/open source software project Epiphany. Estimates of structural parameters of Exponential Random Graph Models for two-mode networks reveal the structural logics shaping activities of collaborative problem solving. After controlling for contributor-specific and software bug-specific characteristics, we find that contributors ("problem solvers") tend to distribute their activity over multiple software bugs. At the same time, however, we find that software bugs ("problems") tend not to share multiple contributors. This dual tendency toward de-specialization and exclusivity is sustained by specific local network dependencies revealed by our analysis which also suggests possible organizational mechanisms that may be underlying the puzzling macro-structural regularities frequently observed, but rarely explained, in the production of open source software. By combining these mechanisms with the influence of contributors characterized by different levels of involvement in the project, we provide micro-level evidence of structural interdependence between "core" and "peripheral" members identified exclusively on the basis of their individual level of contribution to the project. (C) 2013 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000320479500009
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="121">
<title>Geographical variability and network structure</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2011.08.003</url>
<snippet>In this paper, we explore the potential implications of geographical variability for the structure of social networks. Beginning with some basic simplifying assumptions, we derive a number of ways in which local network structure should be expected to vary across a region whose population is unevenly distributed. To examine the manner in which these effects would be expected to manifest given realistic population distributions, we then perform an exploratory simulation study that examines the features of large-scale interpersonal networks generated using block-level data from the 2000 U.S. Census. Using a stratified sample of micropolitan and metropolitan areas with populations ranging from approximately 1000 to 1,000,000 persons, we extrapolatively simulate network structure using spatial network models calibrated to two fairly proximate social relations. From this sample of simulated networks, we examine the effect of both within-location and between-location heterogeneity on a variety of structural properties. As we demonstrate, geographical variability produces large and distinctive features in the "social fabric" that overlies it; at the same time, however, many aggregate network properties can be fairly well-predicted from relatively simple spatial demographic variables. The impact of geographical variability is thus predicted to depend substantially on the type of network property being assessed, and on the spatial scale involved. (C) 2011 Published by Elsevier B.V.
WOS:000300131600008
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="122">
<title>Closure, connectivity and degree distributions: Exponential random graph (&lt;i&gt;p&lt;/i&gt;*) models for directed social networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2008.10.006</url>
<snippet>The new higher order specifications for exponential random graph models introduced by Snijders et al. [Snijders,T.A.B., Rattison, RE., Robins G.L., Handcock. M., 2006. New specifications for exponential random graph models. Sociological Methodology 36,99-153] exhibit substantial improvements in model fit compared with the commonly used Markov random graph models. Snijders et al., however, concentrated on non-directed graphs, with only limited extensions to directed graphs. In particular, they presented a transitive closure parameter based on path shortening. In this paper, we explain the theoretical and empirical advantages in generalizing to additional closure effects. We propose three new triadic-based parameters to represent different versions of triadic closure: cyclic effects; transitivity based on shared choices of partners; and transitivity based on shared popularity. We interpret the last two effects as forms of structural homophily, where ties emerge because nodes share a form of localized structural equivalence. We show that, for some datasets, the path shortening parameter is insufficient for practical modeling, whereas the structural homophily parameters can produce useful models with distinctive interpretations. We also introduce corresponding lower order effects for multiple two-path connectivity. We show by example that the in- and out-degree distributions may be better modeled when star-based parameters are supplemented with parameters for the number of isolated nodes, sources (nodes with zero in-degrees) and sinks (nodes with zero out-degrees). Inclusion of a Markov mixed star parameter may also help model the correlation between in- and out-degrees. We select some 50 graph features to be investigated in goodness of fit diagnostics, covering a variety of important network properties including density, reciprocity, geodesic distributions, degree distributions, and various forms of closure. As empirical illustrations, we develop models for two sets of organizational network data: a trust network within a training group, and a work difficulty network within a government instrumentality. (C) 2008 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000265325900001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="123">
<title>Predicting the trajectory of the evolving international cyber regime: Simulating the growth of a social network</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2015.01.002</url>
<snippet>This paper presents an agent-based model of regime growth. States and the relations comprising a regime are conceptualized as social networks. Regime growth is understood as the addition of ties between states as they agree to work with one another. These ties are added as a result of the interaction between state behavior and the structure of their relations. We apply the model to the emerging cyber security regime. Based on reasonable assumptions of the nature of the current international system, the model predicts a bi-polar structure pitting two distinct blocs led by the two states with the greatest capacity to conduct cyber conflict. However, if states either place increasing emphasis on the benefits of trade or if the more materially powerful seek greater cooperation among themselves, linkages will develop across the two blocs. (C) 2015 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000351979100007
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="124">
<title>Exponential random graph models for multilevel networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2013.01.004</url>
<snippet>Modern multilevel analysis, whereby outcomes of individuals within groups take into account group membership, has been accompanied by impressive theoretical development (e.g. Kozlowski and Klein, 2000) and sophisticated methodology (e.g. Snijders and Bosker, 2012). But typically the approach assumes that links between groups are non-existent, and interdependence among the individuals derives solely from common group membership. It is not plausible that such groups have no internal structure nor they have no links between each other. Networks provide a more complex representation of interdependence. Drawing on a small but crucial body of existing work, we present a general formulation of a multilevel network structure. We extend exponential random graph models (ERGMs) to multilevel networks, and investigate the properties of the proposed models using simulations which show that even very simple meso effects can create structure at one or both levels. We use an empirical example of a collaboration network about French cancer research elites and their affiliations (Lazega et al., 2006, 2008) to demonstrate that a full understanding of the network structure requires the cross-level parameters. We see these as the first steps in a full elaboration for general multilevel network analysis using ERGMs. 
WOS:000317943100009
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="125">
<title>Univariate and multivariate models of positive and negative networks: Liking, disliking, and bully-victim relationships</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2012.08.001</url>
<snippet>Three relations between elementary school children were investigated: networks of general dislike and bullying were related to networks of general like. These were modeled using multivariate cross-sectional (statistical) network models. Exponential random graph models for a sample of 18 classrooms, numbering 393 students, were summarized using meta-analyses. Results showed (balanced) network structures with positive ties between those who were structurally equivalent in the negative network. Moreover, essential structural parameters for the univariate network structure of positive (general like) and negative (general dislike and bullying) tie networks were identified. Different structures emerged in positive and negative networks. The results provide a starting point for further theoretical and (multiplex) empirical research about negative ties and their interplay with positive ties. 
WOS:000313304100027
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="126">
<title>Network dynamics of television use in school classes</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2011.08.002</url>
<snippet>Seventy years ago Paul Lazarsfeld and colleagues found empirical evidence for a significant influence of the social context on media effects by interpersonal communication. Subsequently various theories in mass media science incorporated the social context as an independent or dependent variable. However, there is little empirical research that addresses the dynamics of media use within a social context using network analytic methods. This study considers the social context as both an independent and dependent variable in a dynamic network process in order to disentangle social selection and influence processes. Hence, on one hand it tests whether the intensity of TV use and the use of specific TV genres predict the selection of conversation partners in social groups (social selection process). On the other hand it tests if individuals social context predicts their TV use (social influence process). Here, social context is defined as the conversation structure as well as the media use of all other persons in the social group. The research design includes a four wave panel survey on interpersonal communication networks and TV use of 707 students (age 13-16) in 29 Swiss school classes. The stochastic actor-based models tested with the program SIENA support the hypothesized selection processes. Conversation partners about TV programs are selected according to the similarity of their TV use. In contrast to this finding, the widely held assumption that individuals are influenced by their social network is not supported. Some inconclusive evidences suggest a possible social influence process on the level of TV intensity but not on the level of specific TV genres. Network-autocorrelation of conversation ties and TV use has therefore primarily be accredited to social selection processes and not social influence. Furthermore, the results show that avid viewers tend to talk more often about TV programs (ego effect), that avid viewers are more likely to be addressed (alter effect), and a general tendency to talk to persons with the same program preference (similarity effect). This challenges the classic idea of a two-step flow of communication in which intensive media users which are well informed would provide information to occasional users which are less conversant with a topic. (C) 2011 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000305495600006
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="127">
<title>Group based trajectories of network formation and dynamics</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2012.04.001</url>
<snippet>In this paper, we propose the application of a semi-parametric statistical methodology called Group-Based Developmental Trajectory Analysis to studying the dynamics of social networks. We begin with a discussion of theoretical problems in network analysis that may benefit from this approach. Next, we describe the methodology and how it can be applied to dyadic network data as well as aggregated node level data. We then demonstrate the methodology by analyzing the Newcomb Fraternity and the van de Bunt student data sets. Finally, we conclude with a discussion of potential directions for further research. (C) 2012 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000313304100014
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="128">
<title>Motivations for self-assembling into project teams</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2013.03.001</url>
<snippet>This study investigates the self-assembly mechanisms of ad hoc project teams using a bipartite network perspective. Individuals and projects are modeled as two types of nodes and team membership as relations between them. This approach enables us to investigate factors that impact voluntary team assembly at the individual, dyadic, and team levels simultaneously. Using Exponential Random Graph Models (ERGM/p*), we study players combat teams in a Massively Multiplayer Online Role-Playing Game (MMORPG) as a case of self-assembled project teams. Empirical results show that individuals are motivated to join ad hoc teams to complete difficult projects but not projects with long durations. We also found that individuals tend to collaborate with specific teammates who have complementary skills, those who have similar age or skill level, and those who are affiliated with the same organizational entity. (C) 2013 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000320479500010
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="129">
<title>Multilevel meta network analysis with application to studying network dynamics of network interventions</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2015.03.006</url>
<snippet>In this paper, I introduce new methods for multilevel meta network analysis. The new methods can combine results from multiple network models, assess the effects of predictors at network or higher levels and account for both within- and cross-network correlations of the parameters in the network models. To demonstrate the new methods, I studied network dynamics of a smoking prevention intervention that was implemented in 76 classes of six middle schools in China. The results show that as compared to random intervention (i.e., that targets random students), smokers popularity was significantly reduced in the classes with network interventions (i.e., those target central students or students with their friends together). The findings highlight the importance of examining network outcomes in evaluating social and health interventions, the role of social selection in managing social influence, and the potential of using network methods to design more effective interventions. (C) 2015 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000358626400005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="130">
<title>Social and geographic contexts of adolescent substance use: The moderating effects of age and gender</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2010.10.003</url>
<snippet>This study investigates whether age and gender moderate the effects of social network and neighborhood contexts on adolescent substance use using a spatially embedded, egocentric social network data set comprised of 254 urban adolescents. Results indicate that substance use is enhanced by being older and male, as well as the presence of neighborhood concentrated disadvantage and interaction with substance using peers at adolescents perceived risky places. Older adolescents are more strongly influenced by social and neighborhood contexts than younger adolescents, where ages 14-16 appear to be a key transition age for the emergence of contextual effects on substance use. (C) 2010 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000300131600013
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="131">
<title>Dynamics of adolescent friendship networks and smoking behavior</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2009.02.005</url>
<snippet>The mutual influence of smoking behavior and friendships in adolescence is studied. It is attempted to disentangle influence and selection processes in reciprocal and non-reciprocal friendships. An actor-based model is described for the co-evolution of friendship networks and smoking behavior. This model considers alternative selection and influence mechanisms, and models continuous-time changes in network and behavior. The data consists of a longitudinal sample of 1326 Finnish adolescents in 11 high schools. Findings suggest that selection as well as influence Processes play air important role in adolescent smoking behavior. Selection had a relatively stronger role than influence, in particular when selecting non-reciprocal friends. The strength of both influence and selection processes decreased over time. (C) 2009 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000274948700007
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="132">
<title>Relational event models for social learning in MOOCs</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2015.05.001</url>
<snippet>We propose three extensions for the relational event framework to model the co-evolution of multiple network event streams which are increasingly available thanks to the explosive growth of online applications. Firstly, a flexible stratification approach is considered to allow for more complex data structures with many types of nodes and events. Secondly, an inference method that combines nested case-control sampling with stratification is discussed to scale the approach to very large data sets. Finally, a suite of new temporal and network statistics is introduced to reflect the potentially complex dependencies among events and observed heterogeneities on nodes and edges. The empirical value of new extensions is demonstrated through an analysis of social learning in Massive Open Online Courses (MOOCs). In particular, three modeling problems are considered from the network perspective: (1) the utility of social factors, performance indicators, and clickstream behaviors in the prediction of course dropout, (2) the social and temporal structure of learner interactions across discussion threads, and (3) the forms of mutual dependence of social learning interactions on prior learning success, and future learning success on forms of prior social learning interaction. (C) 2015 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000358626400012
</snippet>
</document>

</searchresult>
