<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<searchresult>
<query>Global</query>
<document id="1">
<title>Exponential random graph model specifications for bipartite networks A dependence hierarchy</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2011.12.004</url>
<snippet>In this paper, we review the development of dependence structures for exponential random graph models for bipartite networks, and propose a hierarchy of dependence structures within which different dependence assumptions may be located. Based on this hierarchy, we propose a new set of model specifications by including bipartite graph configurations involving more than four nodes. We discuss the theoretical significance of the various effects that the extended models afford, and illustrate application of this hierarchy of models to several bipartite networks related to the political mobilization in Brazil in the early 1990s (Mische, 2007). (C) 2011 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000320479500007
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="2">
<title>Modelling a disease-relevant contact network of people who inject drugs</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2013.06.003</url>
<snippet>This study uses social network analysis to model a contact network of people who inject drugs (PWID) relevant for investigating the spread of an infectious disease (hepatitis C). Using snowball sample data, parameters for an exponential random graph model (ERGM) including social circuit dependence and four attributes (location, age, injecting frequency, gender) are estimated using a conditional estimation approach that respects the structure of snowball sample designs. Those network parameter estimates are then used to create a novel, model-dependent estimate of network size. Simulated PWID contact networks are created and compared with Bernoulli graphs. Location, age and injecting frequency are shown to be statistically significant attribute parameters in the ERGM. Simulated ERGM networks are shown to fit the collected data very well across a number of metrics. In comparison with Bernoulli graphs, simulated networks are shown to have longer paths and more clustering. Results from this study make possible simulation of realistic networks for investigating treatment and intervention strategies for reducing hepatitis C prevalence. (C) 2013 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000328713500016
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="3">
<title>"Trust Me": Differences in expressed and perceived trust relations in an organization</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2012.01.004</url>
<snippet>The possibility of resolving the tension between trust as a psychological condition and trust as a general organizing principle depends on assumptions about the convergence of expressed and perceived trust relations. In empirical organizational research these assumptions are frequently left implicit and only rarely modeled directly. Using data that we have collected on trust relations within the top management team of a multiunit industrial group we specify and estimate multivariate exponential random graph models (ERGMs) that reveal important differences in the structural logics underlying networks of expressed and perceived trust relations. Results confirm that trust induces awareness and produces expectations of reciprocity - features that are consistent with the view of trust as a general organizing principle. Results also show that networks of perceived trust relations are characterized by tendencies toward reciprocity and generalized giving of trust. When multivariate network effects are introduced, however, expressed trust relations no longer show a significant tendency toward reciprocation. Interpreted together these results suggest that: (i) the distribution of expressed and perceived trust relations differs; (ii) expressed trust relations in organizations are more hierarchical than are perceived trust relations, and (iii) expressed and perceived trust relations need to be modeled jointly. These findings suggest caution in the adoption and interpretation of trust only as a general organizing principle, and suggest that psychological mechanisms also play an important role in the making and breaking of trust relations within organizations. (C) 2012 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000313304100005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="4">
<title>Advances in exponential random graph (&lt;i&gt;p&lt;/i&gt;*) models</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2006.08.004</url>
<snippet>
WOS:000246430600001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="5">
<title>A statistical model for the analysis of mobility tables as weighted networks with an application to faculty hiring networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.08.003</url>
<snippet>Mobility of individuals between a wide variety of geographic locations, social positions, or roles is frequently analysed in the social sciences. In recent research, mobility has increasingly been conceptualised as a network. For example, residential mobility, when individuals move between neighbourhoods of a city, can be understood as a network in which neighbourhoods are nodes that are tied by counts of mobile individuals that move from one neighbourhood to another. Understanding mobility as a network allows to apply concepts and methods from the network analysts toolbox. However, the statistical modelling of such weighted networks in which ties can have individual attributes remains difficult. In this article we propose a statistical model for the analysis of mobility tables conceptualised as networks, combining properties from log-linear models and exponential random graph models (ERGMs). When no endogenous patterns are modelled, it reduces to a classic log-linear model for mobility tables. When modelling endogenous patterns but ignoring individual attributes, the model can be understood as an ERGM for weighted networks in which tie weights denote counts. Making use of special constraints of mobility networks, the model offers a parsimonious way to deal with weighted ties. Going beyond classical ERG modelling, the proposed approach can additionally incorporate tie characteristics that represent individual attributes of mobile people. The model is applied to two cases of faculty hiring networks-linking current departments of faculty members with their PhD granting institution-in history and computer science in the US.
WOS:000702773800003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="6">
<title>Data collection for social network research</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.08.010</url>
<snippet>
WOS:000777556900001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="7">
<title>Limits to inferring status from friendship relations</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2019.05.007</url>
<snippet>Informal status in communities is a relational phenomenon, it is attributed by others, and can be analysed using social network measures. However, many studies measure a single network relation - friendship - and interpret it related to status hierarchies: the number of friends is assumed to indicate status and asymmetric friendships are assumed to indicate status difference. While this practice is grounded in theoretical models of group structure, its assumptions have not been tested thoroughly and contradict research from various fields. We assess the validity of the approach using multiplex network data with three measures of status attribution from 17,469 high-school students in 5 European countries. We find that (i) asymmetric and symmetric friendships rarely overlap with status attributions, (ii) asymmetric friends are closer in status than expected by chance, and (iii) friendship and status attribution indegrees are only moderately correlated. These findings show that friendship relations cannot substitute for direct measurements of status in the study of informal hierarchies.
WOS:000487171000008
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="8">
<title>Exponential random graph (p*) models for affiliation networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2008.08.002</url>
<snippet>Recent advances in Exponential Random Graph Models (ERGMs), or p* models, include new specifications that give a much better chance of model convergence for large networks compared with the traditional Markov models. Simulation based MCMC maximum likelihood estimation techniques have been developed to replace the pseudolikelihood method. To date most work on ERGMs has focused on one-mode networks, with little done in the case of affiliation networks with two or more types of nodes. This paper proposes ERGMs for two-mode affiliation networks drawing on the recent advances for one-mode networks, including new two-mode specifications. We investigate features of the models by simulation, and compared the goodness of fit results obtained using the maximum likelihood and pseudolikelihood approaches. We introduce a new approach to goodness of fit for network models, using a heuristic based on Mahalanobis distance. The classic Southern Women data and Australian Interlocking Director data are used as examples to show that the ERGM with the newly specified statistics is a powerful tool for statistical analysis of affiliation networks. 
WOS:000262547600002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="9">
<title>Recent developments in exponential random graph (&lt;i&gt;p&lt;/i&gt;*) models for social networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2006.08.003</url>
<snippet>This article reviews new specifications for exponential random graph models proposed by Snijders et al. [Snijders, T.A.B., Pattison, P., Robins, G.L., Handcock, M., 2006. New specifications for exponential random graph models. Sociological Methodology] and demonstrates their improvement over homogeneous Markov random graph models in fitting empirical network data. Not only do the new specifications show improvements in goodness of fit for various data sets, but they also help to avoid the problem of near-degeneracy that often afflicts the fitting of Markov random graph models in practice, particularly to network data exhibiting high levels of transitivity. The inclusion of a new higher order transitivity statistic allows estimation of parameters of exponential graph models for many (but not all) cases where it is impossible to estimate parameters of homogeneous Markov graph models. The new specifications were used to model a large number of classical small-scale network data sets and showed a dramatically better performance than Markov graph models. We also review three current programs for obtaining maximum likelihood estimates of model parameters and we compare these Monte Carlo maximum likelihood estimates with less accurate pseudo-likelihood estimates. Finally, we discuss whether homogeneous Markov random graph models may be superseded by the new specifications, and how additional elaborations may further improve model performance. 
WOS:000246430600003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="10">
<title>The Swiss StudentLife Study: Investigating the emergence of an undergraduate community through dynamic, multidimensional social network data (Reprinted from vol 65, pages 71-84, 2021)</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.01.012</url>
<snippet>The Swiss StudentLife Study (SSL Study) is a longitudinal social network data collection conducted in three undergraduate student cohorts (N-1 = 226, N-2 = 261, N-3 = 660) in 2016-2019. The main goal of the study was to understand the emergence of informal student communities and their effects on different individual outcomes, such as well-being, motivation, and academic success. To this end, multiple dimensions of social ties were assessed, combining computer-based surveys, social sensors, social media data, and field experiments. The dy-namics of these social networks were measured on various time scales. In this paper, we present the design and data collection strategy of the SSL Study. We discuss practical challenges and solutions related to the data collection in four areas that were key to the success of our project: study design, research ethics, communication, and population definition.
WOS:000777028500003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="11">
<title>Reciprocity, transitivity, and the mysterious three-cycle</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2014.10.005</url>
<snippet>Reciprocity and transitivity are the two most important structural mechanisms underlying friendship network evolution. While on their own they are understood in great detail, the relation between them is rarely studied systematically. Are friendships outside of social groups more or less likely to be reciprocated than friendships embedded in a group? Using a theoretical framework that focusses on the situations in which friends interact and the social structures that stabilise one-sided friendships, I propose that the tendency towards reciprocation of friendships within transitive groups is usually lower than outside of transitive groups. In a meta-analysis of two datasets including 29 friendship networks using stochastic actor-oriented models (SAOMs), the interaction between reciprocity and transitivity is analysed. Supporting the theoretical reasoning, the interaction is consistently negative. Second, the tendency against forming three-cycles in friendship networks, which was consistently found in previous studies, is shown to be spurious and a result of neglecting to control for the tendency against reciprocation in transitive groups. The tendency against three-cycles is commonly seen as an indicator that unreciprocated friendships indicate local hierarchy differences between individuals; this proposition has to be re-evaluated in light of the findings of this study. Future studies that analyse the evolution of friendship networks should consider modelling reciprocation in transitive triplets and potentially omit modelling three-cycles. 
WOS:000347585500016
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="12">
<title>Embeddedness as a multilevel problem: A case study in economic sociology</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2015.03.005</url>
<snippet>Economic sociology has established the interdependencies between economic and social structures using the notion of embeddedness of the former in the latter. However research usually studies inter-organizational commercial networks and inter-individual informal networks separately. In this article we use a multilevel framework to analyze jointly economic networks between firms and informal networks between their members in order to reframe this embeddedness hypothesis. Based on a network study of a trade fair for television programmes in Eastern Europe we show that while each level has its own specific processes they are partly nested. Beyond this result, we observe that these levels of agency emerge in different contexts and in different temporalities. To conclude, we show that in order to understand performance on a market one needs to look at this dual positioning of individuals and organizations. (C) 2015 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000367423900029
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="13">
<title>Perceived friendship network of socially anxious adolescent girls</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.08.011</url>
<snippet>In this study we investigated how social anxiety and expressed friendship relate to the perceived friendship network of adolescent girls. We define an expressed friendship as a friendship choice made by an individual, and a perceived friend as one whom the individual perceives as choosing them as a friend; expressed and perceived friends need not be the same. We applied Exponential Random Graph Models (ERGMs) to understand effects of social anxiety and expressed friendship on structural patterns of the perceived friendship network, aiming to shed light how social anxiety and expressed friendship choices relate to cognitive perceptions of the social environment (in terms of perceived friendship partners). Participants were 94 year-nine students recruited from an all female high school in Melbourne, Australia. Results indicated that socially anxious students were similar to other students in terms of their number of perceived friends but were themselves less popular in the perceived friendship network. High anxiety students perceive friendship from low anxiety alters. Expressed and perceived friendship ties tended to be congruent so that students expressed friendship to partners who they perceived would nominate them as friends. Furthermore, students tended to be accurate in understanding their social environment in that perceived friends did tend to nominate them. Socially anxious students did not differ markedly from other students in terms of congruence and accuracy, although congruence was less likely in in ties from high anxiety to low anxiety students. The results indicate the ways in which social anxiety influences how students perceive their friendship relations.
WOS:000702773800008
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="14">
<title>Avoiding GIGO: Learnings from data collection in innovation research</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.04.005</url>
<snippet>This paper follows a research project meant to focus on understanding how universities and public research organisations (PRO) collaborate with firms in order to innovate and develop products or services using the same technology, an invention called Controlled Radical Polymerisation (CRP). We say meant to quite deliberately as this project was plagued with a range of data collection issues. We aim to give the reader a sense of the com-plications our research team faced as we share and highlight the issues we did not properly consider in the process of collecting our data, and the strategies we implemented to save the project and collect useful data. These issues included the benefits of the choice of a face-to-face methodology, using our own networks to recruit participants, the underestimated influence of secrecy when collaborating with industry on an innovation project, the value of having a "local champion" and having specific procedures in place for operational matters; but most of all the importance of being flexible and agile.We share the lessons we learned during this journey. Importantly, we seek to give some practical advice and a sense of the reality of data collection - a reality which is often smoothed over and written up as unproblematic in academic publications.
WOS:000777556900002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="15">
<title>Bullying and victimization among majority and minority students: The role of peers' ethnic perceptions</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2018.08.006</url>
<snippet>In this study, we investigate the associations between self-reported and victim-reported bullying and two dimensions of ethnicity (self-identification and ethnic perceptions) among non-Roma majority and Roma minority Hungarian secondary school students. Results of the meta-analysis of exponential random graph models for 12 classes (347 students, 4 schools) show that both self-declared Roma and non-Roma students are more likely to report that they bully peers they perceive as Roma compared to peers they perceive as non-Roma. This is after controlling for gender, socio-economic status, and structural characteristics of the bullying networks. Similar associations have not been found, however, analysing victims reports.
WOS:000501619700005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="16">
<title>The dual network structure of organizational problem solving: A case study on open source software development</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2012.12.003</url>
<snippet>We reconstruct the dual network structure generated by the association between 72 contributors and 737 software bugs engaged during a full development cycle of the free/open source software project Epiphany. Estimates of structural parameters of Exponential Random Graph Models for two-mode networks reveal the structural logics shaping activities of collaborative problem solving. After controlling for contributor-specific and software bug-specific characteristics, we find that contributors ("problem solvers") tend to distribute their activity over multiple software bugs. At the same time, however, we find that software bugs ("problems") tend not to share multiple contributors. This dual tendency toward de-specialization and exclusivity is sustained by specific local network dependencies revealed by our analysis which also suggests possible organizational mechanisms that may be underlying the puzzling macro-structural regularities frequently observed, but rarely explained, in the production of open source software. By combining these mechanisms with the influence of contributors characterized by different levels of involvement in the project, we provide micro-level evidence of structural interdependence between "core" and "peripheral" members identified exclusively on the basis of their individual level of contribution to the project. (C) 2013 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000320479500009
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="17">
<title>A model for the multiplex dynamics of two-mode and one-mode networks, with an application to employment preference, friendship, and advice</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2012.05.005</url>
<snippet>We propose a new stochastic actor-oriented model for the co-evolution of two-mode and one-mode networks. The model posits that activities of a set of actors, represented in the two-mode network, co-evolve with exchanges and interactions between the actors, as represented in the one-mode network. The model assumes that the actors, not the activities, have agency. The empirical value of the model is demonstrated by examining how employment preferences co-evolve with friendship and advice relations in a group of seventy-five MBA students. The analysis shows that activity in the two-mode network, as expressed by number of employment preferences, is related to activity in the friendship network, as expressed by outdegrees. Further, advice ties between students lead to agreement with respect to employment preferences. In addition, considering the multiplexity of advice and friendship ties yields a better understanding of the dynamics of the advice relation: tendencies to reciprocation and homophily in advice relations are mediated to an important extent by friendship relations. The discussion pays attention to the implications of this study in the broader context of current efforts to model the co-evolutionary dynamics of social networks and individual behavior. (C) 2012 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000320479500011
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="18">
<title>Closure, connectivity and degree distributions: Exponential random graph (&lt;i&gt;p&lt;/i&gt;*) models for directed social networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2008.10.006</url>
<snippet>The new higher order specifications for exponential random graph models introduced by Snijders et al. [Snijders,T.A.B., Rattison, RE., Robins G.L., Handcock. M., 2006. New specifications for exponential random graph models. Sociological Methodology 36,99-153] exhibit substantial improvements in model fit compared with the commonly used Markov random graph models. Snijders et al., however, concentrated on non-directed graphs, with only limited extensions to directed graphs. In particular, they presented a transitive closure parameter based on path shortening. In this paper, we explain the theoretical and empirical advantages in generalizing to additional closure effects. We propose three new triadic-based parameters to represent different versions of triadic closure: cyclic effects; transitivity based on shared choices of partners; and transitivity based on shared popularity. We interpret the last two effects as forms of structural homophily, where ties emerge because nodes share a form of localized structural equivalence. We show that, for some datasets, the path shortening parameter is insufficient for practical modeling, whereas the structural homophily parameters can produce useful models with distinctive interpretations. We also introduce corresponding lower order effects for multiple two-path connectivity. We show by example that the in- and out-degree distributions may be better modeled when star-based parameters are supplemented with parameters for the number of isolated nodes, sources (nodes with zero in-degrees) and sinks (nodes with zero out-degrees). Inclusion of a Markov mixed star parameter may also help model the correlation between in- and out-degrees. We select some 50 graph features to be investigated in goodness of fit diagnostics, covering a variety of important network properties including density, reciprocity, geodesic distributions, degree distributions, and various forms of closure. As empirical illustrations, we develop models for two sets of organizational network data: a trust network within a training group, and a work difficulty network within a government instrumentality. (C) 2008 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000265325900001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="19">
<title>Exponential random graph models for multilevel networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2013.01.004</url>
<snippet>Modern multilevel analysis, whereby outcomes of individuals within groups take into account group membership, has been accompanied by impressive theoretical development (e.g. Kozlowski and Klein, 2000) and sophisticated methodology (e.g. Snijders and Bosker, 2012). But typically the approach assumes that links between groups are non-existent, and interdependence among the individuals derives solely from common group membership. It is not plausible that such groups have no internal structure nor they have no links between each other. Networks provide a more complex representation of interdependence. Drawing on a small but crucial body of existing work, we present a general formulation of a multilevel network structure. We extend exponential random graph models (ERGMs) to multilevel networks, and investigate the properties of the proposed models using simulations which show that even very simple meso effects can create structure at one or both levels. We use an empirical example of a collaboration network about French cancer research elites and their affiliations (Lazega et al., 2006, 2008) to demonstrate that a full understanding of the network structure requires the cross-level parameters. We see these as the first steps in a full elaboration for general multilevel network analysis using ERGMs. 
WOS:000317943100009
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="20">
<title>The Swiss StudentLife Study: Investigating the emergence of an undergraduate community through dynamic, multidimensional social network data</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.11.006</url>
<snippet>The Swiss StudentLife Study (SSL Study) is a longitudinal social network data collection conducted in three undergraduate student cohorts (N-1 = 226, N-2 = 261, N-3 = 660) in 2016-2019. The main goal of the study was to understand the emergence of informal student communities and their effects on different individual outcomes, such as well-being, motivation, and academic success. To this end, multiple dimensions of social ties were assessed, combining computer-based surveys, social sensors, social media data, and field experiments. The dynamics of these social networks were measured on various time scales. In this paper, we present the design and data collection strategy of the SSL Study. We discuss practical challenges and solutions related to the data collection in four areas that were key to the success of our project: study design, research ethics, communication, and population definition.
WOS:000614282000007
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="21">
<title>Introduction to multilevel social networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2015.10.006</url>
<snippet>
WOS:000367423900024
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="22">
<title>Assimilation and differentiation: A multilevel perspective on organizational and network change</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2015.04.010</url>
<snippet>This paper builds on recently derived stochastic actor-oriented models (SAOMs) for the coevolution of one-mode and two-mode networks, and extends them to the analysis of how concurrent multilevel processes of (internal) organizational and (external) network change affect one another over time. New effects are presented that afford specification and identification of two apparently conflicting microrelational mechanisms that jointly affect decisions to modify the portfolio of internal organizational activities. The first mechanism, assimilation, makes network partners more similar by facilitating the replication and diffusion of experience. The second mechanism, functional differentiation, operates to maintain and amplify differences between network partners by preventing or limiting internal organizational change. We illustrate the empirical value of the model in the context of data that we have collected on a regional community of hospital organizations connected by collaborative patient transfer relations observed over a period of seven years. We find that processes of social influence conveyed by network ties may lead both to similarity and differences among connected organizations. We discuss the implications of the results in the context of current research on interorganizational networks. (C) 2015 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000367423900032
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="23">
<title>Snowball sampling for estimating exponential random graph models for large networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2015.11.003</url>
<snippet>The exponential random graph model (ERGM) is a well-established statistical approach to modelling social network data. However, Monte Carlo estimation of ERGM parameters is a computationally intensive procedure that imposes severe limits on the size of full networks that can be fitted. We demonstrate the use of snowball sampling and conditional estimation to estimate ERGM parameters for large networks, with the specific goal of studying the validity of inference about the presence of such effects as network closure and attribute homophily. We estimate parameters for snowball samples from the network in parallel, and combine the estimates with a meta-analysis procedure. We assess the accuracy of this method by applying it to simulated networks with known parameters, and also demonstrate its application to networks that are too large (over 40000 nodes) to estimate social circuit and other more advanced ERGM specifications directly. We conclude that this approach offers reliable inference for closure and homophily. (C) 2015 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000382592500016
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="24">
<title>Short- and long-term stability in organizational networks: Temporal structures of project teams</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2013.07.001</url>
<snippet>Network research focuses on patterns of stable relationships, where stability represents the unfolding of social processes over long time frames. We argue that social interactions exhibit important regularities in different time frames (short and long term), reflecting distinct social processes. We illustrate the value of this distinction through a comparative case study of technology-mediated communication, within two project teams in a digital marketing agency. We examine how the embedding of interpersonal interactions in processes of reciprocity and closure over different time horizons enables the emergence of cohesion in the face of constant compositional changes. We propose that the time frames in which stable patterns of interactions develop are the key to understanding the nature of the underlying social processes with short-term patterns of closure and reciprocity representing adaptation to change while longer term patterns indicate cohesion. Our results are supportive of this argument and show that the two teams exhibit the same regularities in interactions but across different time horizons. We discuss the implication of our findings and argue that distinguishing between short- and long-term stability of social networks offers a novel and promising avenue for network research. (C) 2013 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000328713500003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="25">
<title>Understanding the self-organization of occupational sex segregation with mobility networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.12.004</url>
<snippet>Decades after the beginning of the gender revolution, most women and men still work in sex-typed occupations. This is a primary driver of the gender wage gap. Most research describing the patterns of occupational sex segregation focuses on supposedly innate job characteristics that match gender stereotypical abilities and preferences, such as the use of mathematical skills or social skills, on income and status differences between occupations, and on organizational job characteristics, for example, the need to work long hours. However, beyond such occupational attributes, sex segregation is hypothesized to exhibit emergent patterns that are linked to the interdependent job mobility of women and men, in particular, men selectively leaving feminizing occupations. Developing new tools inspired by statistical network research, and using representative, longitudinal data that contain detailed occupational mobility from the UK between 2000 and 2008, this replacement mechanism is analyzed. It is shown that 19-28&#37; of observed sex segregation is linked to this emergent phenomenon in a statistical model that disentangles the various predictors of the allocation of women and men to different occupations. This makes it the most important predictor of segregation in contrast to concurrently modelled explanations based on occupational characteristics. Data and materials availability: The BHPS data and the LFS data are available from the UK Data Service (https:// www.ukdataservice.ac.uk/). The O*NET data is available from the O*NET homepage (https://www.onetcenter. org/). Software implemented in the environment R and code for data analysis are available upon request from the authors.
WOS:000914895700001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="26">
<title>The embeddedness of organizational performance: Multiple Membership Multiple Classification Models for the analysis of multilevel networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2015.06.005</url>
<snippet>We present a Multiple Membership Multiple Classification (MMMC) model for analysing variation in the performance of organizational sub-units embedded in a multilevel network. The model postulates that the performance of organizational sub-units varies across network levels defined in terms of: (i) direct relations between organizational sub-units; (ii) relations between organizations containing the sub-units, and (iii) cross-level relations between sub-units and organizations. We demonstrate the empirical merits of the model in an analysis of inter-hospital patient mobility within a regional community of health care organizations. In the empirical case study we develop, organizational sub-units are departments of emergency medicine (EDs) located within hospitals (organizations). Networks within and across levels are delineated in terms of patient transfer relations between EDs (lower-level, emergency transfers), hospitals (higher-level, elective transfers), and between EDs and hospitals (cross-level, non-emergency transfers). Our main analytical objective is to examine the association of these interdependent and partially nested levels of action with variation in waiting time among EDs - one of the most commonly adopted and accepted measures of ED performance. We find evidence that variation in ED waiting time is associated with various components of the multilevel network in which the EDs are embedded. Before allowing for various characteristics of EDs and the hospitals in which they are located, we find, for the null models, that most of the network variation is at the hospital level. After adding these characteristics to the model, we find that hospital capacity and ED uncertainty are significantly associated with ED waiting time. We also find that the overall variation in ED waiting time is reduced to less than a half of its estimated value from the null models, and that a greater share of the residual network variation for these models is at the ED level and cross level, rather than the hospital level. This suggests that the covariates explain some of the network variation, and shift the relative share of residual variation away from hospital networks. We discuss further extensions to the model for more general analyses of multilevel network dependencies in variables of interest for the lower level nodes of these social structures. (C) 2015 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000367423900025
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="27">
<title>An introduction to exponential random graph (&lt;i&gt;p*&lt;/i&gt;) models for social networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2006.08.002</url>
<snippet>This article provides an introductory summary to the formulation and application of exponential random graph models for social networks. The possible ties among nodes of a network are regarded as random variables, and assumptions about dependencies among these random tie variables determine the general form of the exponential random graph model for the network. Examples of different dependence assumptions and their associated models are given, including Bernoulli, dyad-independent and Markov random graph models. The incorporation of actor attributes in social selection models is also reviewed. Newer, more complex dependence assumptions are briefly outlined. Estimation procedures are discussed, including new methods for Monte Carlo maximum likelihood estimation. We foreshadow the discussion taken up in other papers in this special edition: that the homogeneous Markov random graph models of Frank and Strauss [Frank, O., Strauss, D., 1986. Markov graphs. Journal of the American Statistical Association 81, 832-842] are not appropriate for many observed networks, whereas the new model specifications of Snijders et al. [Snijders, T.A.B., Pattison, P., Robins, G.L., Handock, M. New specifications for exponential random graph models. Sociological Methodology, in press] offer substantial improvement. 
WOS:000246430600002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="28">
<title>Bayesian analysis for partially observed network data, missing ties, attributes and actors</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2013.07.003</url>
<snippet>We consider partially observed network data as defined in Handcock and Gile (2010). More specifically we introduce an elaboration of the Bayesian data augmentation scheme of Koskinen et al. (2010) that uses the exchange algorithm (Caimo and Friel, 2011) for inference for the exponential random graph model (ERGM) where tie variables are partly observed. We illustrate the generating of posteriors and unobserved tie-variables with empirical network data where 74&#37; of the tie variables are unobserved under the assumption that some standard assumptions hold true. One of these assumptions is that covariates are fixed and completely observed. A likely scenario is that also covariates might only be partially observed and we propose a further extension of the data augmentation algorithm for missing attributes. We provide an illustrative example of parameter inference with nearly 30&#37; of dyads affected by missing attributes (e.g. homophily effects). The assumption that all actors are known is another assumption that is liable to be violated so that there are "covert actors". We briefly discuss various aspects of this problem with reference to the Sageman (2004) data set on suspected terrorists. We conclude by identifying some areas in need of further research. (C) 2013 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000328713500002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="29">
<title>Social selection models for multilevel networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2014.12.003</url>
<snippet>Social selection models (SSMs) incorporate nodal attributes as explanatory covariates for modelling network ties (Robins et al., 2001). The underlying assumption is that the social processes represented by the graph configurations without attributes are not homogenous, and the network heterogeneity maybe captured by nodal level exogenous covariates. In this article, we propose SSMs for multilevel networks as extensions to exponential random graph models (ERGMs) for multilevel networks (Wang et al., 2013). We categorize the proposed model configurations by their similarities in interpretations arising from complex dependencies among ties within and across levels as well as the different types of nodal attributes. The features of the proposed models are illustrated using a network data set collected among French elite cancer researchers and their affiliated laboratories with attribute information about both researchers and laboratories (Lazega et al., 2006, 2008). Comparisons between the models with and without nodal attributes highlight the importance of attribute effects across levels, where the attributes of nodes at one level affect the network structure at the other level. (C) 2015 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000367423900031
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="30">
<title>Inter-ethnic friendship and negative ties in secondary school</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2015.03.004</url>
<snippet>This paper investigates several different aspects of inter-ethnic relationships. It focuses on friendships and negative ties between secondary school students from different ethnic backgrounds, introducing and measuring two different aspects of ethnicity: self-declared ethnicity, and ethnicity based on peer perception. These are first applied separately and then together on a sample of secondary school students in Hungary consisting of two ethnic groups: Roma and non-Roma Hungarian (N=420). Friendships and negative ties are modelled using cross-sectional exponential random graph models for sixteen classrooms separately, and then individual models are summarized using meta-analysis. Based on the social identity approach, we predict that inter-ethnic friendships are less likely, and negative ties are more likely, than those within ethnic groups; and that majority students reject their minority peers more than the other way around. Moreover, minority students are expected to exclude those whom they perceive as minorities, but who, at the same time, identify with the majority group, since these classmates might seem to them as "traitors" of their "original" ethnic group. Results mostly confirm our hypotheses, emphasizing the role of perceived ethnicity: majority students tend to dislike peers whom they perceive as minorities, regardless of these peers self-declared ethnicity; on the other hand, minority students are likely to send friendship nominations towards their perceived minority classmates if these also declare themselves as minorities, but, as predicted, negative nominations if these declare themselves as majorities. This supports our general idea that different ethnicity aspects might influence friendships and negative ties in different ways, and inconsistencies in someones ethnic categorization might play an important role in social rejection. (C) 2015 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000358626400006
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="31">
<title>Relational collaboration among spatial multipoint competitors</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2010.10.005</url>
<snippet>The presence of network ties between multipoint competitors is frequently assumed but rarely examined directly. The outcomes of multipoint competition, therefore, are better understood than their underlying relational mechanisms. Using original fieldwork and data that we have collected on an interorganizational network of patient transfer relations within a regional community of hospitals, we report and interpret estimates of Exponential Random Graph Models (ERGM) that specify the probability of observing network ties between organizations as a function of the degree of their spatial multipoint contact. We find that hospitals competing more intensely for patients across multiple geographical segments of their market (spatial multipoint competitors) are significantly more likely to collaborate. This conclusion is robust to alternative explanations for the formation of network ties based on organizational size differences, resource complementarities, performance differentials, and capacity constraints. We show that interorganizational networks between spatial multipoint competitors are characterized by clear tendencies toward clustering and a global core-periphery structure arising as consequences of multiple mechanisms of triadic closure operating simultaneously. We conclude that the effects of competition on the structure of interorganizational fields depends on how markets as physical and social settings are connected by cross-cutting network ties between competitors. (C) 2010 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000300131600009
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="32">
<title>Effects of competition on collective learning in advice networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2016.04.001</url>
<snippet>This paper looks at the effect of identifying alters as direct competitors on their selection as advisors. We differentiate between two kinds of competition: cut-throat vs friendly. We argue that, unlike cut-throat competition, friendly competition makes collective learning possible as a social process: when knowledge is built in interactions that are able to mitigate the negative effects of status competition and take place in homophilous social niches; and when the quality of this knowledge is guaranteed by members with epistemic status in these niches. Social niches and status facilitate advice seeking and collective learning because advice seeking between direct competitors is not obvious even when members have a common interest in sharing advice - a learning-related dilemma of collective action. We apply this reasoning to a network dataset combining identification of direct competitors and selection of advisors among the elite of cancer researchers in France. We use a procedure of multiplex stochastic block-modeling designed by Barbillon et al. (2015) to measure the effect of these identifications of direct competitors on the structure of the advice network. Results obtained with this dataset support our theory. (C) 2016 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000382592500001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="33">
<title>Organizational learning across multi-level networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2015.03.003</url>
<snippet>This paper examines organizational learning through a multilevel network lens. We assess how interpersonal knowledge transfer is sustained by the organizational structure of interunit work-flow ties and by the level of specialism of the connected units. To do this, we apply Multilevel Exponential Random Graph Models on data collected in a multiunit government institution in Italy. Results indicate that our approach allows simplifying and better understanding of organizational learning. Units are more likely to retain knowledge transfer ties within their boundaries. Unit boundary-spanning tends to occur only when knowledge transfer ties are sustained by hierarchical interunit work-flow ties. (C) 2015 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000367423900027
</snippet>
</document>

</searchresult>
