<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<searchresult>
<query>Global</query>
<document id="1">
<title>What is(n't) a friend? Dimensions of the friendship concept among adolescents (Reprinted from vol 66, pages 161-170, 2021)</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.01.010</url>
<snippet>Much research in network analysis of adolescent friendships assumes that friendships represent liking and social interaction, friendships are directed, and friendships are equivalent to one another. This study investigates the meaning of friendship for eight diverse cohorts of sixth graders. Analysis of focus group and survey data suggests that these adolescents construe friendship as a multidimensional role relation composed primarily of relational norms, expectations for mutual behavior. Their friendship definitions may also include mutual liking and interaction, and other structural expectations such as reciprocity, homophily, and transitivity. Lastly, boys and girls weight these dimensions differently in defining friendship.
WOS:000777028500005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="2">
<title>Using &lt;i&gt;Trellis&lt;/i&gt; software to enhance high-quality large-scale network data collection in the field (Reprinted from vol 66, pages 171-184, 2021)</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.01.004</url>
<snippet>Trellis is a mobile platform created by the Human Nature Lab at the Yale Institute for Network Science to collect high-quality, location-aware, off-line/online, multi-lingual, multi-relational social network and behavior data in hard-to-reach communities. Respondents use Trellis to identify their social contacts by name and photograph, a procedure especially useful in low-literacy populations or in contexts where names may be similar or confusing. We use social network data collected from 1,969 adult respondents in two villages in Kenya to demonstrate Trellis ability to provide unprecedented metadata to monitor and report on the data collection process including artifactual variability based on surveyors, time of day, or location.
WOS:000777028500011
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="3">
<title>The role of sociopolitical workplace networks in involuntary employee turnover</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2023.10.005</url>
<snippet>While poor performance is one reason employees are fired, previous research suggests it plays a limited role in explaining terminations. We argue that sociopolitical concerns play a role in determining who is terminated. Using field data from a U.S. health care company and experimental data using participants with supervisory experience, we show how the supervisors political concerns with the focal employee, which are contingent on the supervisor-employee political relationship and the way it is embedded within the workplace network, are related to dismissal decisions. Not only do we expect that a supervisor will be less likely to terminate an employee they see as a political ally and more likely to dismiss an adversary, but we also argue that a supervisor with fewer (more) alternative allies to the employee is less (more) likely to dismiss the employee. Additionally, a supervisor with numerous adversaries in their own network depends more heavily on the employee politically, making dismissal less likely, whereas if the employee has numerous adversaries, the supervisor has greater latitude to terminate the employee. Our findings contribute to research on involuntary turnover by showing that a social network approach to understanding organizational politics helps us understand why specific individuals are targeted for dismissal, above and beyond performance considerations.
WOS:001112821400001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="4">
<title>Choosing isolation in the face of stigma: Relational work in tie severance among Korean unwed mothers</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2024.06.001</url>
<snippet>Though network scholars long have observed that people experience high rates of network turnover, theorization on how ties dissolve has lagged behind, with natural tie decay dominating as the primary explanation. Many deviants face stigma and become social pariahs from communities of origin, yet current network theories struggle to explain how such processes of network dissolution occur. Using interviews conducted with Korean unwed mothers, a highly stigmatized and hard -to -reach population, this study shows that shared culture in networks -norms, expectations, and meanings -plays a key role in how people navigate stigma in their networks. I demonstrate that tie severance requires work : relational work that matches network -specific culture. I propose a typology of tie severance processes along two dimensions, actor and motive, and identify associated relational work for each type. This study shows that macro -level cultural values are adapted to each network and (re) interpreted before relational work can be engaged to manage social relations.
WOS:001258187800001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="5">
<title>Positive and negative tie perceptual accuracy: Pollyanna principle vs. negative asymmetry explanations</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.07.008</url>
<snippet>We examine the affective content of ties and explore whether negative affective tie content is systematically advantaged or disadvantaged when recalling the social network as compared to positive affective tie content. We test this in three workgroups from two organizations and analyze differences in perceptual accuracy comparing negative and positive affective tie perception. We theorize that ego will be more accurate for others positive than negative ties due to generalized positivity bias, or the Pollyanna principle. We also theorize that ego will be more accurate for their own negative ties due to negative asymmetry perspective, as ego will attend more to those ties that pose a personal threat. Findings suggest that observers were more accurate overall about their own and others positive compared to negative affective ties. We conclude that the Pollyanna principle is an important factor in explaining perceptions in naturalistic cognitive networks. Supplementary analysis showed that negative ties were more likely to be missed and imagined and having a valenced tie toward another person influences perceptions of that persons network ties. Finally, we find that balanced and imbalanced triads were also important factors of relative accuracy. The studys contribution, limitations, and future research are also discussed.
WOS:000591504600008
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="6">
<title>The networks and success of female entrepreneurs in China</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2019.01.003</url>
<snippet>Despite population opinion in China favoring men over women, data on a large probability sample of Chinese entrepreneurs show that men and women on average build similar network structures, experience similar distributions of network advantage, achieve similar levels of business success, and experience similar performance returns to their network advantage. Digging into network content, male and female entrepreneurs have similarly close and trusting relations with similar kinds of contacts, with one exception, gender homophily: men are more likely than women to operate in a network composed entirely of men, while women operate more often than men in a network containing multiple female contacts. There is also gender pattern in the use of contacts, reflecting conservative attitudes in the broader society: Women are the object of more interaction on technical matters out of the public eye, while men are the preferred contact for representation (men and women more often cite male contacts for help in founding the business, dealing with suppliers, and dealing with customers). The gender pattern is more obvious in the business contacts of men than in the business contacts of women, and more linked with business success for men. In sum, there is gender pattern to the networks around male and female entrepreneurs, but the network theory of advantage from access to structural holes similarly predicts the success of male and female entrepreneurs regardless of gender.
WOS:000472813200004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="7">
<title>Network integration within a prison-based therapeutic community</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.07.007</url>
<snippet>Prison-based therapeutic communities (TCs) are a widespread, effective way to help incarcerated individuals address substance abuse problems. The TC philosophy is grounded in an explicitly relational paradigm that entails building community and conditioning residents to increasingly take responsibility for leadership therein. Although TCs are based on cultivating a network that continuously integrates new residents, many common structural features can jeopardize TC goals and are hence discouraged (e.g., clustering, homophily). In light of this tension, analyzing the TC from a network perspective can offer new insights to its functioning, as well as to broader questions surrounding how networks integrate new members. In this study we examine a mens TC unit in a Pennsylvania prison over a 10-month span. Using data on residents informal networks, we examine: (1) how well individuals integrate into the TC network across time, (2) what predicts how well residents integrate into the TC, and (3) how well the TC network structure adheres to theoretical ideals. Results suggest that individual integration is driven by a range of hypothesized factors and, with limited exceptions, the observed TC is able to foster a network structure and integrate residents consistent with TC principles. We discuss the implications of these results for evaluating TCs and for understanding the process of network integration.
WOS:000591504600002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="8">
<title>On the structural equivalence of coresidents and the measurement of village social structure</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.02.010</url>
<snippet>Researchers in the social and biomedical sciences regularly measure networks spanning entire villages in low and middle-income countries by documenting the social contacts of just one or two representatives from participating households. This "lean" approach to network measurement is cost-effective compared to a sociometric census of a villages adult population. However, it implicitly assumes that interviewed and non interviewed coresidents are structurally equivalent - i.e., directly connected to the same network members in the same fashion. Drawing from research on multilevel networks and intra-household heterogeneity, here I argue that this assumption is unlikely to hold for the personal social ties typically of interest to field researchers (i.e., friends and other preferred sources and targets of material, informational and emotional support). I substantiate my claim with an exploratory case study on the similarity of coresidents incoming and outgoing ties using data documenting unrestricted roster-based reports on the provision of tangible aid amongst all adult residents of a remote village of indigenous horticulturalists in Nicaragua (108 adults; 32 nuclear-family households). Results indicate that coresidents markedly deviate from structural equivalence and its generalisation in the form of stochastic equivalence (i.e., similar probabilities of being directly connected to the same network members in the same fashion). All in all, it is ill-advised to assume that the personal network of any one coresident, or, more generally, the manner in which a coresident tends to send and receive their personal ties, is representative of their household.
WOS:000777556900007
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="9">
<title>Privacy and confidentiality considerations for collecting HIV risk network data among men who have sex with men and implications for constructing valid risk networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2019.09.002</url>
<snippet>Studies aiming to construct risk networks have historically collected network members names, demographic characteristics and relational data (i.e., type, strength, duration, frequency of interaction, and HIV-related risk behaviors between the pair). Due to difficulties in constructing risk networks stemming from partner anonymity and the use of nicknames, some studies also collect network members screen names, phone numbers, physical attributes, and scars/tattoos to assist with entity resolution. In-depth interviews with 20 men who have sex with men and transgender women in Kentucky assessed privacy/confidentiality concerns as well as accuracy/recall issues associated with providing these details. Most preferred providing alters nicknames/first names only or a first name with the first letter of the last name. Many perceived screen names, phone numbers, and scars/tattoos to be too personal/identifying. Willingness to provide more detailed information varied by relationship type/ strength, which could influence the validity of the resulting network.
WOS:000685648800007
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="10">
<title>Imputation of attributes in networked data using Bayesian autocorrelation regression models</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.02.005</url>
<snippet>Misspecification in network autocorrelation models poses a challenge for parameter estimation, which is amplified by missing data. Model misspecification has been a focus of recent work in the statistics literature and new robust procedures have been developed, in particular cutting feedback. This paper shows how this helps in a misspecified network autocorrelation model. Where model misspecification is mild and the traits are fully observed, Bayesian imputation is routine. In settings with high missingness, Bayesian inference can fail, but a closely related cut model is robust. We illustrate this on a data set of graduate students using a Facebook-like messaging app.
WOS:000527272000003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="11">
<title>Limits to inferring status from friendship relations</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2019.05.007</url>
<snippet>Informal status in communities is a relational phenomenon, it is attributed by others, and can be analysed using social network measures. However, many studies measure a single network relation - friendship - and interpret it related to status hierarchies: the number of friends is assumed to indicate status and asymmetric friendships are assumed to indicate status difference. While this practice is grounded in theoretical models of group structure, its assumptions have not been tested thoroughly and contradict research from various fields. We assess the validity of the approach using multiplex network data with three measures of status attribution from 17,469 high-school students in 5 European countries. We find that (i) asymmetric and symmetric friendships rarely overlap with status attributions, (ii) asymmetric friends are closer in status than expected by chance, and (iii) friendship and status attribution indegrees are only moderately correlated. These findings show that friendship relations cannot substitute for direct measurements of status in the study of informal hierarchies.
WOS:000487171000008
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="12">
<title>An inductive typology of egocentric networks with data from the Socio-Economic Panel</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.07.005</url>
<snippet>In this article we apply Random Forests to data from the German Socio-Economic-Panel (SOEP), creating an inductive typology of egocentric networks. Using an earlier application of the machine learning algorithm as a guideline, we are putting the wider applicability of the method to the test by using data not exclusively constructed for network analysis and focusing on core networks of respondents. Applying Random Forests promises more differentiated compositional typologies than currently used. Overcoming the prevailing approach to typologies by creating a larger number of finer-grained types can improve network-oriented life course analysis. We started our analysis by selecting 44 descriptors of 8341 respondent networks and reduced this number by combining most of them to indices representing basic dimensions of egocentric networks. The descriptors are used in hierarchical clustering to derive clusters that are then predicted with Random Forests to evaluate the reliability of this approach. We can identify stable core differentiators underlying typology construction but are also confronted with variation in the resulting types. While some of this can be traced back to the distinct socio-demographics of the respective populations, some is the result of measurement disparities. Against the backdrop of the presented results, we discuss the relationship between a deductive approach of network sociology, dedicated to theory-testing and inductive typologies of egocentric networks within a framework of life course analysis.
WOS:000932028700005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="13">
<title>Some days are better than others: Examining time-specific variation in the structuring of interorganizational relations</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2018.10.001</url>
<snippet>The generative mechanisms controlling change in interorganizational relations are typically assumed to be time- independent, i.e., operate homogeneously and synchronously over time. In this paper we consider some of the implications of violating this assumption. We adopt and extend statistical models for relational events to reveal time-specific variations in mechanisms underlying interorganizational relations observed within a small community of health care organizations. We find that aggregate estimates of parameters associated with mechanisms of theoretical interest mask fine-grained temporal variation in relational events sequences. We discuss the implications of this result for studies of interorganizational relations - and social networks snore generally.
WOS:000458224300002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="14">
<title>Networks from culture: Mechanisms of tie-formation follow institutionalized rules in social fields</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.12.005</url>
<snippet>Tie-formation mechanisms like homophily, reciprocity, transitivity, and preferential attachment operate to varying degrees across contexts. Romantic ties tend to be homophilous by age, education, and ethnicity, and to remain dyadic. Scientific citations, in contrast, fall into highly unequal preferential attachment patterns. Triangulation is nearly absent in advice and patronage networks but features prominently in friendship ties. Building on relational sociology and field theory, we argue that such variation in patterns of connectivity derives from the meaning attached to relationships, which varies by context. Tie-formation logics are institutionalized rules-of-the-game and susceptible to change over time. Accordingly, the mechanisms of tie-formation behind empirical network patterns have to be connected to the cultural rules in particular fields.
WOS:001188848400001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="15">
<title>The Swiss StudentLife Study: Investigating the emergence of an undergraduate community through dynamic, multidimensional social network data (Reprinted from vol 65, pages 71-84, 2021)</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.01.012</url>
<snippet>The Swiss StudentLife Study (SSL Study) is a longitudinal social network data collection conducted in three undergraduate student cohorts (N-1 = 226, N-2 = 261, N-3 = 660) in 2016-2019. The main goal of the study was to understand the emergence of informal student communities and their effects on different individual outcomes, such as well-being, motivation, and academic success. To this end, multiple dimensions of social ties were assessed, combining computer-based surveys, social sensors, social media data, and field experiments. The dy-namics of these social networks were measured on various time scales. In this paper, we present the design and data collection strategy of the SSL Study. We discuss practical challenges and solutions related to the data collection in four areas that were key to the success of our project: study design, research ethics, communication, and population definition.
WOS:000777028500003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="16">
<title>Low status rejection: How status hierarchies influence negative tie formation</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2018.08.005</url>
<snippet>Scholarship investigating how social status patterns negative ties has yielded contradictory findings. Three likely sources for these differences are: different measures of social status, measures of negative ties (perceived versus dyadic), and structural factors. This study uses multiple measures of social status, sociometrically-measured negative ties, and multiple analytic approaches - MRQAP to control for structure and within-individual to control for heterogeneity - to help resolve this debate. We find: negative ties travel down status hierarchies and target low status individuals, and a negative tie between two people becomes more likely as their status difference increases. These results suggest a low-status rejection mechanism.
WOS:000454966400004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="17">
<title>Multilevel determinants of collaboration between organised criminal groups</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.04.002</url>
<snippet>Collaboration between members of different criminal groups is an important feature of crime that is considered organised, as it allows criminals to access resources and skills in order to exploit illicit economic opportunities. Collaboration across criminal groups is also difficult and risky due to the lack of institutions supporting peaceful cooperation in illicit markets. Thus cross-group collaboration has been thought to take place mostly among small and transient groups. This paper determines whether and under what conditions members of different, larger organised crime groups collaborate with one another. To do so we use intelligence data from the Canadian province of Alberta, centering on criminals and criminal groups engaged in multiple crime types in multiple geographic locations. We apply a multilevel network analytical framework and exponential random graph models using Bayesian techniques to uncover the determinants of cross-group criminal collaboration. We find cross-group collaboration depends not only on co-location, but also on the types of groups to which the criminals are affiliated, and on illicit market overlap between groups. When groups are operating in the same geographically-situated illicit markets their members tend not to collaborate with one another, providing evidence for the difficulty or undesirability of cross-group collaboration in illicit markets. Conversely, members of Outlaw Motorcycle Gangs are more likely to collaborate across groups when markets overlap, suggesting the superior capacity and motivation of biker gangs to coordinate criminal activity. Our paper contributes to the understanding of criminal networks as complex, emergent, and spatially embedded market phenomena.
WOS:000563919700006
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="18">
<title>Network brokerage and the perception of leadership</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.09.002</url>
<snippet>We renovate a classic experiment to define a research platform that provides data on network behavior and the causal effect of access to structural holes. Our hypothesis is that people are perceived to be leaders when they behave as network brokers, which is to say, when they coordinate information across structural holes. We focus on the perception of leadership to connect with the many field studies in which access to structural holes predicts success measures keyed to leadership. Our hypothesis is clearly supported. The broker-leader association we report is very similar in strength and form to broker-success associations reported in previous research. At the same time, it is also clear that people adapt to their randomly assigned network, re-shaping it to suit preferences that in some part emerge in team deliberations or outside the experiment. A modification to our hypothesis - at least for these small laboratory teams - is that monopoly brokerage is key to being cited as team leader. Leadership is ambiguous when multiple people are positioned to be brokers unless one person emerges by his or her network behavior as a monopoly broker. Our summary conclusion is that access to structural holes can be causal to the perception of leadership, a characteristic implicit in many success measures used to document the broker-success association.
WOS:000614282000004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="19">
<title>More than one's negative ties: The role of friends' antipathies in high school gossip</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.11.009</url>
<snippet>Gossip is universal, and multiple studies have demonstrated that it can have beneficial group-level outcomes when negative reports help identify defectors or norm-violators. Gossip, however, seldom happens in a social vacuum. Instead, it is enmeshed in a fabric of positive and negative relationships that creates opportunities, constraints, and also motives to gossip. This article studies the importance of friendships and antipathies among the three concerned parties (sender, receiver, target) for negative gossip among adolescents. We contrast two theoretical accounts. According to the first, gossip brings closer individuals who have "enemies" in common. Based on this, we infer that gossip appears in triads where both the sender and receiver share their antipathy against the target. The second position argues that gossip is used to compromise different opinions of friends towards the target. Thus, what predicts gossip is direct antipathy against the target or being friends with someone who dislikes the target (indirect antipathy) rather than the combination of the two antipathies. We test these two lines of reasoning with sociometric data from 17 classroom observations (13 unique classrooms in different time points) in Hungary. Bayesian Exponential Random Graph Models yield support for direct antipathy in 13 (nine unique) classrooms and indirect antipathy in five. No evidence for shared antipathy is found. Results suggest that, at least among adolescents, negative gossip is not about bonding with potential allies but more about consensus-making between friends. Also, results reveal that negative gossip concentrates on the two ends of the reputational echelon, hinting that, in the classroom, high reputation might be contested instead of rewarded.
WOS:000724026400003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="20">
<title>Perceived friendship network of socially anxious adolescent girls</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.08.011</url>
<snippet>In this study we investigated how social anxiety and expressed friendship relate to the perceived friendship network of adolescent girls. We define an expressed friendship as a friendship choice made by an individual, and a perceived friend as one whom the individual perceives as choosing them as a friend; expressed and perceived friends need not be the same. We applied Exponential Random Graph Models (ERGMs) to understand effects of social anxiety and expressed friendship on structural patterns of the perceived friendship network, aiming to shed light how social anxiety and expressed friendship choices relate to cognitive perceptions of the social environment (in terms of perceived friendship partners). Participants were 94 year-nine students recruited from an all female high school in Melbourne, Australia. Results indicated that socially anxious students were similar to other students in terms of their number of perceived friends but were themselves less popular in the perceived friendship network. High anxiety students perceive friendship from low anxiety alters. Expressed and perceived friendship ties tended to be congruent so that students expressed friendship to partners who they perceived would nominate them as friends. Furthermore, students tended to be accurate in understanding their social environment in that perceived friends did tend to nominate them. Socially anxious students did not differ markedly from other students in terms of congruence and accuracy, although congruence was less likely in in ties from high anxiety to low anxiety students. The results indicate the ways in which social anxiety influences how students perceive their friendship relations.
WOS:000702773800008
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="21">
<title>Using geographical data and rolling statistics for diagnostics of respondent-driven sampling</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.05.001</url>
<snippet>Respondent-driven sampling (RDS) is commonly used to sample from key populations without a sampling frame since traditional methods are unable to efficiently survey them. Surveying these populations is often desirable to inform service delivery, assess effectiveness of programs, and determine prevalence of diseases. However, there are concerns about how RDS works in practice due to its many assumptions. To assess some of these assumptions, we develop diagnostics using geographical data and demonstrate their utility by identifying lack of convergence and characterizing RDS reach in surveys conducted among female sex workers and men who have sex with men in Kampala, Uganda.
WOS:000777556900008
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="22">
<title>Streams of interactions: Social connectedness in daily life</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2024.03.001</url>
<snippet>This study contributes to the social connectedness literature by exploring the range of social interactions that people experience on a daily basis using time diary data. First, we investigate the different types of people whom individuals encounter in everyday life (i.e., family, friends, co-workers, acquaintances, others). Quantifying the degree of this social exposure provides insight into potential sources of support, information, comparison, and control. It further allows us to capture certain types of social connections that are commonly missed in traditional social network questionnaires. Second, we examine how social context fosters interactions between different types of people. Upon analyzing data from the American Time Use Survey, we find that a majority of respondents (69&#37;) engaged in at least one interaction with a non-household member in a 24-hour period. We also found that interactions with different types of people varied according to social context. Interactions with friends, acquaintances, and "others" were significantly more likely to occur in public contexts rather than private or professional contexts. Collectively, our findings highlight the prevalence of social exposure among the American population as well as the important role of social context in making these interactions possible.
WOS:001208404700001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="23">
<title>Balancing bias and burden in personal network studies</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.10.007</url>
<snippet>Personal network data is increasingly used to answer research questions about the interplay between individuals (i.e., egos) and their social environment (i.e., alters). Researchers designing such data collections face a trade-off: When eliciting a high number of alters, study participation can be particularly burdensome as all data is obtained by surveying the ego. Eliciting a low number of alters, however, may incur bias in network characteristics. In the present study we use a sample of 701 Dutch women and their personal networks of 25 alters to investigate two strategies reducing respondent burden in personal network data collections: (1) eliciting fewer alters and (2) selecting a random subsample from the original set of elicited alters for full assessment. We present the amount of bias in structural and compositional network characteristics connected to applying these strategies for every possible network size (2-24 alters) as well as the potential study time savings as a proxy for respondent burden reduction. Our results can aid researchers designing a personal network study to balance respondent burden and bias in estimates for a range of compositional and structural network characteristics.
WOS:000722628400002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="24">
<title>Social network and family business: Uncovering hybrid family firms</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.12.005</url>
<snippet>What does it mean for a private enterprise in China to be embedded in a family? Our purpose here is twofold: (1) use social network analysis to describe what it means for a firm to be embedded in a family, (2) reveal from the application a new kind of firm, not family, yet akin to family. Armed with data on a large probability sample of private enterprises - a third of which meet ownership and employment criteria of being family businesses - we uncover a category of "hybrid family firms" that look modern in the style of firms that exclude family, but operate socially in ways similar to family firms. Our conclusion from summary statistics on the sample is that there are no differences in average performance level or network advantage for the three categories of businesses: family firms, hybrid family firms, and family-excluded firms. The fact that CEOs of family firms and hybrid family firms more often turn to family as key business contacts is a fact about network composition that raises no question about network mechanisms. Whether the CEO turns to more or fewer family contacts, government help is more likely with stronger political connections, and business success and survival are more likely with a large, open network. That said, the look-modern, act-traditional hybrid family firms stand alone in prospering with a CEO embedded in a closed business network. Recognition of hybrid family firms adds to the literatures illustrations of social network analysis used to distinguish types of businesses and business people, and extends the population of organizations within which governance and strategy are likely to be better understood when viewed through a family logic.
WOS:000614282000012
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="25">
<title>?Defriending? in a polarized age: Political and racial homophily and tie dissolution</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2023.01.006</url>
<snippet>Given increased political polarization and racial tension in the wake of the 2016 presidential election in the United States, this study examines dropped ties in personal networks at that time based on political and racial identities. We employed data from the 2015-2018 UCNets study (n = 1159), a longitudinal, representative data set of the San Francisco Bay Area. In late 2015 and early 2016 it generated personal network data via multiple name generators, eliciting alters whom respondents socialized with, confided in, received advice from, exchanged social support with, and found difficult. Using multilevel multinomial logit models, we then examined various reasons for tie dissolution immediately following the inauguration of Trump in early 2017. The results show that among young adults, politically dissimilar alters were more likely to be dropped due to disagreements. With respect to racial homophily, we found that interracial dyads were more likely to be dropped because of drifting apart or some other reason for both younger and older cohorts. Overall, there is some support for the notion that dropped ties due to political disagreements did occur immediately following the 2016 election, but the results highlight the continuing significance of race in personal networks.
WOS:000943785700001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="26">
<title>The political position generator-A new instrument for measuring political ties in China</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.05.004</url>
<snippet>This paper proposes a novel instrument - the political position generator - for measuring individuals political ties, or personal, affective connections to state officials and other political actors. It adopts and adapts the more general position generator framework in social capital research to capture three key dimensions of political ties upper reachability, network diversity, and tie strength. The measure is validated with data from a representative survey of the Chinese population and three scales representing the three political ties dimensions are created. In correlational and multivariate regression analyses, we find initial evidence of the instruments criterion-related (discriminant and concurrent) validity.
WOS:000563919700007
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="27">
<title>Neighborhood conditions and social network turnover among older adults</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2023.01.003</url>
<snippet>Increasing research highlights heterogeneity in patterns of social network change, with growing evidence that these patterns are shaped in part by social structure. The role of social and structural neighborhood conditions in the addition and loss of kin and non-kin network members, however, has not been fully considered. In this paper, we argue that the residential neighborhood context can either facilitate or prevent the turnover of core network relationships in later life - a period of the life course characterized by heightened reliance on network ties and vulnerability to neighborhood conditions. Using longitudinal data from the National Social Life, Health, and Aging Project linked with data from the American Community Survey, we find that higher levels of neighborhood concentrated disadvantage are associated with the loss of older adults kin and non-kin network members over time. Higher levels of perceived neighborhood social interaction, however, are associated with higher rates of adding non-kin network members and lower rates of adding kin network members over time. We suggest that neighborhood conditions, including older adults perceptions of neighborhood social life, represent an underexplored influence on kin and non-kin social network dynamics, which could have implications for access to social resources later in the life course.
WOS:000931603800001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="28">
<title>Similarity and differences in age, gender, ethnicity, and education as explanatory factors of tie loss in the core discussion network</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2023.09.003</url>
<snippet>Individuals are more likely to interact with people who are similar in terms of socio-demographics and values than dissimilar people, which is often explained by a focus on selection effects. Yet, tie loss of dissimilar ties might also cause network homogeneity. Unfortunately, within the literature, there is a relative dearth of knowledge on the relationship between (dis)similarity and tie loss. Hence, we address this gap by theorizing and testing the relation between (dis)similarity and tie loss in the core discussion network (CDN) of Dutch citizens, also considering how ties are embedded in the CDN.
WOS:001083100300001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="29">
<title>Fast clustering for signed graphs based on random walk gap</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2018.08.008</url>
<snippet>Signed graphs are often used as models for social media mining, social networks analysis and nature language processing. In this paper, we study clustering algorithms for signed graphs that can be scaled for use in large-scale signed networks. A proposed mechanism, called a random walk gap (RWG), is used to extract more cluster structure information. RWG uses two types of random walks on signed graphs. The first considers positive edges only. The second takes negative edges into account. Three types of edges in signed graphs are identified and their different characteristics in terms of transition probability changes are determined for the two types of random walk graphs. Different characteristics contain different information about cluster structure and a RWG matrix is used to reflect the differences. The RWG matrix is used to adjust the weights of edges in signed graphs. This is the first study to perform a random walk on negative edges. A fast clustering for signed graphs (FCSG) algorithm is then proposed. This FCSG is compared with existing methods. The computational times for different algorithms are measured. The experiments show that the proposed FCSG algorithm gives better results than existing algorithms based on the performance criteria of imbalance and modularity.
WOS:000501619700010
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="30">
<title>Not all friends are created equal: Friendship ties across different social contexts in South Korea</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2024.02.002</url>
<snippet>This study explores variation in composition and strength of close friendship ties across timing and contexts of tie formation. Analyzing South Korean survey data and comparing it with existing U.S. and Korean network data, we find both similarities and differences between friendship and non -kin discussion networks in the two countries. We show that schools are a crucial source of close friendships for Koreans, shaping homophily patterns. Additionally, we uncover substantial variations in tie strength across timings and contexts of tie formation. We discuss the implications of these findings, highlighting the role of social and cultural contexts in shaping personal networks.
WOS:001208596500001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="31">
<title>Network Ecology: Introduction to the Special Issue</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2023.12.001</url>
<snippet>
WOS:001188768500001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="32">
<title>Key aspects of covert networks data collection: Problems, challenges, and opportunities</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2019.10.002</url>
<snippet>Data quality is considered to be among the greatest challenges in research on covert networks. This study identifies six aspects of network data collection, namely nodes, ties, attributes, levels, dynamics, and context. Addressing these aspects presents challenges, but also opens theoretical and methodological opportunities. Furthermore, specific issues arise in this research context, stemming from the use of secondary data and the problem of missing data. While each of the issues and challenges has some specific solution in the literature on organized crime and social networks, the main argument of this paper is to try and follow a more systematic and general solution to deal with these issues. To this end, three potentially synergistic and combinable techniques for data collection are proposed for each stage of data collection - biographies for data extraction, graph databases for data storage, and checklists for data reporting. The paper concludes with discussing the use of statistical models to analyse covert networks and the cultivation of relations within the research community and between researchers and practitioners.
WOS:000777028500001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="33">
<title>Missing data in cross-sectional networks - An extensive comparison of missing data treatment methods</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.02.004</url>
<snippet>This paper compares several missing data treatment methods for missing network data on a diverse set of simulated networks under several missing data mechanisms. We focus the comparison on three different outcomes: descriptive statistics, link reconstruction, and model parameters. The results indicate that the often used methods (analysis of available cases and null-tie imputation) lead to considerable bias on descriptive statistics with moderate or large proportions of missing data. Multiple imputation using sophisticated imputation models based on exponential random graph models (ERGMs) lead to acceptable biases in descriptive statistics and model parameters even under large amounts of missing data. For link reconstruction multiple imputation by simple ERGM performed well on small data sets, while missing data was more accurately imputed in larger data sets with multiple imputation by complex Bayesian ERGMs (BERGMs).
WOS:000527272000011
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="34">
<title>Assessing the missing data problem in criminal network analysis using forensic DNA data</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2019.09.003</url>
<snippet>Missing data is pertinent to criminal networks due to the hidden nature of crime. Generally, researchers evaluate the impact of incomplete network data by extracting or adding nodes and/or edges from a known network. Statistics on this reduced or completed network are then compared with statistics from the known network. In this study, we integrate police data on known offenders with DNA data on unknown offenders. Statistics from the integrated dataset (known network) are compared with statistics from the police data (reduced network). Networks with both known and unknown offenders are bigger but also have a different structure to networks with only known offenders.
WOS:000512481500009
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="35">
<title>Migration, mixedness, and the partner's role in core discussion networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.03.004</url>
<snippet>Research into migration and social networks has suggested that migrants are relationally more vulnerable than non-migrants, especially those in endogamous couples. However, non-probability samples and lack of data about partners networks have often impeded rigorous testing. This paper analyses the influence of migration and mixedness (unions between two persons from different geographical origins) on some compositional and structural measures of the core discussion networks of the adult population in Spain, paying special attention to the partners role. Data from the 2013 Spanish General Social Survey (SGSS) were used. A graph census shows the predominance of complete graphs both for endogamous and exogamous couples, but more clearly in the case of natives. Multivariate models prove that, in general, Spaniards in mixed unions seem less partner-dependent, whereas endogamous immigrants seem the most affected by the effects of the geographical mobility on relational vulnerability.
WOS:000798769300001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="36">
<title>Network Canvas: Key decisions in the design of an interviewer-assisted network data collection software suite</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.02.003</url>
<snippet>Self-reported social network analysis studies are often complex and burdensome, both during the interview process itself, and when conducting data management following the interview. Through funding obtained from the National Institute on Drug Abuse (NIDA/NIH), our team developed the Network Canvas suite of software - a set of complementary tools that are designed to simplify the collection and storage of complex social network data, with an emphasis on usability and accessibility across platforms and devices, and guided by the practical needs of researchers. The suite consists of three applications: Architect: an application for researchers to design and export interview protocols; Interviewer: a touch-optimized application for loading and administering interview protocols to study participants; and Server: an application for researchers to manage the interview deployment process and export their data for analysis. Together, they enable researchers with minimal technological expertise to access a complete research workflow, by building their own network interview protocols, deploying these protocols widely within a variety of contexts, and immediately attaining the resulting data from a secure central location. In this paper, we outline the critical decisions taken in developing this suite of tools for the network research community. We also describe the work which guides our decision-making, including prior experiences and key discovery events. We focus on key design choices, taken for theoretical, philosophical, and pragmatic reasons, and outline their strengths and limitations.
WOS:000648645200010
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="37">
<title>Disliking friends of friends in schools: How positive and negative ties can co-occur in large numbers</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.08.001</url>
<snippet>Current network scholarship does not explain why negative and positive ties both frequently occur in large numbers in some settings, such as schools. In the present paper, I argue that this can happen when people disproportionately send negative ties to socially close individuals (friends of friends). I propose a new theor-y-intensity theory-which argues that disliking ties disproportionately occur between friends of friends in intense foci. Intense foci are settings that concentrate social relations, and in which other people are difficult to avoid. I draw on a mixed-methods case study of a boarding school and several strands of literature to substantiate the theory. In so doing, I offer a new mechanism for the initial appearance of disliking ties, propose a contextual approach to balance theory and networks in general, and suggest a more complex view of the link between positive and negative ties.
WOS:000591504700002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="38">
<title>Dimensions of social networks: A taxonomy and operationalization</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.02.005</url>
<snippet>What are the basic types of social network ties captured by name generators? While there have been several classifications proposed, and a large proliferation of name generators capturing various tie content has emerged, there is no clear way to map a given name generator to a particular tie type. Building on previous research, this paper proposes a framework for doing so in a principled way based on two studies. Study 1 is a dimension reduction of 24 common name generators. We find two dimensions (Valence and Social Distance), three positive tie types (Admiration, Closeness, Socialize), and three negative tie types (Active Conflict, Passive Conflict, Contempt) and use Youdens J statistic as a metric to identify the name generator that best maximizes sensitivity and specificity for detecting our tie types. We find that the most common name generators used by researchers fall within just one tie type (Closeness). Study 2 models these six tie types as predictors and outcomes of important sociological variables and finds that each tie type is associated with distinct patterns of emotions, social support, social status, and social roles. Our taxonomy makes a contribution to network theory as well as study design. In particular, it advances our understanding of the nature of signed ties. We find that negative ties are both bipolar and orthogonal, and distinguish between two types of ambivalence. Moreover, the findings contribute to the further refinement and elaboration of a comprehensive taxonomy of network ties.
WOS:000861374000001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="39">
<title>Network dynamics of affiliative ties in preschool peer groups</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2018.12.005</url>
<snippet>This study investigated the network dynamics of affiliative ties in Portuguese preschool children, over three consecutive school years, using stochastic actor-based models. Our first goal was to test the extent to which different criteria to identify ties from observational data lead to different theoretical interpretations of model estimates. Contrary to past observational studies the data we use here takes into account the identities of children responsible for initiating social interactions. The second goal was to test the influence of two interaction effects involving reciprocity to analyze if reciprocity is constrained by the presence of transitive ties and if it constrains the creation and maintenance of new unreciprocated ties. Results showed that most effects were robust to changes in criteria to operationalize ties, supporting previous descriptions of preschool network dynamics. Also, contrary to recent findings in older samples, being embedded in a transitive triad did not make an unreciprocated dyad more likely to be maintained. Finally, results showed that the existence of reciprocal ties decreased preschool childrens tendency to create new ties.
WOS:000458224300006
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="40">
<title>The network of interfamily marriages in 'Ndrangheta</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.08.012</url>
<snippet>A common claim is that mafia families arrange marriages strategically to seal alliances, cement partnerships and enhance cohesion. However, this claim is mainly based on anecdotal evidence and limited case studies. In this paper, by relying on an original database of biographical and relational information on over 4,600 members, we carry out the first large-scale exploratory analysis of the network of interfamily marriages in Ndrangheta. Our analysis shows that this alliance network is polycentric, made up of cohesive subgroups centered around well-connected, powerful families, that occupy different positions in the network. The presence of patterns suggests that marriages in Ndrangheta are possibly the result of family strategies to explore and exploit their power and business. We discuss the implications of these findings for the study of marriages as an organizational instrument.
WOS:000702773800007
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="41">
<title>Collecting experimental network data from interventions on critical links in workplace networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.02.004</url>
<snippet>This article describes and discusses challenges associated with interventionist network data gathering in organizational settings, with a special focus on dyadic interventions. While pointing out major risks of these approaches, we argue that collecting data in combination with dyadic network alteration methods can enable social network researchers to explore network mechanisms from a new angle and potentially benefit the members of the targeted social networks and the entire collectives, if certain research design and implementation principles are followed. We introduce a facilitated self-disclosure method for strengthening critical dyads in social networks in combination with longitudinal and retrospective network measurement. We assess the participants perceptions of the different stages of this process by qualitative interviews. The study illustrates that experimental network data collection includes some extra challenges in addition to the many challenges of observational network data collection but participants also reported practical benefits that would not be gained through observational network surveys alone. The results highlight the importance of early and continuous communication during the data collection process with all research participants, not just the management, and the benefits of sharing more of the preliminary results. The lessons learnt through this study can inform the design of experimental network data collection to prioritize the preferences of the participants and their benefits.
WOS:000648645200007
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="42">
<title>Who are in charge, who do i work with, and who are my friends: A latent space approach to understanding elite coappearances in China</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.01.002</url>
<snippet>How ruling elite arrange and maintain their power-sharing is key to our understanding of authoritarian politics. We analyze the dynamics of elite power-sharing in authoritarian regimes using a network framework that embeds actors onto a low-dimensional space. We also introduce a novel dataset tracking appearances of elite Chinese Community Party (CCP) members at political events. Our framework and data allow us to disentangle three key aspects of CCP elite power-sharing: (1) who are in charge, (2) who do I work with, and (3) who are my friends. Using a latent factor network analysis of approximately 10,000 appearance records of over 200 top CCP elites from 2013 to 2017, we empirically assess these three questions by computing elites total appearances, dyadic coappearances, and their distance in a latent social space. We test how well these three indicators fare at predicting elites appointments to the leading small groups (LSGs) of the CCP Central Committee and the Central Government, and from that analysis are able to highlight the need to account for the indirect ties elites share.
WOS:000648645200003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="43">
<title>Collecting network data from documents to reach non-participatory populations</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.09.004</url>
<snippet>Collecting social network data is challenging, not least because conventional approaches rely on human participation. However, there are instances where access to research subjects is restricted or non-existent, especially in the high-stakes commercial world. This paper outlines the collection of network data from a relatively obscure financial document - the offering circular. I consider the implications of dealing with a non participatory population and data that is not produced for social network research. In exploring the process of translating data into social network data I highlight the importance of retaining context and qualitative descriptions in the data. I also consider how different coding strategies impact the network. Finally, I discuss the triangulation, data anonymity and potential ethical-legal implications of collecting data from documents.
WOS:000777556900011
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="44">
<title>Dynamic network analysis of contact diaries</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.04.001</url>
<snippet>Analyzing two-mode networks linking actors to events they attend may help to uncover the structure and evolution of social networks. This classic social network insight is particularly valuable in the analysis of data extracted from contact diaries where contact events produce - and at the same time are the product of relations among participants. Contact events may comprise any number of actors meeting at a specific point in time. In this paper we recall the correspondence between two-mode actor-event networks and hypergraphs, and propose relational hyperevent models (RHEM) as a general modeling framework for networks of time stamped multi-actor events in which the diarist ("ego") simultaneously meets several of her alters. RHEM can estimate event intensities associated with each possible subset of actors that may jointly participate in events, and test network effects that may be of theoretical or empirical interest. Examples of such effects include preferential attachment, prior shared activity (familiarity), closure, and covariate effects explaining the propensity of actors to co-attend events. Statistical tests of these effects can uncover processes that govern the formation and evolution of informal groups among the diarists alters. We illustrate the empirical value of RHEM using data comprising almost 2000 meeting events of former British Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher with her cabinet ministers, transcribed from contact diaries covering her first term in office (1979-1983).
WOS:000648526600002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="45">
<title>Leadership and contagion by COVID-19 among residence hall students: A social network analysis approach</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2023.01.001</url>
<snippet>University students have changed their behaviour due to the COVID-19 pandemic. In this paper, we describe the characteristics of PCR+ and PCR-nodes, analyse the structure, and relate the structure of student leaders to pandemic contagion as determined by PCR+ in 93 residential university students. Leadership comes from the male students of social science degrees who have PCR +, with an eigenvector centrality structure, beta-centrality, and who are part of the bow-tie structure. There was a significant difference in beta-centrality between leaders and non-leaders and in beta-centrality between PCR+ and non-leaders. Leading nodes were part of the bow-tie structure. MR-QAP results show how residence and scientific branch were the most important factors in network formation. Therefore, university leaders should consider influential leaders, as they are vectors for disseminating both positive and negative outcomes.
WOS:000920256100001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="46">
<title>Positive, negative, and ambivalent dyads and triads with family and friends: A personal network study on how they are associated with young adults' well-being</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2024.02.004</url>
<snippet>Although negative ties may cause stress and harm well-being, they are also considered fundamental in close and ongoing relationships. This study distinguishes positive, negative, and - when characterized by both valences - ambivalent ties. Analyzing almost 10,000 personal networks from the Swiss CH-X study shows that: (1) ambivalence among family members is more prevalent than among non-family members, (2) ambivalent family dyads or triads are not negatively associated with well-being, and (3) certain balanced family triads are associated with higher well-being and an unbalanced non-family triad is associated with lower well-being. These results suggest that conflicts are not necessarily detrimental to young adults well-being.
WOS:001226516200001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="47">
<title>Prismatic effects of negative ties</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2019.07.004</url>
<snippet>Research on negative ties has focused primarily on the harm they do. In this paper, we show that negative ties can also have beneficial effects. We argue that, like positive ties, negative ties can link actors together in the minds of observers. As a result, we theorize that negative ties with high-status actors can benefit a focal actor, whereas negative ties with low-status actors can harm the focal actor. This prismatic effect depends on the existing status of the focal actor: a focal actor of low status is likely to benefit far more from negative ties with high-status actors and suffer more from negative ties with low-status actors than will an actor of high-status. To test our ideas, we analyze the phenomenon of "diss songs" in hip-hop music. A diss song is a song in which a rapper makes derogatory comments about another rapper, constituting a negative tie. We analyze the effects of negative ties among 53 rappers over 20 points in time on audience reaction as measured by record sales. We find that negative ties with high-status actors enhance future sales for low-status actors. However, negative ties with lower-status actors have no effect on the future sales of both low- and high-status actors. Just as some researchers have reported both positive and negative consequences of social capital, our study demonstrates that negative ties can also have both positive and negative outcomes.
WOS:000501619700003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="48">
<title>Social networks and the emergence of health inequalities following a medical advance: Examining prenatal H1N1 vaccination decisions</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2019.03.002</url>
<snippet>Health inequalities persist, in part, because people in socioeconomically advantageous positions possess resources to avoid new health risks when medicine advances. Although these health decisions rarely occur in isolation, we know less about the specific role of networks. We examine whether social capital mediates the relationship between individual educational attainment and decisions about a medical advance: H1N1 vaccination during pregnancy. Building on prior work that defines social capital as the resources of network members, we examine two mechanisms through which social capital may affect health decisions, facilitating information flow and exerting influence. Using egocentric network data collected from 225 pregnant women during the 2009-10 H1N1 pandemic, we measure social capital as the proportion of networks that are college-educated H1N1 discussants (information flow) and the proportion of college-educated H1N1 supporters (influence). Findings reveal that college-educated women knew more college-educated H1N1 discussants and supporters. Further, both measures of social capital predicted higher probabilities of vaccination, with the latter mechanism emerging as a particularly strong predictor. Our findings provide evidence that health decisions are shaped by individual resources as well as social capital available through network ties, offering a unique perspective of the ways that social networks contribute to producing, and potentially reproducing, unequal health.
WOS:000472813200013
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="49">
<title>What is(n't) a friend? Dimensions of the friendship concept among adolescents</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.01.004</url>
<snippet>Much research in network analysis of adolescent friendships assumes that friendships represent liking and social interaction, friendships are directed, and friendships are equivalent to one another. This study investigates the meaning of friendship for eight diverse cohorts of sixth graders. Analysis of focus group and survey data suggests that these adolescents construe friendship as a multidimensional role relation composed primarily of relational norms, expectations for mutual behavior. Their friendship definitions may also include mutual liking and interaction, and other structural expectations such as reciprocity, homophily, and transitivity. Lastly, boys and girls weight these dimensions differently in defining friendship.
WOS:000648645200014
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="50">
<title>Multiple partitioning of multiplex signed networks Application to European parliament votes</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2019.02.001</url>
<snippet>For more than a decade, graphs have been used to model the voting behavior taking place in parliaments. However, the methods described in the literature suffer from several limitations. The two main ones are that 1) they rely on some temporal integration of the raw data, which causes some information loss; and/or 2) they identify groups of antagonistic voters, but not the context associated with their occurrence. In this article, we propose a novel method taking advantage of multiplex signed graphs to solve both these issues. It consists in first partitioning separately each layer, before grouping these partitions by similarity. We show the interest of our approach by applying it to a European Parliament dataset.
WOS:000501619700008
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="51">
<title>Let it go or let it grow? - Personal network development and the mobilization of intra-organizational social capital</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.06.002</url>
<snippet>We investigate how differences in personal network development affect the mobilization of social capital for new organizational members. Analyzing three waves of panel data reported by 24 newcomers in nine organizations, we ask whether the kind and volume of resources derived by focal actors depends rather on changes in the composition or in the size of their intra-organizational networks. We find that change in network composition predicts an increase in social capital mobilization over time. Network growth is found to reduce the affective resources that newcomers mobilize. Implications for subsequent research and organizational socialization practices are discussed.
WOS:000700623500014
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="52">
<title>The influence of structural balance and homophily/heterophobia on the adjustment of random complete signed networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2015.08.005</url>
<snippet>Inconsistencies in the empirical support for balance theory are often explained by recourse to competing mechanisms that reduce the total degree of balance in the network. These mechanisms (such as differential popularity and subgroup hostility) may depend on exogenous properties of the nodes. This paper offers an alternative explanation for the departure of networks from global balance, according to which the myopic nature of sign adjustment in accordance with a pressure for local balance may reduce the global degree of balance and impede the formation of groups, whereas competing mechanisms that rely on exogenous node properties (e.g., homophily) facilitate these processes. The paper describes a set of simulations designed to study the evolution of complete signed networks under a local sign-change regime, induced by structural balance, homophily and heterophobia. Tolerance for local violation of balance and homophily is allowed to vary with a consequent impact upon the global degree of balance and group formation processes. We find the conditions under which the pressure towards local homophily and balance operate against each other culminating in a (locally) dynamic yet (globally) stationary state in which homophily adjusts towards group formation and balance undermines this process. (C) 2015 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000367423900017
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="53">
<title>Seeing and being seen: Predictors of accurate perceptions about classmates' relationships</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2015.07.002</url>
<snippet>This study examines predictors of observer accuracy (i.e. seeing) and target accuracy (i.e. being seen) in perceptions of classmates relationships in a predominantly African American sample of 420 second through fourth graders (ages 7-11). Girls, children in higher grades, and children in smaller classrooms were more accurate observers. Targets (i.e. pairs of children) were more accurately observed when they occurred in smaller classrooms of higher grades and involved same-sex, high-popularity, and similar-popularity children. Moreover, relationships between pairs of girls were more accurately observed than relationships between pairs of boys. As a set, these findings suggest the importance of both observer and target characteristics for childrens accurate perceptions of classroom relationships. Moreover, the substantial variation in observer accuracy and target accuracy has methodological implications for both peer-reported assessments of classroom relationships and the use of stochastic actor-based models to understand peer selection and socialization processes. (C) 2015 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000367423900001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="54">
<title>Multilevel network data facilitate statistical inference for curved ERGMs with geometrically weighted terms</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2018.11.003</url>
<snippet>Multilevel network data provide two important benefits for ERG modeling. First, they facilitate estimation of the decay parameters in geometrically weighted terms for degree and triad distributions. Estimating decay parameters from a single network is challenging, so in practice they are typically fixed rather than estimated. Multilevel network data overcome that challenge by leveraging replication. Second, such data make it possible to assess out-of-sample performance using traditional cross-validation techniques. We demonstrate these benefits by using a multilevel network sample of classroom networks from Poland. We show that estimating the decay parameters improves in-sample performance of the model and that the out-of-sample performance of our best model is strong, suggesting that our findings can be generalized to the population of interest.
WOS:000487171000009
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="55">
<title>Keep around, drop, or revise? exploring what becomes of difficult ties in personal networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2023.06.001</url>
<snippet>Previous studies increasingly recognize the presence and impact of difficult individuals within personal networks. However, current research sheds little light on the turnover, retention, and change in quality of such difficult ties. The current study addresses this gap by focusing on two distinct forms of network change. We examine how role relationships, support exchange, relational homophily, and personal characteristics are associated with these processes. Data are drawn from three waves of the University of California Social Network Study (UCNets), a project containing comprehensive longitudinal data on ego networks among two adult cohorts. Findings indicate that over time, 34&#37; of difficult ties re-appear in peoples networks as sources of aggravation; 26&#37; of difficult ties are removed from the network; and 40&#37; can no longer be verified as problematic network members. Most ties no longer deemed difficult are identified as providing one or more supportive functions. Multinomial multilevel models reveal that exchanging support tends to anchor difficult ties in the network. Kinship, meanwhile, plays a large role in whether difficult ties remain or get dropped. Personal characteristics such as gender, income, and relocation also play a role in these processes. Overall, we conclude that the turnover dynamics of difficult ties are similar to other ties, and the apparent change from negative to positive suggests that many ties hold ambivalent properties that make shedding such ties less common than may be expected.
WOS:001032849900001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="56">
<title>A restricted multiple generator approach to enumerate personal support networks: An alternative to global important matters and satisficing in web surveys</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.04.006</url>
<snippet>Overlooked issues in the selection and presentation of name generators may lead to extreme measurement errors in Web surveys. This paper compares networks elicited from the standard "important matters" (IM) name generator, which records alter names on one or five boxes per page, with a two-generator design and an alternative approach, the R5D. The R5D consists of five name generators focused on a range of topics commonly discussed as important matters. Each generator is restricted to recording one alter. Generally accepted practices in egocentric surveys result in inaccurate measures of network size and composition. They include the use of the stand-alone IM generator and advice to present a single name box to record one alter name per page. The use of a single name box encourages satisficing. The R5D is a parsimonious alternative with stronger construct validity. It has less measurement error, provides measures of social support, and enumerates alters with less slippage in importance than other approaches.
WOS:000700623500004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="57">
<title>From neighbors to school friends? How adolescents' place of residence relates to same-ethnic school friendships</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2015.07.004</url>
<snippet>This study examines to what extent adolescents place of residence is related to the opportunities and the preferences to befriend same-ethnic classmates. Analyzing 3345 students within 158 German and Dutch school classes, we find that sharing a neighborhood provides additional meeting opportunities to become friends in class as adolescents are likely to befriend classmates who live nearby them or who live nearby a friend of them (propinquity mechanism). However, this hardly explains why adolescent friendship networks in school classes tend to be ethnically homogeneous. Also, we find no convincing evidence that an adolescents preference for same-ethnic friends in class varies with the share of outgroup members in his/her neighborhood (exposure mechanism). (C) 2015 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000367423900012
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="58">
<title>Selection and influence processes in academic achievement-More pronounced for girls?</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2017.09.003</url>
<snippet>Friends tend to be similar in their academic achievement. In this study, we investigate whether this similarity results from students selecting friends with similar achievement or from friends influencing students achievement. In particular, we argue that selection and influence effects should be stronger among girls than among boys. Using friendship network data on 1273 German secondary school students and stochastic actor-oriented models for the co-evolution of networks and behavior, we find selection effects only among girls, which is in line with our theoretical arguments. By contrast, influence effects contribute to achievement similarity among both boys and girls. (C) 2017 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000416496300023
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="59">
<title>Order of recall and meaning of closeness in collecting affective network data</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.12.006</url>
<snippet>The paper investigates how study participants handle the so-called "hierarchical mapping technique", an affective name generator developed by Antonucci (1986), which is accompanied by a diagram enabling respondents to compare alters with regard to different degrees of closeness. By applying the thinking-aloud method, we identified three patterns in the order of recalling alters: closeness as overarching schema (with either role relationships or relationship properties as subordinate schema), roles and foci as overarching schema, and a fraying schema. In addition, we investigated how study participants understand and interpret "closeness". The meanings of closeness can refer to various relationship properties, cultural framing, and relationship dynamics. Results show that specific meanings of closeness are related to different recall patterns. Furthermore, recall patterns vary according to the socio-economic status of the participants. Finally, implications for the construction of name generators and data collection are discussed.
WOS:000614282000011
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="60">
<title>Analyzing multiplex networks using factorial methods</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2019.07.005</url>
<snippet>Multiplex networks arise when more than one source of relationships exists for a common set of nodes. Many approaches to deal with this kind of complex network data structure are reported in the literature. In this paper, we propose the use of factorial methods to visually explore the complex structure of multiplex networks. Specifically, the adjacency matrices derived from multiplex networks are analyzed using the DISTATIS technique, an extension of multidimensional scaling to three-way data. This technique allows the representation of the different types of relationships in both separate spaces for each layer and a compromise space. The analytical procedure is illustrated using a real world example and simulated data.
WOS:000487171000013
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="61">
<title>Building a structural typology of personal networks: Individual differences in the cohesion of interpersonal environment</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.09.006</url>
<snippet>The development of typologies is an efficient strategy in the descriptive study of individual differences in the interpersonal environment of relationships. In this paper, we developed a classification of personal networks using structural indicators with a representative sample (n = 403) in a medium-sized city of the metropolitan environment of Seville, in the south of Spain. The typology was based on the analysis of conglomerates with three criteria variables: centralization, number of cliques, and the number of components. The results allowed the identification of four types of personal networks: dense, intermediate, clustered, and fragmented networks. The classification was validated with descriptive data, linear discriminant analysis, and visual-classification pro-cedure. The structural cohesion and the formation of cohesive sub-groups were two key dimensions to describe the variability of the personal networks in the sample.
WOS:000591504700005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="62">
<title>Optimizing dynamical changes of structural balance in signed network based on memetic algorithm</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2015.06.004</url>
<snippet>In dynamical evolution of structural balance, unbalanced signed networks evolve to structurally balanced ones. In this paper, we compute the least number of sign changes in the evolution of structural balance. It is suggested that there be a certain bias towards flipping positive or flipping negative signs. The number of flipped signs is quantified by an objective function. Moreover, a memetic algorithm is proposed to optimize the objective function. Experiments show that our algorithm is efficient and effective to optimize dynamical evolution of structural balance. (C) 2015 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000367423900006
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="63">
<title>The Swiss StudentLife Study: Investigating the emergence of an undergraduate community through dynamic, multidimensional social network data</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.11.006</url>
<snippet>The Swiss StudentLife Study (SSL Study) is a longitudinal social network data collection conducted in three undergraduate student cohorts (N-1 = 226, N-2 = 261, N-3 = 660) in 2016-2019. The main goal of the study was to understand the emergence of informal student communities and their effects on different individual outcomes, such as well-being, motivation, and academic success. To this end, multiple dimensions of social ties were assessed, combining computer-based surveys, social sensors, social media data, and field experiments. The dynamics of these social networks were measured on various time scales. In this paper, we present the design and data collection strategy of the SSL Study. We discuss practical challenges and solutions related to the data collection in four areas that were key to the success of our project: study design, research ethics, communication, and population definition.
WOS:000614282000007
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="64">
<title>Building trust and co-designing a study of trust and co-operation: Observations from a network study in a high-risk, high-security environment</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.06.005</url>
<snippet>As part of a larger project on trust and co-operation in IT-Security, the author collected network data from an international security team specialized in cyber-incident response, leading to the only dataset of its kind. Collecting these data involved a number of challenges. First, the team in question had recently been established and was based in a large international firm. Thus, the author had to navigate legal and procedural issues, and stay on top of a changing environment. Second, actors in IT-Security are acutely aware of how data can be misused, requiring the author to build trust and demonstrate appropriate data handling. Attaining support from security managers was a key step to build trust with participants and the host organization. Third, precautions were necessary due to the project's security implications, as the study data could be abused by adversaries. Consequentially, it was necessary to engage in a co-design process, negotiating technical and procedural precautions. Not all measures initially agreed upon were feasible in practice.
WOS:000777556900013
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="65">
<title>Order of recall and meaning of closeness in collecting affective network data (Reprinted from vol 65, pages 124-140, 2021)</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.01.011</url>
<snippet>The paper investigates how study participants handle the so-called "hierarchical mapping technique", an af-fective name generator developed by Antonucci (1986), which is accompanied by a diagram enabling re-spondents to compare alters with regard to different degrees of closeness. By applying the thinking-aloud method, we identified three patterns in the order of recalling alters: closeness as overarching schema (with either role relationships or relationship properties as subordinate schema), roles and foci as overarching schema, and a fraying schema. In addition, we investigated how study participants understand and interpret "closeness". The meanings of closeness can refer to various relationship properties, cultural framing, and relationship dynamics. Results show that specific meanings of closeness are related to different recall patterns. Furthermore, recall patterns vary according to the socio-economic status of the participants. Finally, implications for the construction of name generators and data collection are discussed.
WOS:000777028500004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="66">
<title>Who is dropped and why? Methodological and substantive accounts for network loss</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2019.08.008</url>
<snippet>High rates of egocentric network turnover are frequently observed but not well explained. About 1000 respondents to the UCNets survey named an average of 10 names in each of two waves a year apart. Consistent with prior studies, respondents in wave 2 failed to relist about half of the names they provided in wave 1. Asked why, respondents explained that they had forgotten the alter for about 40 percent of the missing names. Other common answers, such as no "occasion ... to be in touch," also suggest that the true rate of alters being dropped is probably under 20 percent. Multilevel logit models identified the predictors of alters being dropped (neither relisted nor forgotten) versus retained. Immediate kin were likeliest to be retained and roommates, coworkers, and acquaintances to be dropped. Alters who provided companionship, confiding, advice, and emergency help were especially likely to be retained, as were those to whom respondents felt close. Little about the respondents themselves affected drop rates: having moved recently, having a close friend die, or having had an important relationship break up. Results are consistent with the argument that a ties degree of constraint (notably being close family) and its balance of rewards determine the likelihood of it being dropped or demoted.
WOS:000512481500007
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="67">
<title>What kinds of social networks protect older adults? health during a pandemic? The tradeoff between preventing infection and promoting mental health</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.05.004</url>
<snippet>When the coronavirus emerged in early 2020, older adults were at heightened risk of contracting the virus, and of suffering mental health consequences from the pandemic and from the precautions designed to mitigate it. In this paper, we examine how social networks prior to the pandemic helped to shape health beliefs, behaviors, and outcomes among older adults during its onset, focusing on (1) perceived risk of COVID-19, (2) preventative health behaviors, and (3) mental health, including loneliness, perceived stress, depression, and anxiety. Drawing on the longitudinal Social Networks in Alzheimer Disease study, we find that networks high in bridging social capital predict greater perceived risk and more precautions taken, but worse mental health. In contrast, networks high in bonding social capital predict less perceived risk and fewer precautions taken, but better mental health. We discuss this apparent tradeoff between physical and mental health.
WOS:000807817000001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="68">
<title>A community matching based approach to measuring layer similarity in multilayer networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.04.004</url>
<snippet>In multilayer networks, quantifying layer similarity is of great importance for many applications. Traditional approaches to measure layer similarities rely mainly on micro-level features of network structures, such as node degree. In this paper, we propose to use mesoscopic network structures, i.e., communities, to assess layer sim-ilarity. Our proposed approach is based on matching the communities detected at the layers being compared. The similarity is thus defined using clustering evaluation methods such as purity and F-measure. Our results on empirical datasets show that the proposed approach provides more consistent layer taxonomies than other approaches.
WOS:000700623500001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="69">
<title>Avoidance, antipathy, and aggression: A three-wave longitudinal network study on negative networks, status, and heteromisos</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.08.006</url>
<snippet>Our aim is to explain negative networks in Dutch high schools, using three-wave stochastic actor oriented models (SAOMs). We differentiate between avoidance, antipathy, and aggression based on how costly and visible these behaviours are. Our results show that pupils ethnicity does not explain negative ties. Moreover, we do not find that negative ties form archetypical social hierarchies, formed by networks that are asymmetrical and transitive. Instead, we find positive effects of reciprocity on avoidance, antipathy, and aggression, and we find no effects of transitivity. Rather than allowing themselves to be dominated by their classmates, pupils fight back and recip-rocate negative behaviour. We further show that some pupils behave negatively to a lot of their classmates, and that some pupils are treated negatively by many classmates. These results require us to reconsider what status hierarchies look like. Finally, we explore the extent to which the avoidance, antipathy, and aggression networks co-evolve.
WOS:000591504700001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="70">
<title>Collecting experimental network data from interventions on critical links in workplace networks (Reprinted from vol 66, pages 72-90, 2021)</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.01.005</url>
<snippet>This article describes and discusses challenges associated with interventionist network data gathering in organizational settings, with a special focus on dyadic interventions. While pointing out major risks of these approaches, we argue that collecting data in combination with dyadic network alteration methods can enable social network researchers to explore network mechanisms from a new angle and potentially benefit the members of the targeted social networks and the entire collectives, if certain research design and implementation principles are followed. We introduce a facilitated self-disclosure method for strengthening critical dyads in social networks in combination with longitudinal and retrospective network measurement. We assess the participants perceptions of the different stages of this process by qualitative interviews. The study illustrates that experimental network data collection includes some extra challenges in addition to the many challenges of observational network data collection but participants also reported practical benefits that would not be gained through observational network surveys alone. The results highlight the importance of early and continuous communication during the data collection process with all research participants, not just the management, and the benefits of sharing more of the preliminary results. The lessons learnt through this study can inform the design of experimental network data collection to prioritize the preferences of the participants and their benefits.
WOS:000777028500010
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="71">
<title>Chronic illness and social network bridging in later life*</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2023.01.007</url>
<snippet>Chronic disease has profound impacts on the structural features of individuals interpersonal connections such as bridging - ties to people who are otherwise poorly connected to each other. Prior research has documented competing arguments regarding the benefits of network bridging, but less is known about how chronic illness influences bridging and its underlying mechanisms. Using data on 1555 older adults from the National Social Life, Health, and Aging Project (NSHAP), I find that older adults diagnosed with chronic illness tend to have lower bridging potential in their networks, particularly between kin and non-kin members. They also report more frequent interactions with close ties but fewer neighbors, friends, and colleagues in their networks, which mediates the association between chronic illness and social network bridging. These findings illuminate both direct and indirect pathways through which chronic illness affects network bridging and highlight the context-specific implications for social networks in later life.
WOS:001002532800001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="72">
<title>Dissecting discursive contention: A relational analysis of the Dutch debate on minority integration, 1990-2006</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2016.05.006</url>
<snippet>This paper elaborates a relational approach to examine discursive contention. We develop a network method to identify groups forming through contentious interactions as well as relational measures of polarization, leadership, solidarity and various aspects of discursive power. The paper analyzes how an assimilationist movement confronted its adversaries in the Dutch debate on minority integration. Over different periods in the debate, we find a recurrent pattern: a small yet cohesive group of challengers with strong discursive leaders forces their framing of integration issues upon other participants. We suggest that the pattern found in our study may exemplify a more universal network pattern behind discursive contention. (C) 2016 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000382592500010
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="73">
<title>Confidentiality, power relations and evaluation of potential harm in the study of the personal and organizational networks of travel agents in Moscow</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2019.10.009</url>
<snippet>Network research in organizational contexts faces ethical challenges related to revealing the identity of participants, managing power relations, and managing the interests and potential harms of the different stakeholders. In this article, we review the ethical issues associated with the investigation of the personal and organizational networks of travel agents in Moscow. In our case study, we interviewed 32 tourism agents from Moscow and its region, obtaining information on 45 people with whom they have regular relation as part of their work; and relational data, with a 2-mode matrix, on 15 organizations with which the agency could be linked in the RussianAndalusian tourism market. Our results highlight the utility of presenting the information of personal networks in an aggregate manner. It also demonstrates the value of cultural adaptation strategies and adjustment to the characteristics of the community. Moreover, the central role of power relations in organizations, within a cultural context with a greater distance to authority was also found.
WOS:000685648800008
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="74">
<title>External exposure, boundary-spanning, and opinion leadership in remote communities: A network experiment</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2018.08.002</url>
<snippet>Are boundary spanners opinion leaders in ethnically segregated remote low-income communities or are they shunned? Can external exposure create opinion leaders in such peripheral communities? To answer these questions, we invited randomly selected farmers from 16 randomly selected communities in Sumatra to three-day networking and training events outside of their villages. The substantive purpose of these events was for the farmers to learn new practices from their peers in the visited locations. Eighteen months later, we conducted a sociocentric survey of information-sharing networks in the 16 communities. These 16 networks included 380 members, of which 117 participated in our randomized intervention and 263 were in the control group. We found that participants of our randomized intervention had an average indegree that was double that of the control group (2.8 vs 1.4). We applied Exponential Random Graph Models to the 16 networks to account for endogenous network tendencies. We treated participation in the intervention and the number of boundary spanning links of each actor as node covariates. Results from our models show that actors who participated in the intervention had higher levels of influence in their communities than the control group, and actors with more boundary spanning links were more popular sources of advice. The results suggest that network interventions do not always need to rely on opinion leaders. Under certain conditions, interventions can create opinion leaders by changing local social networks. We conclude with methodological implications for using interventions in social network research.
WOS:000454966400002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="75">
<title>Using&lt;i&gt; Trellis&lt;/i&gt; software to enhance high-quality large-scale network data collection in the field</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.02.007</url>
<snippet>Trellis is a mobile platform created by the Human Nature Lab at the Yale Institute for Network Science to collect high-quality, location-aware, off-line/online, multi-lingual, multi-relational social network and behavior data in hard-to-reach communities. Respondents use Trellis to identify their social contacts by name and photograph, a procedure especially useful in low-literacy populations or in contexts where names may be similar or confusing. We use social network data collected from 1,969 adult respondents in two villages in Kenya to demonstrate Trellis ability to provide unprecedented metadata to monitor and report on the data collection process including artifactual variability based on surveyors, time of day, or location.
WOS:000648645200015
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="76">
<title>Who is fighting with whom? How ethnic origin shapes friendship, dislike, and physical violence relations in German secondary schools</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2019.04.004</url>
<snippet>This study examines the role of ethnic background for friendship, dislike, and violence networks in secondary school. We analyze data on multiple networks from a large-scale study of more than 2500 seventh-graders in Germany. In addition to ethnic homophily in friendship networks, our results reveal a tendency among students to dislike ethnic outgroup members (ethnic heterophobia). However, students are more likely to engage in violence towards same-ethnic peers than outgroup members. This is partly due to the greater prevalence of violence among students who are close in the friendship network and students who spend time together outside of school. Moreover, schools marked by stronger ethnic homophily in friendships tend to display higher levels of ethnic heterophobia but exhibit higher levels of intra-ethnic rather than inter-ethnic violence.
WOS:000501619700004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="77">
<title>Spatial effects on individual social capital: Differentiating the constraints of local occupational structures</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.09.003</url>
<snippet>Recent studies have paid more attention to how position-generated social capital varies by an individuals characteristics, and less to how geographical distributions of occupations may constrain position-specific con-nections. By integrating two national surveys from the United States, we differentiate the extent to which individual social capital fluctuates by occupational compositions at the county, metropolis, and state levels. Multilevel analyses show that when more people at all three levels work in education, training, and library occupations, residents have a greater chance to gain access to professional-type resources. Similar spatial effects on farming and production resources, however, are more apparent at the county level. Not only does the association between individual social capital and local occupational structures vary across different occupations, but the magnitude of such spatial effects also differs by the scope of the geographical areas. The findings underscore how contextual factors and geographical location may contribute to building occupation-specific network resources.
WOS:000591504700007
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="78">
<title>Re-print of: Contextualizing oppositional cultures: A multilevel network analysis of status orders in schools</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2023.11.001</url>
<snippet>Different lines of research have argued that specific groups, such as boys or ethnic minorities, are more prone to develop an anti-school culture than others, leading to group differences in the social acceptance of high performers. Taking an ecological view, we ask to what extent the school context promotes or prevents the emergence of group-specific oppositional cultures. Theoretically, we argue that group-based oppositional cultures become more likely in schools with low socio-economic resources and in schools where socio-economic differences align with demographic attributes. We test our hypotheses based on data from a large-scale, four-wave network panel survey among more than 4000 students in Germany. Applying stochastic actor-oriented models for the coevolution of networks and behavior, we find that group-based oppositional cultures in which students like high performers less are very rare. However, in line with theoretical expectations, the less resourceful a school is, the more boys tend to evaluate high-performing peers less positively than girls do. Moreover, the more ethnic minority boys are socioeconomically disdvantaged in a school, the more they tend to evaluate high performers less positively than majority boys do.
WOS:001188248700001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="79">
<title>'Entanglement' - A new dynamic metric to measure team flow</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.11.010</url>
<snippet>We introduce "entanglement", a novel metric to measure how synchronized communication between team members is. This measure calculates the Euclidean distance among team members social network metrics timeseries. We validate the metric with four case studies. The first case study uses entanglement of 11 medical innovation teams to predict team performance and learning behavior. The second case looks at the e-mail communication of 113 senior executives of an international services firm, predicting employee turnover through lack of entanglement of an employee. The third case analyzes the individual employee performance of 81 managers. The fourth case study predicts performance of 13 customer-dedicated teams at a big international company by comparing entanglement in the e-mail interactions with satisfaction of their customers measured through Net Promoter Score (NPS). While we can only speculate about what is causing the entanglement effect, we find that it is a new and versatile indicator for the analysis of employees communication, analyzing the hitherto underused temporal dimension of online social networks which could be used as a powerful predictor of employee and team performance, employee turnover, and customer satisfaction.
WOS:000819930800002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="80">
<title>Inferring signed networks from preschoolers' observed parallel and social play</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.07.002</url>
<snippet>Early childhood is an important developmental period for network formation. However, the observational methods used for measuring young childrens networks present challenges for capturing both positive and negative ties. To overcome these challenges, we explored the use of a bipartite projection backbone model for inferring both negative and positive ties from observational data of childrens play. Using observational data collected in one 3-year-old (N = 17) and one 4-year-old (N = 18) preschool classroom, we examined whether patterns of homophily, triadic closure, and balance in networks inferred using this method matched theoretical and empirical expectations from the early childhood literature. Consistent with this literature, we found that signed networks inferred using a backbone model exhibited gender homophily in positive ties and gender heterophily in negative ties. Additionally, networks inferred from social play exhibited more closed and balanced triads than networks inferred from parallel play. These findings offer evidence of the validity of bipartite projection backbone models for inferring signed networks from preschoolers observed play.
WOS:000932028700001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="81">
<title>Nonresponse in name generators across countries and survey modes</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2024.06.002</url>
<snippet>Past research indicates interviewer effects lead to an underestimation of network size and higher nonresponse to the "important matters" name generator. Self-administered surveys offer a potential solution, but evidence is mixed and context-specific. We employ a logistic multilevel regression, estimated using a Bayesian Markov Chain Monte Carlo approach, to analyze nonresponse to this name generator from 33 post-electoral surveys across 21 countries in the Comparative National Election Project. We find higher nonresponse in interviewer-administered surveys compared to self-administered surveys, particularly among specific demographic groups. Finally, we discuss the trade-offs in selecting survey modes for collecting ego-network data using this instrument.
WOS:001266439200001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="82">
<title>Network sampling coverage III: Imputation of missing network data under different network and missing data conditions</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.05.002</url>
<snippet>Missing data is a common, difficult problem for network studies. Unfortunately, there are few clear guidelines about what a researcher should do when faced with incomplete information. We take up this problem in the third paper of a three-paper series on missing network data. Here, we compare the performance of different imputation methods across a wide range of circumstances characterized in terms of measures, networks and missing data types. We consider a number of imputation methods, going from simple imputation to more complex modelbased approaches. Overall, we find that listwise deletion is almost always the worst option, while choosing the best strategy can be difficult, as it depends on the type of missing data, the type of network and the measure of interest. We end the paper by offering a set of practical outputs that researchers can use to identify the best imputation choice for their particular research setting.
WOS:000700623500013
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="83">
<title>Connecting mobile social media with psychosocial well-being: Understanding relationship between WeChat involvement, network characteristics, online capital and life satisfaction</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.08.006</url>
<snippet>Previous studies have confirmed the powerful influence of social networks on individuals mental health and well-being. However, the relative contribution of different dimensions of network characteristics to psychosocial outcomes on mobile social media is unclear. The objectives of this current research are to investigate the effect of WeChat involvement on young peoples network characteristics (network diversity and network size) and to examine the influence of network characteristics on their online bridging capital, bonding capital and life satisfaction. Especially, the hypothesized research model is developed to unpack the mediating role of network characteristics in the association between WeChat usage and related psychosocial outcomes. Based on survey data collected from 566 young people, the study demonstrates that WeChat involvement positively predicts individuals network diversity and network size in their daily routine life. Interestingly, network diversity is also positively associated with degrees of online bridging capital, online bonding capital and satisfaction with life. Additionally, the mediating roles of network diversity and network size between WeChat involvement and psychosocial outcomes is revealed. The research findings provide fresh insight into understanding the implication of individuals mobile social media use and network network attibutes for well-being outcomes in contemporay mobile-mediated environment.
WOS:000702773800002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="84">
<title>Religious friendship preferences of Muslim and non-Muslim students in German schools: Bright boundaries everywhere or contingent on the proportion of Muslim classmates?</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.04.005</url>
<snippet>While network studies have shown that preferences of both Muslim and non-Muslim adolescents contribute to religious friendship segregation, it is unclear whether these preferences are ubiquitous or dependent on local context. Examining large-scale longitudinal friendship network data of adolescents in Germany, we investigate how the proportion of Muslim classmates affects friendship preferences of Muslims and non-Muslims. We find that Muslim youth favor Muslims over non-Muslims to a similar degree at all proportions of Muslim classmates. Non-Muslims reluctance to be friends with Muslims peaks in classrooms in which about half of the students are Muslims but is otherwise lower or absent.
WOS:000700623500005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="85">
<title>Impact of survey design on estimation of exponential-family random graph models from egocentrically-sampled data</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.10.001</url>
<snippet>Egocentric sampling of networks selects a subset of nodes ("egos") and collects information from them on themselves and their immediate network neighbours ("alters"), leaving the rest of the nodes in the network unobserved. This design is popular because it is relatively inexpensive to implement and can be integrated into standard sample surveys. Recent methodological developments now make it possible to statistically analyse this type of network data with exponential-family random graph models (ERGMs). This provides a framework for principled statistical inference, and the fitted models can in turn be used to simulate complete networks of arbitrary size that are consistent with the observed sample data, allowing one to infer the distribution of whole network properties generated by the observed egocentric network statistics. In this paper, we discuss how design choices for egocentric network studies impact statistical estimation and inference for ERGMs. The design choices include both measurement strategies (for ego and alter attributes, and for ego-alter and alter-alter ties) and sampling strategies (for egos and alters). We discuss the importance of harmonising measurement specifications across egos and alters, and conduct simulation studies to demonstrate the impact of sampling design on statistical inference, specifically stratified sampling and degree censoring.
WOS:000777556900004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="86">
<title>Use of a hierarchical deconstruction procedure for the classification of personal networks: Exploring nested groups around you</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.12.005</url>
<snippet>The deconstruction of personal networks through the iterative elimination of the nodes with the highest betweenness centrality is an effective strategy for describing their structural properties. In this study we show that iterative deconstruction can also serve to classify personal networks into typologies. With longitudinal data from a sample of 69 students, we found that denser networks are more resistant to fragmentation while those organized in defined subgroups usually have a shorter deconstruction process. In addition, the deconstruction strategy allows knowing the hierarchical structure of personal networks, made up of nested subgroups.
WOS:000912320700001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="87">
<title>Homophily in collaborations among US House Representatives, 1981-2018</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.04.007</url>
<snippet>Effective lawmaking requires collaboration among legislators, who form coalitions to advance their legislative agendas. In this paper, we explore how legislators party and gender identities simultaneously influence whom they choose as collaborators by examining differential party and gender homophily during a period of shifting party control and increasing representation of women in the US House of Representatives. We introduce new methods for inferring legislative collaboration networks from bill co-sponsorship data, then estimate cross-sectional logistic regression models on these networks from 1981-2018. We find evidence of differential homophily by both party and gender: Republicans and women tend to prefer same-party and same-gender political collaborators more than Democrats and men. However, party homophily (i.e., partisanship) is stronger than gender homophily, suggesting that party is a more salient identity for legislators than gender.
WOS:000700623500008
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="88">
<title>Collecting large personal networks in a representative sample of Dutch women</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.07.012</url>
<snippet>In this study we report on our experiences with collecting large personal network data (25 alters) from a representative sample of Dutch women. We made use of GENSI, a recently developed tool for network data collection using interactive visual elements that has been shown to reduce respondent burden. A sample of 758 women between the ages of 18 and 40 were recruited through the LISS-panel; a longitudinal online survey of Dutch people. Respondents were asked to name exactly 25 alters, answer sixteen questions about these alters (name interpreter questions), and assess all 300 alter-alter relations. Nearly all (97&#37;) respondents reported on 25 alters. Non-response was minimal: 92&#37; of respondents had no missing values, and an additional 5&#37; had fewer than 10&#37; missing values. Listing 25 alters took 3.5 +/- 2.2 (mean +/- SD) minutes, and reporting on the ties between these alters took 3.6 +/- 1.3 min. Answering all alter questions took longest with a time of 15.2 +/- 5.3 min. The majority of respondents thought the questions were clear and easy to answer, and most enjoyed filling in the survey. Collecting large personal networks can mean a significant burden to respondents, but through the use of visual elements in the survey, it is clear that it can be done within reasonable time, with enjoyment and without much non-response.
WOS:000591504600006
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="89">
<title>Does the -measure make empirical sense? A vignette experiment on humans' judgment of social dominance</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.02.002</url>
<snippet>Dominance hierarchies play an important role in governing the social interactions of humans and other species of social animals. In a social group, dominance relations can be inferred from the directed network of matchups between actors. Methodologists have proposed different ways to measure social dominance in directed networks. One such measure, the "beta-measure" (van den Brink and Gilles, 2000), emphasizes the quality of defeated opponents in a way that an actor is seen as being more dominant when s/he defeats opponents who are more rarely defeated. While insightful in theory, the validity of the measure in peoples perception remains questionable, considering the cognitive complexity imposed by this measure, compared to a simpler measure that merely counts the number of defeated opponents. We conducted a vignette experiment with human subjects (professional athletes) to test their judgments of the dominance relation in a hypothetical tournament. Fitting our parametric model to peoples evaluations in the experiment, we found strong evidence in support of the beta-measure: Although, in general, contestants who win more in the tournament are regarded as being more dominant, the contents of the winning records matter, such that those who beat more victorious opponents are further regarded as more dominant than those who defeat less victorious opponents. We also found a gender difference, in that men have a stronger propensity than women to adopt the beta-measure when judging social dominance.
WOS:000527272000005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="90">
<title>Peer influence, friend selection, and gender: How network processes shape adolescent smoking, drinking, and delinquency</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2018.05.008</url>
<snippet>We examine gender differences in the extent to which the social network processes of peer influence and friend selection explain why adolescents tend to exhibit similar risky behaviors as their friends for three problem behaviors (smoking, drinking, and delinquency). Using dynamic Stochastic Actor-Oriented Models (SAOMs), we analyze five waves of data on a large sample of 13,214 adolescents from 51 friendship networks. While both processes explain patterns of risky activities for girls and boys, the delinquent behavior of girls is more susceptible to influence and girls are especially likely to select friends who have similar smoking behaviors to their own. (C) 2018 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000444666300009
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="91">
<title>The social ecology of intergenerational closure in school class networks. Socio-spatial conditions of parents' norm generation and their effects on students' interpersonal conflicts</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.12.009</url>
<snippet>In this paper, we investigate how protective effects of intergenerational closure correspond with conflict networks in school classes. Taking a multilevel ecological perspective, we also consider networks socio-spatial conditions. In a first step, we use ERGMs to analyze the association between parental contact and students friendship ties, i.e., intergenerational closure (IC). Then, we utilize spatial regressions to analyze direct and moderating effects of a schools neighborhood on conflicts in the 135 German class networks (N = 3143 student measurements). In accordance with Colemans theoretical notions, we find consistent negative effects of IC on the (standardized) density of the conflict networks. Moreover, we show that ICs impact is particularly strong in neighborhoods with a relatively high concentration of minorities. The results are in line with our theoretical considerations on multilevel network ecologies and the selective pressure of IC against conflict ties. Practically, our results provide evidence that fostering connections among parents (e.g., by implementing opportunity structures for parents to meet) might help to prevent deviating behavior in schools, especially in neighborhoods with relatively large proportions of ethnic minorities.
WOS:001188886600001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="92">
<title>Class inequalities in access to social capital in the metropolitan area of Buenos Aires</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.09.003</url>
<snippet>this paper analyzes social class inequalities in access to social capital. Quantitative methodology was used with data from the PI-Clases "Reproduction and social mobility in family trajectories and life courses " survey, con-ducted in the Metropolitan Area of Buenos Aires in 2015 (n = 1065). Social capital measures where derived from the Position Generator (Lin, 2001) to identify the volume, status and range of the respondents networks. Results show that there are class inequalities in access to social capital in terms of the number of contacts, mean status of contacts, range of contacts status and highest status of contacts. Also, the working class is more heterogeneous in its access to social capital, suggesting it has a sector that has network ties with people from the middle class and a sector with lower social capital. The observed trend is of gradational differences between class strata, with more marked inequalities between the service, intermediate and working class, but with fluid class boundaries without social segregation. Also, social capital is conditioned by intergenerational mobility trajectory, showing a trend of elasticity in the class composition of social relationships. The upwardly mobile can increase their access to social capital but dont reach the same level as the intergenerationally stable, while the downwardly mobile retain some social capital from their class origins.
WOS:000861598500004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="93">
<title>Predicting data quality of proxy reports in egocentric network studies</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.01.007</url>
<snippet>Egocentric network studies and many general population surveys rely on proxy reports about network contacts of study participants that are asked in name interpreter questions. A central concern is the extent to which proxy reports match the answers these contacts would give themselves if they would be directly interviewed. Based on the theory of survey satisficing, the present research proposes a theoretical framework that allows predicting when proxy reports are likely to match self-reports. Congruence is higher if respondents possess the motivation and ability to answer a proxy question effortfully, and if the task is not too difficult. Moreover, the theory of survey satisficing states that motivation, abilities, and task difficulty are not independent of each other, which provides an explanation for inconsistent findings in the literature. Results from two egocentric network studies study among German adults (N = 756) and among Dutch middle school students (N = 679), in which network contacts were also interviewed, are in line with these hypotheses. Design recommendations for egocentric network studies are provided.
WOS:000648645200004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="94">
<title>How new is "New"? Who gets added in a panel study of personal networks?</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.02.011</url>
<snippet>Using longitudinal data from UCNets, we examined newly-listed alters and distinguished between truly new ties who were recently met (typically coworkers and acquaintances) and awakened ties who were previously known to ego (typically extended kin and friends). Half of the newly-listed ties among the younger respondents were truly new, whereas two-thirds among the older respondents were awakened. In both groups, however, most alters were previously listed. These ties mainly included kin, confidants, and advisors, suggesting stability in the network core. Methodological implications for the name-generating process and substantive implications for the understanding of network dynamics and structure are discussed.
WOS:000819930800016
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="95">
<title>Effects of smartphone use and recall aids on network name generator questions</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.06.006</url>
<snippet>The increasing use of smartphones around the world provides new opportunities for network data collection using smartphone surveys. We investigated experimentally whether the use of smartphones and of a recall aid affects the number of reported names in a network name generator question. In a German online access panel (N = 3891), respondents were randomly assigned to answer the survey on their PC or on their smartphone and were randomly assigned to receive an open-ended recall aid question before the name generator question or after. Results showed that respondents on PCs and smartphones reported the same number of network contacts. This suggests that smartphone surveys have no negative effect on the network sizes in ego-centered network studies. However, requiring people to answer on smartphones resulted in a selection bias due to non-compliance, which may have led to an overrepresentation of persons with larger network sizes. The recall aid question did not lead to more reported names, but it proved to be an indicator of respondents motivation and response quality. In sum, the study suggests that smartphones can effectively be used for network research in tech-savvy populations or when respondents can choose to complete the survey on another device.
WOS:000777556900006
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="96">
<title>Persistence and change in structural signatures of tie formation over time</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.12.001</url>
<snippet>Using data on the formation of Facebook friendships from over 100,000 students at the 1141 four-year colleges and universities in the Department of Education Scorecard dataset, we examine whether students tendencies to form more open or closed relations (their closure "signature") persist as they leave high school and attend college, and whether this varies by the type of institution attended. Despite significant persistence of individual signature, for the case of Facebook friendships, individuals do tend to adopt the closure signature that characterizes their school. Contrary to expectation, students at more selective colleges are more, not less, likely to form friends with those with whom they share more friends. Yet, at the crucial time of transition to a new school, they form more open ties, due to the tendency of very popular students to reach out to those they generally would not form ties with.
WOS:001188870300001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="97">
<title>Network formation in organizational settings: Exploring the importance of local social processes and team-level contextual variables in small groups using bayesian hierarchical ERGMs</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.07.001</url>
<snippet>Statistical models for social networks, such as exponential random graphs (ERGMs), have increasingly been used by organizational scholars to study the social interactions inside organizations, departments, and teams. While such models have been successful in providing insights about the local processes that underlie these interactions (such as homophily, reciprocity or transitivity), an additional interesting avenue for research focuses on the role of group -level contextual variables (such as the climate or composition of a team or organization) when considering a multitude of teams or organizations. In this paper we show how, in a team context, integrating team -level factors in a multilevel framework (i.e., a Bayesian hierarchical ERGM) enables us to answer questions about: 1) how team -level contextual factors might provide alternative explanations for the emergence of intra-team ties, and 2) whether any variation in local tendencies between teams might be dependent on such team -level variables (i.e., cross -level interactions). Using data collected among 103 MBA students who were grouped into 18 teams of 5-7 members to work on a project, we study the impact of members expertise and perceived psychological safety on advice seeking behavior. At a local level, we focus on the effect of these nodal attributes for homophily and differences in advice seeking and giving, while at the team level we incorporate the average expertise and the teams psychological safety climate. Our results show that expert members are more likely to be the recipient of advice ties, but also that this effect is more pronounced in teams where the overall level of expertise is high. For psychological safety, we find that a high psychological safety climate impacts the advice relations among all members in the group, not solely those who themselves perceive a high level of psychological safety, suggesting that the team climate has an impact on all its members. This illustrates how a Bayesian hierarchical ERGM allows us to obtain relevant results even when studying small -sized groups.
WOS:001188361400001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="98">
<title>The evolution of the board interlock network following Sarbanes-Oxley</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2017.05.005</url>
<snippet>We examine the impact of the passage of Sarbanes-Oxley (SOX) on the evolution of the board interlock network for Fortune 300 firms during the 1998-2006 period using a stochastic actor-oriented model. Placing particular emphasis on director accountability and board independence, SOX created considerable disparity in demand and supply in the labor market for corporate directors. We examine whether the regulatory change may have led firms to draw more on socially embedded processes of board interlock partner selection such as reciprocity, transitivity, and multiplexity after SOX. We find that after the passage of SOX, a firms tendency to reciprocate board interlock ties has been reinforced. Similarly, firms appear to have relied more on their existing alliance partners to fill their board seats in the post-SOX period. (C) 2017 Published by Elsevier B.V.
WOS:000416496300007
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="99">
<title>Assessing the performance of the bootstrap in simulated assemblage networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.11.005</url>
<snippet>Archaeologists are increasingly interested in networks constructed from site assemblage data, in which weighted network ties reflect sites' assemblage similarity. Equivalent networks would arise in other scientific fields where actors' similarity is assessed by comparing distributions of observed counts, so the assemblages studied here can represent other kinds of distributions in other domains. One concern with such work is that sampling variability in the assemblage network and, in turn, sampling variability in measures calculated from the network must be recognized in any comprehensive analysis. In this study, we investigated the use of the bootstrap as a means of estimating sampling variability in measures of assemblage networks. We evaluated the performance of the bootstrap in simulated assemblage networks, using a probability structure based on the actual distribution of sherds of ceramic wares in a region with 25 archaeological sites. Results indicated that the bootstrap was successful in estimating the true sampling variability of eigenvector centrality for the 25 sites. This held both for centrality scores and for centrality ranks, as well as the ratio of first to second eigenvalues of the network (similarity) matrix. Findings encourage the use of the bootstrap as a tool in analyses of network data derived from counts.
WOS:000614282000009
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="100">
<title>Negative ties and signed graphs research: Stimulating research on dissociative forces in social networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2019.09.004</url>
<snippet>
WOS:000501619700001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="101">
<title>Networks in lockdown: The consequences of COVID-19 for social relationships and feelings of loneliness</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.08.001</url>
<snippet>This paper studies social network changes during the COVID-19 crisis in the Netherlands and their relation to perceived loneliness for the younger and the older cohorts. Arguments from opportunity theory and social capital theory are used to formulate hypotheses on network changes during the pandemic. Core discussion networks and networks with practical helpers from two representative cohorts (18-35 years of age and 65+ years of age, n = 1342 participants in both waves) during the lockdown in May 2020 are compared with networks of the same respondents in May 2019. We find that networks became smaller and more focused on stronger ties, while weaker ties more often decayed. Feelings of loneliness incsreased on average for all respondents and in particular for those who live alone or have a disadvantaged socioeconomic position. Importantly, the decrease in the number of the practical helper network, that is, decline in relatively weaker ties, affects experiences of loneliness in both groups.
WOS:000847385700001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="102">
<title>Crowdfunding digital platforms: Backer networks and their impact on project outcomes</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.09.005</url>
<snippet>Crowdfunding platforms serve to connect project creators and backers. Previous research has explored several project and platform determinants that impact crowdfunding outcomes. However, there has been limited research on these determinants at an individual level. Our paper addresses how backers may influence the outcomes of projects in crowdfunding platforms. We explore several methods commonly used in the industry to identify influence and show that centrality measures through a backer affiliation network best exemplifies in-fluence. Using data from Kickstarter, we construct a weighted backer network based on 52,678 common projects backed by 11,134 backers. Controlling for digital media mentions and project quality, we find evidence that backers in central positions within the network have a positive impact on multiple project outcomes such as the project success rates, amount of funds raised, speed of reaching the crowdfunding goal as well as the number of backers contributing to the project. These findings are replicated and reinforced by using data from a different crowdfunding platform using the entire backer network based on 1095 projects backed by 87,896 backers. Several robustness tests are used to validate these results.
WOS:000591504700004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="103">
<title>The free encyclopedia that anyone can dispute: An analysis of the micro-structural dynamics of positive and negative relations in the production of contentious Wikipedia articles</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2018.12.003</url>
<snippet>We consider two rival hypotheses on the emergence of organization in open production communities. According to the first ("reputation hypothesis"), patterns of agreement and disagreement among participants in open production communities are explained by differences in individual reputation for quality of contribution. The reputation hypothesis predicts that participants will tend to agree with more reputable others and disagree with less reputable others thus contributing to establish a stable open production community. According to the second hypothesis ("balance hypothesis"), patterns of agreement and disagreement are explained by membership in sub-communities of "friends" and "enemies." The balance hypothesis predicts that participants in open production communities will agree mainly with friends and disagree mainly with enemies, regardless of considerations about reputation for the quality of their contributions. In this paper, we examine which one of these hypotheses is more consistent with patterns of positive and negative interaction events observed during the production of the complete set of 1,206 English-language Wikipedia articles officially considered controversial. We specify and estimate new models for signed and weighted relational event networks predicting the probability that a user deletes the contributions of another user - thus expressing personal disagreement - and/or protects the contributions of another user against deletion from third parties - thus expressing personal agreement. In an analysis of positive and negative interaction among Wikipedia contributors consisting of more than 60 million observations, we find strong support for the balance hypothesis and for the predictions of the reputation hypothesis that are more consistent with alter-centric interpretations of social status as conferred by alters through observable acts of deference.
WOS:000501619700002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="104">
<title>Bullying and victimization among majority and minority students: The role of peers' ethnic perceptions</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2018.08.006</url>
<snippet>In this study, we investigate the associations between self-reported and victim-reported bullying and two dimensions of ethnicity (self-identification and ethnic perceptions) among non-Roma majority and Roma minority Hungarian secondary school students. Results of the meta-analysis of exponential random graph models for 12 classes (347 students, 4 schools) show that both self-declared Roma and non-Roma students are more likely to report that they bully peers they perceive as Roma compared to peers they perceive as non-Roma. This is after controlling for gender, socio-economic status, and structural characteristics of the bullying networks. Similar associations have not been found, however, analysing victims reports.
WOS:000501619700005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="105">
<title>The way bullying works: How new ties facilitate the mutual reinforcement of status and bullying in elementary schools</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2018.12.006</url>
<snippet>This study addresses the puzzle how high-status bullies in elementary school are able to maintain high status among their classmates despite bullying (some of) them. The dynamic interplay between bullying and status was studied, focusing on how relational bullying affects the creation, dissolution, and maintenance of status attributions, and vice versa. Longitudinal round-robin peer nomination data were obtained from 82 school classes in 15 Dutch elementary schools (2055 students; 50&#37; boys) followed over three yearly measurements, starting out in grades 2-5 when students were aged 8-11. An age-dependent effect of bullying on the creation of new status attributions was found. Whereas the youngest group punished bullying by a refusal to attribute status to the bully, this turned into a reward of bullying in the oldest groups. Unexpectedly, high-status bullies seemed to avoid continual bullying of the same victims, pointing to explanations of why their status can persist.
WOS:000501619700007
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="106">
<title>Triadic balance in the brain: Seeking brain evidence for Heider's structural balance theory</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.05.003</url>
<snippet>Structural balance theory is a foundational theory of social network research. Despite enduring interest in seeking network evidence for the theory, the fundamental question of why people care about structural (im) balance has received relatively little attention. The original answer to the question, dating back to Heiders work six decades ago, is that structural imbalance causes a person to experience cognitive dissonance and sentimental disturbance. In this paper, we used a state-of-the-art neuroimaging technique to test the argument. Our study shows that individuals psychological states, evidenced by the activation of brain areas, are different when they are situated in unbalanced rather than balanced triads. More specifically, the differences in the brain activation between triadic imbalance and balance were found in brain regions known for processing cognitive dissonance, as discovered by previous research. Our study provides novel brain evidence in support of Heiders original account for the psychological and biological foundations of structural balance theory in the formation of social networks.
WOS:000563919700008
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="107">
<title>Partitioning signed networks using relocation heuristics, tabu search, and variable neighborhood search</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2018.08.007</url>
<snippet>Recently, there have been significant advancements in the development of exact methods and metaheuristics for partitioning signed networks. The metaheuristic advancements have led commonly to adverse implications for multiple restart (multistart) relocation heuristics for these networks. Most notably, it has been reported that multistart relocation heuristics are not computationally feasible for large signed networks with thousands or tens of thousands of vertices. In this paper, we show that combining multistart relocation heuristics with tabu search or variable neighborhood search can rapidly produce partitions of the vertices of signed networks that are competitive with those obtained using existing metaheuristics.
WOS:000454966400007
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="108">
<title>Contextualizing oppositional cultures: The variable significance of gender and ethnic minority status across schools</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.11.004</url>
<snippet>Different lines of research have argued that specific groups, such as boys or ethnic minorities, are more prone to develop an anti-school culture than others, leading to group differences in the social acceptance of high performers. Taking an ecological view, we ask to what extent the school context promotes or prevents the emergence of group-specific oppositional cultures. Theoretically, we argue that group-based oppositional cultures become more likely in schools with low socio-economic resources and in schools where socio-economic differences align with demographic attributes. We test our hypotheses based on data from a large-scale, four-wave network panel survey among more than 4000 students in Germany. Applying stochastic actor-oriented models for the coevolution of networks and behavior, we find that group-based oppositional cultures in which students like high performers less are very rare. However, in line with theoretical expectations, the less resourceful a school is, the more boys tend to evaluate high-performing peers less positively than girls do. Moreover, the more ethnic minority boys are socioeconomically disdvantaged in a school, the more they tend to evaluate high performers less positively than majority boys do.
WOS:000724026400002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="109">
<title>Organizational practices and workplace relationships in precarious work: New survey evidence</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.10.003</url>
<snippet>Organizational practices are important dimensions of the social contexts that shape relationship formation. In workplaces, the formation of relationships among coworkers are resources for personal outcomes, and they can be channels through which workers might identify common grievances, form workplace solidarity, and engage in collective action. Using a unique dataset of retail workers across the United States from the Shift Project, this paper examines two potential pathways by which organizational practices common in the retail industry in the U.S. might shape the formation of workplace relationships. I find evidence of the role of both pathways: practices that limit the opportunities for regular contact and practices that negatively impact the conditions of contact among employees are both associated with fewer workplace ties. I discuss the implications of these findings for the study of collective action and network ecology.
WOS:001188960200001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="110">
<title>The Emergence and Stability of Groups in Social Networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2019.10.008</url>
<snippet>An important puzzle in social network research is to explain how macro-level structures emerge from micro-level network processes. Explaining the emergence and stability of structural groups in social networks is particularly difficult for two reasons. First, because groups are characterized both by high connectedness within (group cohesion) and lack of connectedness between them (group boundaries). Second, because a large number of theoretical micro-level network processes contribute to their emergence. We argue that traditional social network theories that are concerned with the evolution of positive relations (forces of attraction) are not sufficient to explain the emergence of groups because they lack mechanisms explaining the emergence of group boundaries. Models that additionally account for the evolution of negative ties (forces of repulsion) may be better suited to explain the emergence and stability of groups. We build a theoretical model and illustrate its usefulness by fitting stochastic actor-oriented models (SAOMs) to empirical data of co-evolving networks of friendship and dislike among 479 secondary-school students. The SAOMs include a number of newly developed effects expressing the co-evolution between positive and negative ties. We then simulate networks from the estimated models to explore the micro-macro link. We find that a model that considers forces of attraction and repulsion simultaneously is better at explaining groups in social networks. In the long run, however, the empirically informed simulations generate networks that are too stylized to be realistic, raising further questions about model degeneracy and time heterogeneity of group processes.
WOS:000501619700011
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="111">
<title>Structural balance across the strait: A behavioral experiment on the transitions of positive and negative intergroup relationships in mainland China and Taiwan</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2018.07.003</url>
<snippet>Structural balance theory explains how ties are formed in signed networks. A balanced triad, however, could be incidentally caused by balance-unrelated mechanisms. Teasing apart the multiple mechanisms that lead to balanced networks helps clarify the explanatory power of a theory. In a behavioral experiment, we investigated the transition of intergroup relations across the positive/negative boundary. Voluntary participants, recruited from mainland China and Taiwan, were placed in triadic networks, each facing two alters. We manipulated the attributes and relationships of the alters to examine how people adjust their relationships. Our experiment shows that people are more likely to change from behaving negatively to positively to an alter when they know the alter is negatively treated by the other alter. Conversely, people are more likely to change from behaving positively to negatively to an alter when they know the alter negatively treats the other alter. Beyond these effects, people are more likely to turn from positive to negative and vice versa to an alter when doing so achieves structural balance in a triad. Our study provides new experimental evidence for the structural balance theory in predicting the formation of signed networks when other conflating mechanisms are controlled for.
WOS:000454966400001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="112">
<title>Predicting data quality of proxy reports in egocentric network studies (Reprinted from vol 66, pages 38-49, 2021)</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.01.007</url>
<snippet>Egocentric network studies and many general population surveys rely on proxy reports about network contacts of study participants that are asked in name interpreter questions. A central concern is the extent to which proxy reports match the answers these contacts would give themselves if they would be directly interviewed. Based on the theory of survey satisficing, the present research proposes a theoretical framework that allows predicting when proxy reports are likely to match self-reports. Congruence is higher if respondents possess the motivation and ability to answer a proxy question effortfully, and if the task is not too difficult. Moreover, the theory of survey satisficing states that motivation, abilities, and task difficulty are not independent of each other, which provides an explanation for inconsistent findings in the literature. Results from two egocentric network studies study among German adults (N = 756) and among Dutch middle school students (N = 679), in which network contacts were also interviewed, are in line with these hypotheses. Design recommendations for egocentric network studies are provided.
WOS:000777028500008
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="113">
<title>Exploring small-world network with an elite-clique: Bringing embeddedness theory into the dynamic evolution of a venture capital network</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2018.11.002</url>
<snippet>This paper uses a network dynamics model to explain the formation of a small-world network with an elite-clique. This network is a small-world network with an elite-clique at its center in which elites are also the centers of many small groups. These leaders also act as bridges between different small groups. Network dynamics are an important research topic due to their ability to explain the evolution of network structures. In this paper, a Chinese Venture Capital (VC) network was coded from joint investments between VC firms and then analyzed to uncover its network properties and factors that influence its evolution. We first built a random graph model to control for factors such as network scale, network growth, investment frequency and syndication tendency. Then we added a partner-selection mechanism and used two theories to analyze the formation of network structure: relational embeddedness and structural embeddedness. After that, we ran simulations and compared the three models with the actual Chinese VC network. To do this we computed the elite-cliques EI index, degree distribution, clustering coefficient distribution and motifs. Results show that adding embeddedness theories significantly improved the network dynamic models predictive power, and help us uncover the mechanisms that affect the formation of a small-world industrial network with an elite-clique at its center.
WOS:000458224300007
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="114">
<title>Social distance in France: Evolution of homogeneity within personal networks from 2001 to 2017</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.05.001</url>
<snippet>This article explores the evolution of homogeneity within personal networks in France over time and across several relational contexts, using two cross-sectional surveys conducted in 2001 (n = 399) and 2017 (n = 663). Personal networks have changed relatively little overall, but with a tendency toward more homogeneity among the most educated, 26-45 and 61-75 year-olds, singles, and childless individuals. Differences in rates of personal network homogeneity are only partly explained by demographic shifts in French society. These findings are mostly consistent with those of other studies in Hungary and the USA. We argue that the effects of rising education levels, the segmentation of social contexts in terms of age, and the transformation of family models - which can be observed in most western countries - reinforce relational spheres characterized by relatively similar lifestyles.
WOS:000700623500006
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="115">
<title>Farm size shapes friend choice amongst rice producers in China: Some evidence for the theory of network ecology'</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2019.10.001</url>
<snippet>Multiple dynamics jointly determine who we befriend, however, researchers have failed to systematically assess which processes matter most under different circumstances. Here I draw on observations around how the demands of paddy rice cultivation shape social interaction to demonstrate that the relative importance of reciprocity, transitivity and generalised exchange to who rice producers choose as friends varies with the amount of agricultural land under their control. In doing so, I use unique data on farm size and friendship amongst 4713 rice-growing smallholders in 162 rural villages in Jiangxi, China along with a new technique for measuring the relative importance of effects in Stochastic Actor-Oriented Models. In line with the micro-level component of the recently advanced "theory of network ecology", results suggest that features of an individuals proximal environment can powerfully moderate the relative expression of network-formation mechanisms such that for some individuals, a dynamic may be expected to hold substantial sway over the process of choosing social contacts and, for others, no sway at all.
WOS:000512481500010
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="116">
<title>Structure of personal networks and cognitive abilities: A study on a sample of Italian older adults</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2023.02.005</url>
<snippet>Research in social gerontology has suggested that structural complexity of personal networks could moderate cognitive decline of older adults. In line with the environmental complexity hypothesis, their cognitive functioning would benefit from a high number of cohesive subgroups in their own personal networks, i.e., various social foci, thanks to higher cognitive stimuli from various social interactions. Yet, past studies considered only compositional diversity of networks due to lack of data on alter-alter ties. To fill this gap, we collected survey ego-network data on frequent social contacts (including alter-alter ties) and cognitive functioning on a sample of individuals aged &gt;= 75 in Brescia, Italy (N = 230). As a proxy for social foci, we detected cohesive subgroups within each respondents personal networks. Results showed a positive association between the number of cohesive subgroups and cognitive functioning, regardless of the network size, while controlling for relevant socio-demographic attributes and depression symptoms. Our findings testify to the importance of granular network data in studying the link between social relationships and cognitive functioning.
WOS:000948568000001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="117">
<title>Whom do we lose? The case of dissimilarity in personal networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.11.003</url>
<snippet>Previous research finds that individuals tend to form ties with similar others much more often than with dissimilar others. However, we know relatively little about tie loss and to what extent this is driven by (dis)similarity. In this paper, we argue that ties to persons who are dissimilar with regard to gender, age, ethnicity, and education are lost faster than ties to similar persons - and we test three explanations for this faster decay of ties with dissimilar others: lack of meeting opportunities, preferences for similarity, and lower network embeddedness. To test these explanations, we analysed two waves of the Survey on the Social Networks of the Dutch (SSND, 2007, 2014). These SSND-waves contain comprehensive longitudinal panel data on ego networks of 441 respondents, who were interviewed about a wide range of relationships, their alters' sociodemographic characteristics, where and when they met their alters, as well as how and whether they maintain these relationships. We modelled tie loss by event history analyses. Results show that ties to persons who were dissimilar are more likely to be lost faster, and that tie loss occurs mostly in the early years of a relationship. However, meeting opportunities, preferences for similarity, and network embeddedness are unable to explain why ties to dissimilar others are lost faster. We conclude that dissimilarity is a powerful driver of tie loss, and that more arguments and research are needed to fully understand the underlying mechanisms.
WOS:000614282000005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="118">
<title>Avoidance in action: Negative tie closure in balanced triads among pupils over time</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.03.006</url>
<snippet>We study avoidance tie closure in balance triads among pupils in two Dutch secondary schools using stochastic actor-oriented models (SAOMs). We find that pupils were likely to avoid the friends of those they avoided but not enough evidence is found to either fully accept or refute the idea that pupils disagree with their friends on whom to avoid. Moreover, pupils migration background does not seem to influence avoidance tie closure in balanced triads. Results are discussed in terms of their theoretical implications. Based on our findings, we elaborate on the possibility of a singular balance promoting effect rather than multiple distinct ones. Limitations are pointed out and future research suggestions are offered.
WOS:000798769300002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="119">
<title>Collecting survey-based social network information in work organizations</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.04.003</url>
<snippet>Collecting social network data among organization members using surveys is challenging and requires a well considered strategy. Based on extensive past experience with collecting social network information in work organizations with surveys, we identify and discuss four major elements of the data collection process, all linked with and dependent on the specific research question and objective: 1) negotiating access to the organization; 2) identifying the networks boundary, the relevant formal organizational structures that affect social networks, and the sampling approach; 3) deciding how to approach research subjects and collect network data; and, 4) providing useful and ethically-sensitive feedback to the organization and its members. Decisions on each of these elements and their co-alignment, particularly with respect to the chosen research question, is crucial to a successful study. We offer guidelines and provide examples for each of these elements.
WOS:000700623500003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="120">
<title>Exploring the role of network diversity and resources in relationship to generalized trust in Norway</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.02.002</url>
<snippet>Several studies suggest a positive relationship between social capital and generalized trust. Employing a network understanding of social capital (Lin, 2001), this study questions which aspects of social networks may be linked with generalized trust. It investigates whether the diversity of social networks and the socio-economic status of ones contacts are linked with generalized trust in the Norwegian, egalitarian context. The analyses examine these patterns in relationship to both kin and non-kin contacts. The study employs data from the first Norwegian survey that includes the position generator (PG). The empirical analyses show that extensive social networks are indeed linked to higher levels of generalized trust, but that this relationship is limited to non-kin contacts. Concerning the link between network resources and generalized trust, there is evidence of a more general association with generalized trust that holds when considering both kin and non-kin contacts. These results are a first step in developing a more nuanced discussion of the mechanisms associated with generalized trust and highlight the importance of employing measures that account for the homophily of networks when investigating their relationship to trust.
WOS:000648645200008
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="121">
<title>Friends, family, and family friends: Predicting friendships of Dutch women</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.10.008</url>
<snippet>Friends are an important source of well-being but people differ in who they consider to be friends. With a unique quantitative test of such differences based on 17,650 social relations of 706 Dutch women (aged 18-41), of whom 40&#37; were considered friends, we examined (a) which kind of personal relations were typically identified as friends (e.g., family, colleague), (b) how this linked to relationship closeness, face-to-face and non-face-to-face contact, and 
WOS:000722628400003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="122">
<title>Does it take &lt;i&gt;three&lt;/i&gt; to dance the Tango? Organizational design, triadic structures and boundary spanning across subunits</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2019.04.002</url>
<snippet>In this paper, we investigate the processes of boundary spanning across subunits within organizational networks. We hypothesize that patterns of advice across organizational subunits are explained by different triadic mechanisms depending on the organizational design of the intra-organizational network. In organizational networks characterized by limited hierarchical differentiation among members and horizontal coordination, we found triadic cyclic closure to be positively associated to boundary spanning across subunits; but when the network reflects an organizational structure with formal hierarchical differentiation among members, then we found triadic transitive closure to be associated to boundary spanning across subunits. We test these predictions in two empirical studies consisting of two organizational networks that differ from each other in organizational design. We adopt a Bayesian approach for exponential random graph models specifically designed for the statistical analysis of interpersonal relationships within and across subgroups or subunits. We suggest that the effects of informal, triadic network configurations on boundary spanning are contingent on formal organizational design.
WOS:000487171000002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="123">
<title>A first look at justice-involved women's egocentric social networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.12.003</url>
<snippet>Despite the prominence of social support research in the offender rehabilitation literature, network methods have yet to be used to extend research beyond core network support to investigate resources accessible to justice-involved individuals from semi-regular interaction partners. This study is the first to apply egocentric (personal) social network methods to assess the composition and structure of justice-involved individuals networks. Using data from in-person interviews with 159 justice-involved women about their 1313 network members, four social layers - core, active peripheral, latent peripheral, and estranged ties - are delineated, described, and compared. Findings indicated: 1) there is an abundance of resources available to women in the intermediate and outer social layers of their networks - active and latent peripheral - that are ignored when scholars exclusively study core network members, 2) Latent peripheral ties (i.e., colleagues) provide access to resources associated with womens correctional needs (i.e., legal advice, employment opportunities), and 3) relationships become decentralized and unstable - in terms of frequency of contact, geographical distance, and emotional closeness from the inner to outer layers. Measuring the outer social layers is critical to identifying relationships that compromise reintegration (i.e., estranged) and altering network configurations to improve access to social capital and social support.
WOS:000819930800006
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="124">
<title>Ethical implications of network data in business and management settings</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.09.001</url>
<snippet>Reflecting on the compilation and analysis of a range of network datasets drawn from our own work and some prominent examples, we consider the ethical challenges in dealing with network data in business and management settings. We argue that the managerial processes that characterize such settings introduce particular ethical sensitivities in the stages of commissioning and research design, and when collecting, analyzing and reporting network data. These sensitivities arise from the imperatives of business, motivations for commissioning network analyses and the legal authority that managers have over employees. We argue that ethical considerations are much more pervasive in business and management network research than in many other fields. In this contribution, we present a range of ethical challenges in network research in business and management settings that arise at several stages of the research process. For each issue identified, we describe the ethical problem and propose mitigation remedies. From this reflection, we suggest guidelines for other researchers to consider when designing research projects in this application area.
WOS:000685648800005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="125">
<title>Name order effects in measuring adolescent social networks using rosters</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2023.07.002</url>
<snippet>Recent studies have found order effects in social network data collection, where later names on a roster receive fewer nominations. Some thus argue for randomizing name orders or sampling peer names for survey rosters. We model order effects as biases in nomination choices and demonstrate observational and experimental methods for assessing these biases and illuminating their mechanisms. Employing these lenses, we find little evidence of order effects on eight sociometric questions in four middle school cohorts over six waves. To inform future work, we investigate aspects of the survey situation that may amplify or attenuate order effects. Analyzing these moderating forces offers guidance for detecting, understanding, and mitigating order effects in future research.
WOS:001062856000001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="126">
<title>Network Canvas: Key decisions in the design of an interviewer-assisted network data collection software suite (Reprinted from vol 66, pages 114-124, 2021)</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.01.006</url>
<snippet>Self-reported social network analysis studies are often complex and burdensome, both during the interview process itself, and when conducting data management following the interview. Through funding obtained from the National Institute on Drug Abuse (NIDA/NIH), our team developed the Network Canvas suite of software - a set of complementary tools that are designed to simplify the collection and storage of complex social network data, with an emphasis on usability and accessibility across platforms and devices, and guided by the practical needs of researchers. The suite consists of three applications: Architect: an application for researchers to design and export interview protocols; Interviewer: a touch-optimized application for loading and administering interview protocols to study participants; and Server: an application for researchers to manage the interview deployment process and export their data for analysis. Together, they enable researchers with minimal tech-nological expertise to access a complete research workflow, by building their own network interview protocols, deploying these protocols widely within a variety of contexts, and immediately attaining the resulting data from a secure central location. In this paper, we outline the critical decisions taken in developing this suite of tools for the network research community. We also describe the work which guides our decision-making, including prior experiences and key discovery events. We focus on key design choices, taken for theoretical, philosophical, and pragmatic reasons, and outline their strengths and limitations.
WOS:000777028500009
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="127">
<title>Cognitive political networks: A structural approach to measure political polarization in multiparty systems</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.05.004</url>
<snippet>While there is a well-established literature on measuring political polarization in two-party systems, relational approaches to polarization in multiparty systems are still very limited. In this paper we develop a network-based approach for measuring perceived party polarization in survey studies that is suitable for multiparty systems. Our approach is based on cognitive social structures design. We generate a cognitive political network for each respondent in a nationally representative survey in Turkey by asking respondents their perceived ties among all possible dyadic relations among major political parties. From these networks we calculate multiple whole network measures that may be reasonable proxies for perceived party polarization. We compare our approach with the Left-Right political ideology distance scale commonly used in survey studies. Our analyses show that the association between our measure and the Left-Right ideological distance is limited. The cognitive political network approach may be a flexible and a direct alternative for measuring political phenomena in survey studies such as perceived party polarization in multiparty contexts.
WOS:000700623500010
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="128">
<title>Networks never rest: An investigation of network evolution in three species of animals</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.09.002</url>
<snippet>Despite considerable advancement in the study of network evolution, three basic limitations are common to the data collected: (1) examining a small number of networks, (2) not observing networks from scratch, (3) not collecting time-stamped, continuous records of all interactions among all members of groups. Here, we avoid these limitations by observing all aggressive interactions leading to network formation from the moment of introduction among all members of 45 groups of four individuals each in three species of animals: chickens, cichlid fish, and mice. We apply several recently developed methods for the visualization and analysis of network evolution to these unique datasets. We discover, first, that network evolution is a remarkably dynamic process across all three species: networks do not evolve to specific structures and then remain in those configurations. Instead, we find dynamic stability in which many groups continually return to a general class of structures. Second, we find considerable similarity across species in the pathways that the groups take through different possible network configurations as they evolve. Third, we show that transitive component triads are more stable than intransitive ones. Fourth, we track the evolution of individual ranks within groups and discover that many individuals do not have stable positions. Finally, we discuss fundamental questions that our findings raise for the study of networks in both animals and humans.
WOS:000707327500001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="129">
<title>Same but different A comparison of estimation approaches for exponential random graph models for multiple networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2023.05.003</url>
<snippet>The Exponential Random Graph family of models (ERGM) is a powerful tool for social science research as it allows for the simultaneous modeling of endogenous network characteristics and exogenous variables such as gender, age, and socioeconomic status. However, a major limitation of ERGM is that it is mainly used for descriptive analysis of a single network. This paper examines two methods for estimating multiple networks: hierarchical and integrated. We contrast the two approaches, evaluate their accuracy and discuss the advantages and drawbacks of each. Furthermore, we make recommendations for future researchers on how to proceed with multiple network analysis depending on various factors such as the number of networks and the hierarchical structure of the data. This research is important as it highlights the need for the analysis of multiple networks in order to gain a more comprehensive understanding of social phenomena and the potential for new discoveries.
WOS:001012428000001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="130">
<title>The civic elite: A network perspective on elite consolidation among community-based organizations, 1998-2016</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.02.006</url>
<snippet>Is an elite consolidating among the leadership of community-based organizations (CBOs) in U.S. cities? Ethnographers identify a privatized turn in urban governance, with some nonprofit civic leaders becoming a cohesive group with enormous influence in local affairs. However, while researchers propose elite consolidation has occurred and created a more hierarchical, technocratic, and unipolar civic field, these structural changes have not been directly assessed. In this paper, I reintroduce an interorganizational network perspective to elite consolidation and evaluate how interlocking directorates among CBOs in Cleveland, OH, and Austin, TX constitute relationships among civic leaders over twenty years. Results indicate boards of directors are constituting a new civic elite, and that hierarchical interlock tendencies doubled in both cities between 1998 and 2016. The core of the networks appear to be organizations traditionally important in urban governance, though, and community analysis reveals power sharing among elite groups in the cities rather than singular dominant communities, indicating as situation of "elitist pluralism." These findings offer a new perspective on the problem of elite consolidation in civil society, and offer a benchmark for future analysis of civic elites.
WOS:000648645200013
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="131">
<title>Disentangling the relation between young immigrants' host country identification and their friendships with natives</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2015.08.001</url>
<snippet>Immigrants who strongly identify with the host country have more native friends than immigrants with weaker host country identification. However, the mechanisms underlying this correlation are not well understood. Immigrants with strong host country identification might have stronger preferences for native friends, or they might be more often chosen as friends by natives. In turn, having native friends or friends with strong host country identification might increase immigrants host country identification. Using longitudinal network data of 18 Dutch school classes, we test these hypotheses with stochastic actor-oriented models. We find that immigrants host country identification affects friendship selections of natives but not of immigrants. We find no evidence of social influence processes. (C) 2015 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000367423900016
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="132">
<title>Accusation and confession discrepancies in bullying: Dual-perspective networks and individual-level attributes</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2019.09.001</url>
<snippet>Previous research on bullying implicitly assumes that individuals agree on who bullies whom and whom is bullied by who. We analyse dual-perspective networks from 96 school-classes in Germany, where adolescents were asked both whom they bully (confession network) and who bullies them (accusation network). Drawing from goal framing theory we explicitly examine discrepancies in the subjective perception of bullying, demonstrating that the majority of accusations have no corresponding confessions, and vice versa. There are more confessions than accusations overall. Furthermore, we investigate how individual-level attributes are associated with these discrepancies. Our study indicates that analyses of bullying relationships, as well as social networks in general, should account for relational discrepancies resulting from individuals subjective perceptions of social behaviour.
WOS:000501619700006
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="133">
<title>Cross-national variation in political network size, distribution, and prediction</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.01.003</url>
<snippet>Network size has a fundamental influence on other network properties. As studies of social network size have accumulated beyond the U.S. and Western Europe, diversity in the networks examined and methods used to construct size estimates have hindered the ability to make direct cross-national comparisons. We employ data from a summary political discussion network size measure in 17 surveys conducted in 15 countries between 2012 and 2018. We offer improved cross-national data on political network size distributions and estimate aggregate and country-specific models to understand the factors, both social and political, that predict political network size within countries.
WOS:000648645200009
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="134">
<title>Categorical closure: Transitivity and identities in longitudinal networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2024.06.004</url>
<snippet>This research examines whether categorical closure - an increased tendency for closure in homogeneous triads - matters for tie formation and tie persistence. We utilized 2019-2020 panel data on students networks at three law schools and employed separable temporal exponential random graph models to examine whether closed triads with shared identities were more likely to form and to persist over time. We also investigated whether closed triads based on shared organizational assignments were associated with lower likelihoods of tie formation and tie persistence over time. Results supported the notion that law students were more likely to form homogeneous closed triads based on shared categories, particularly family background, gender, and race, while closed triads based on organizational assignments were less likely. Closed triads tended to persist over time, but there was some support for the notion that homogeneous closed triads based on family background, college rank, and sexuality were more durable. This study highlights categorical closure as an additional network mechanism giving rise to homogenous groups.
WOS:001264836000001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="135">
<title>Multiple types of friends and life stage differences in friendship</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.06.001</url>
<snippet>Much research on the life-course measures friend ties using a single aspect of relationships. This measurement has enabled the delineation of friendship networks and the application of rigorous network analysis tools, but at the expense of neglecting the multidimensionality of friendships. As an alternative, this study suggests identi-fying and differentiating multiple types of friends based on friendships multifaceted nature. Analysis using the University of California, Berkeley, Social Networks Survey demonstrates that both young (20-30-year-old) and older (50-70-year-old) people have four distinct types of friends. The conventional "close and supportive friends" or "new friends" only account for half the friendship types. In addition, younger people, particularly married and low-income ones, have friends with whom they do not actively interact, despite the intimacy, proximity, and long tenure of the relationships. Among older people, many friends are not emotionally close despite knowing each other for a long time and living nearby. This type of friendship constitutes a higher proportion in sparse networks and the networks of married, retired, low-income, and non-white older adults. The age group differ-ences in friend types and their distribution are discussed, focusing on different social foci for friend activities between young and older adults.
WOS:000861374000002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="136">
<title>Moral bureaucracies and social network research</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2019.11.001</url>
<snippet>In the wake of Europes General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR), research ethics governance does not just affect the ethical dimensions of social research but also the range of scientific decisions available to researchers. Because of the sensitive status of personal data and the aversion to even minimal risk by what we call "moral bureaucracies", we are concerned that social network researchers will increasingly limit their research decisions to "safe" options, like reusing anonymized datasets, choosing target populations based on convenience rather than theoretical relevance, and routinely subcontracting fieldwork to professional data collection companies, among others. We also suggest that scientific associations and social scientists in general need to adopt a proactive role in preserving both scientific freedom and genuine ethics advice within this new regulatory framework.
WOS:000685648800003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="137">
<title>Does syndicating bring syndicating ?An exploration targeting ECF based on social structure by complex network analysis</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.02.008</url>
<snippet>This paper deploys an abductive reasoning process to explore the ECF investors co-investing preference based on previous online ties, drawing on 7417 investment records for 1355 investors. Based on the BGLL algorithm and Dunbar-Law, we trace the formation of co-investing relationships based on dynamic changes of sub-network. The results show how co-investing preferences of investors arise from the dependency they developed through cooperative behaviors over time. By relating two co-investing preferences to two kinds of community structures, the findings suggest that heterogeneous connections in a hierarchical structure are more stable and sustainable than homogeneous connections not based on strong ties within a decentralized structure. This work presents a dynamic network perspective in examining the relationship between the previous co-investing and following co-investing, enriches the research on the historical dependence in social behavior, and adds new knowledge to ECF investors co-investing preference and ECF practice.
WOS:000819930800012
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="138">
<title>Validation of interaction-based egocentric elicitation using ecological momentary assessment with young adults currently or formerly homeless</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2023.01.002</url>
<snippet>Introduction: Social network changes are common as individuals transition from homeless to Supportive Housing. Egocentric approaches to elicit network members have been utilized with young adults experiencing homelessness to better understand such socio-environmental contexts; however, such approaches are subject to recall bias. Momentary measurements of ones social network via Ecological Momentary Assessment (EMA) can support in understanding the accuracy of egocentric elicitation methods.Objective: To examine who is elicited using an interaction-based approach in egocentric social network analysis among currently homeless and formerly homeless young adults residing in Supportive Housing and explore which alters are reported in interactions and how often are they reported when egocentric network analysis is embedded in EMA.Methods: The present study utilizes interaction-based elicitation embedded within Ecological Momentary Assessment (EMA) in two sub-samples: currently homeless young adults (n = 72) and formerly homeless young adults residing in Supportive Housing (n = 118). Results: Most egos interacted with three of their top five alters, while only 8.9&#37; interacted with all five. Conversely, only 2&#37; of egos reported that they did not interact with any of their top five. Several differences in alter characteristics were identified by housing status. Alters indicated as being more supportive are elicited first and alters elicited first are interacted with the most.Conclusions: EMA findings suggest that a cross-sectional social network survey of top five alters will results in an ordered list, with the most important/frequent alter being named first and trend downward. Results have implications for future study design involving egocentric network analyses. Present findings indicate qualities of alters present and thus, offer plausible "best practices" when utilizing network elicitation methods, particularly interaction-based methods.
WOS:000919072500001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="139">
<title>Network recall among older adults with cognitive impairments</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.08.005</url>
<snippet>Although it is widely accepted that personal networks influence health and illness, network recall remains a major concern. This concern is heightened when studying a population that is vulnerable to cognitive decline. Given these issues, we use data from the Social Network in Alzheimer Disease project to explore similarities and discrepancies between the network perceptions of focal participants and study partners. By leveraging data on a sample of older adults with normal cognition, mild cognitive impairment, and early stage dementia, we explore how cognitive impairment influences older adults perceptions of their personal networks. We find that the average individual is more likely to omit weaker, peripheral ties from their self-reported networks than stronger, central ties. Despite observing only moderate levels of focal-partner corroboration across our sample, we find minimal evidence of perceptual differences across diagnostic groups. We offer two broad conclusions. First, self-reported network data, though imperfect, offer a reasonable account of the core people in ones life. Second, our findings assuage concerns that cognitively impaired older adults have skewed perceptions of their personal networks.
WOS:000591504600009
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="140">
<title>Random sampling of alters from networks: A promising direction in egocentric network research</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.09.004</url>
<snippet>The social network perspective has great potential for advancing knowledge of social mechanisms in many fields. However, collecting egocentric (i.e., personal) network data is costly and places a heavy burden on respondents. This is especially true of the task used to elicit information on ties between network members (i.e., alter-alter ties or density matrix), which grows exponentially in length as network size increases. While most existing national surveys circumvent this problem by capping the number of network members that can be named, this strategy has major limitations. Here, we apply random sampling of network members to reduce cost, respondent burden, and error in network studies. We examine the effectiveness and reliability of random sampling in simulated and real-world egocentric network data. We find that in estimating sample/population means of network measures, randomly selecting a small number of network members produces only minor errors, regardless of true network size. For studies that use network measures in regressions, randomly selecting the mean number of network members (e.g., randomly selecting 10 alters when mean network size is 10) is enough to recover estimates of network measures that correlate close to 1 with those of the full sample. We conclude with recommendations for best practices that will make this versatile but resource intensive methodology accessible to a wider group of researchers without sacrificing data quality.
WOS:000861598500003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="141">
<title>From support to overload: Patterns of positive and negative family relationships of adults with mental illness over time</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2016.04.002</url>
<snippet>Family relationships account for much of the support available to individuals with mental illness. Although some studies have acknowledged the importance of family support, and while others have underlined the harmful effects of negative relationships, research has seldom empirically considered the complex web of positive and negative relationships in family networks. This research hypothesised that social capital has distinct consequences for psychological health depending on the presence or absence of negative family relationships. Through a five-wave follow-up of 60 individuals undergoing psychotherapy in a private practice, the study explored the structural features of positive and negative relationships, considered jointly, in the family networks of adults with mental illness. Four patterns of relationships were found: bonding social capital, bridging social capital, overload and ego-centred conflict. Compared to individuals within a bonding or bridging social capital pattern, those experiencing overload and ego-centred conflict patterns showed higher levels of psychological distress. These results highlight the importance of considering the structural dimensions of positive and negative relationships together to understand the lasting connection between family networks and the psychological health of individuals with mental illness. (C) 2016 The Authors. Published by Elsevier B.V.
WOS:000382592500006
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="142">
<title>Occupational selection and the reliability of position generator measures of social capital</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2024.05.001</url>
<snippet>This article investigates how variation in the social positions (occupations) presented by a position generator (PG) instrument affects the reliability of egocentric network measures based on PG data. We modify the splithalf design employed in Verhaeghe et al.s (2013) study of university students for use with already-existing PG data on a national adult population. After replicating that study, we examine how reliability varies with the relational criterion ( e.g. , friendship) that links an individual to an occupation and with the number of occupations in a PG. We find that most PG measures are only modestly reliable ( i.e. , are relatively sensitive to occupational selection), but our absolute assessment of their reliability (given instrument length) is somewhat more optimistic than that of the prior study. Extensity (the number of positions with which a subject has contact) is the most reliable measure, composition measures based on social class groupings are next, and those that involve socioeconomic standing or prestige scores are least reliable. Deeming someone to be connected to an occupation using an acquaintance criterion yields more reliable measures than requiring a stronger level of connectivity. PG measures based on longer ( i.e. , more occupations) instruments have higher reliability, and projections for longer PGs suggest that including 20 occupations could measure extensity and counts of contacts in some class groupings with adequate reliability; but other class composition measures and all measures involving socioeconomic standing or prestige scores would require 30 or more.
WOS:001255637800001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="143">
<title>Lay theories of networking ability: Beliefs that inhibit instrumental networking</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.01.003</url>
<snippet>While touting the importance of building effective networks, scholars have paid far less attention to why so many people feel so ambivalent or conflicted about instrumental networking, and what can be done to change such attitudes. The present research provides the first empirical test of a novel theory, which argues that people are more likely to disengage from networking if they hold a "fixed theory" of networking ability-believing that how well one networks is fixed or innate rather than learned through effort-which triggers negative attitudes toward moral and instrumental aspects of networking. To test this argument, we first develop and validate a Lay Theory of Networking Ability scale (Study 1) and show that this scale predicts peoples attendance in networking events over a 6-week period (Study 2). Next, we show that lay theories can be experimentally manipulated, with consequences for attendance in networking events over a 4-week period (Study 3) as well as peoples affective experiences in networking events (Study 4). In all, the present research contributes to our understanding of the motivational psychology of networking by highlighting the importance of beliefs as an understudied construct in the networks literature and by introducing methods to measure and manipulate them.
WOS:000527272000001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="144">
<title>Participant engagement in environmentally focused social network research</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.01.005</url>
<snippet>Environmentally focused social network analysis (Env. SNA) has increasingly benefited from engagement, which refers to the process of incorporating the individuals, organizations, actors, stakeholders or other study participants into the research process. Research about engagement in the wider field of environmental management shows that successful engagement often requires significant planning and exchange among researchers and stakeholders. While there is no one size fits all approach, several important guiding principles have been established. To date, this engagement literature has not focused specifically on SNA, even though several examples of engaged SNA exist in the literature and point to some specific challenges to engagement when working with relational data. Drawing upon data from a survey of researchers who have incorporated engagement into Env. SNA, we focus specifically on the goals, scope, effectiveness, benefits and challenges of doing engaged Env. SNA research. We additionally highlight four case studies and demonstrate that researchers and participants find engagement to be a valuable experience with benefits in the researchers understanding of the context and meaning of their findings. Finally, we provide recommendations to scholars looking to embark on engaged Env. SNA research.
WOS:000648645200011
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="145">
<title>A sign of the times? Weak and strong polarization in the US Congress, 1973-2016</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2018.07.007</url>
<snippet>Claims that the United States Congress is (becoming more) polarized are widespread, but what is polarization? In this paper, I draw on notions of intergroup relations to distinguish two forms. Weak polarization occurs when relations between the polarized groups are merely absent, while strong polarization occurs when the relations between the polarized groups are negative. I apply the Stochastic Degree Sequence Model to data on bill cosponsorship in both the U.S. House of Representatives and U.S. Senate, from 1973 (93rd session) to 2016 (114th session) to infer a series of signed networks of political relationships among legislators, which I then use to answer two research questions. First, can the widely reported finding of increasing weak polarization in the U.S. Congress be replicated when using a statistical model to make inferences about when positive political relations exist? Second, is the (increasing) polarization observed in the U.S. Congress only weak polarization, or is it strong polarization? I find that both chambers exhibit both weak and strong polarization, that both forms are increasing, and that they are structured by political party affiliation. However, I also find these trends are unrelated to which party holds the majority in a chamber.
WOS:000501619700009
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="146">
<title>You said, they said: A framework on informant accuracy with application to studying self-reports and peer-reports</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.12.006</url>
<snippet>Informants have been used extensively to provide information on others. However, informant accuracy has rarely been systematically studied. In this paper I argue that studying informant accuracy both helps deepen our understanding about how perceptions of others are configured by personal and network factors and helps develop better methods to use informant reports to correct self-reporting bias. I propose a framework (a systematic conceptualization) that links informant accuracy to not only informant characteristics, but also alter characteristics, dyadic characteristics shared by the informant and the alter, and characteristics of the behavior being reported on. I apply the framework to analyzing self-reports and peer-reports of smoking among 4094 middle school students in China. The analyses present novel strategies to validate a behavior when the truth is unknown, confirm previous findings (e.g., central informants are more accurate) and elaborate selected mechanisms, reveal new findings, and show the distinctive logics of identifying the presence versus the absence of a behavior. The results also indicate that weighting informant reports by informants network centrality can more effectively correct self-reporting bias. Lastly, I discuss the implications of this study for various practices, ranging from health monitoring to online rating.
WOS:000819930800008
</snippet>
</document>

</searchresult>
