<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<searchresult>
<query>Global</query>
<document id="1">
<title>Longitudinal analysis of personal networks. The case of Argentinean migrants in Spain</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2009.05.001</url>
<snippet>This paper discusses and illustrates various approaches for the longitudinal analysis of personal networks (multilevel analysis, regression analysis, and SIENA). We combined the different types of analyses in a study of the changing personal networks of immigrants. Data were obtained from 25 Argentineans in Spain, who were interviewed twice in a 2-year interval. Qualitative interviews were used to estimate the amount of measurement error and to isolate important predictors. Quantitative analyses showed that the persistence of ties was explained by tie strength, network density, and alters Country of origin and residence. Furthermore, transitivity appeared to be an important tendency, both for acquiring new contacts and for the relationships among alters. At the network level, immigrants networks were remarkably stable in composition and structure despite the high turnover. Clustered graphs have been used to illustrate the results. The results are discussed in light of adaptation to the host society. (C) 2009 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000274948700009
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="2">
<title>A note on actor network utilities and network evolution</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2007.07.006</url>
<snippet>The corrections provided by Xie and Cui [Xie, F., Cui, W., in press. Cost range and network structures. Social Networks, 30] to one of the theorems provided by Doreian [Doreian, P., 2006. Actor network utilities and network evolution. Social Networks, 28, 137-164] are both necessary and helpful. Accepting these corrections, and linking them more closely to the work of Hummon [Hummon, N.P., 2000. Utility and dynamic social networks. Social Networks, 22, 221-249], leads to some additional suggestions which, together with a restatement of some earlier results, help set the foundations for future work in this area. (C) 2007 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000253735700010
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="3">
<title>Introduction to the special issue on network dynamics</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2009.12.002</url>
<snippet>
WOS:000274948700001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="4">
<title>Correlations among centrality indices and a class of uniquely ranked graphs</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2017.03.010</url>
<snippet>Various centrality indices have been proposed to capture different aspects of structural importance but relations among them are largely unexplained. The most common strategy appears to be the pairwise comparison of centrality indices via correlation. While correlation between centralities is often read as an inherent property of the indices, we argue that it is confounded by network structure in a systematic way. In fact, correlations may be even more indicative of network structure than of relationships between indices. This has substantial implications for the interpretation of centrality effects as it implies that competing explanations embodied in different indices cannot be separated from each other if the network structure is close to a certain generalization of star graphs. (C) 2017 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000403527900006
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="5">
<title>Diversity in social support by role relations: A typology</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2005.10.001</url>
<snippet>Social support is fundamental for social integration and emotional well-being. One aspect of social support that is often the focus of attention is the size of a persons support network. However, additional complex measures of social support are necessary to capture qualitative aspects of support networks, such as the diversity in types of support available from specific types of alters. This paper presents a simple way to acquire this comprehensive information and a condensed way to represent the complexity of a persons support network so this information can easily be included in classic survey analyses. Log-linear latent class analysis is used to construct a typology of ego-centric support networks showing the types of support respondents can expect from alters with a specific role. Depending on the role relation for the five support items, this diversity can adequately be represented by distinguishing 2-4 types of respondents. For the role relation friends, we can differentiate between respondents who expect only companionship from their friends, those expecting emotional support as well as companionship, and respondents expecting no social support at all from their friends. For immediate kin, we find those with only emotional support, those with emotional and instrumental support, those with all types of support, and finally a group of respondents expecting no support at all from immediate kin. The approach presented in this article enables a more detailed measurement of the dimensions of social support contents by managing to compile the diversity by distinguishing types of respondents. Such typologies can easily be used as explanatory variables in subsequent analyses. 
WOS:000240890700008
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="6">
<title>Introduction to stochastic actor-based models for network dynamics</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2009.02.004</url>
<snippet>Stochastic actor-based models are models for network dynamics that can represent a wide variety of influences on network change, and allow to estimate parameters expressing such influences, and test corresponding hypotheses. The nodes in the network represent social actors, and the collection of ties represents a social relation. The assumptions posit that the network evolves as a stochastic process driven by the actors, i.e., the model lends itself especially for representing theories about how actors change their outgoing ties. The probabilities of tie changes are in part endogenously determined, i.e., as a function of the current network structure itself, and in part exogenously, as a function of characteristics of the nodes (actor covariates) and of characteristics of pairs of nodes (dyadic covariates). In an extended form, stochastic actor-based models can be used to analyze longitudinal data on social networks jointly with changing attributes of the actors: dynamics of networks and behavior. This paper gives an introduction to stochastic actor-based models for dynamics of directed networks, using only a minimum of mathematics. The focus is on understanding the basic principles of the model, understanding the results, and on sensible rules for Model selection. Crown Copyright (C) 2009 Published by Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000274948700005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="7">
<title>Cluster analysis of multiplex networks: Defining composite network measures</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2017.01.002</url>
<snippet>Social relations are multiplex by nature: actors in a group are tied together by various types of relationships. To understand and explain group processes it is, therefore, important to study multiple social networks simultaneously in a given group. However, with multiplexity the complexity of data also increases. Although some multivariate network methods (e.g. Exponential Random Graph Models, Stochastic Actor-oriented Models) allow to jointly analyze multiple networks, modeling becomes complicated when it focuses on more than a few (2-4) network dimensions. In such cases, dimension reduction methods are called for to obtain a manageable set of variables. Drawing on existing statistical methods and measures, we propose a procedure to reduce the dimensions of multiplex network data measured in multiple groups. We achieve this by clustering the networks using their pairwise similarities, and constructing composite network measures as combinations of the networks in each resulting cluster. The procedure is demonstrated on a dataset of 21 interpersonal network dimensions in 18 Hungarian high-school classrooms. The results indicate that the network items organize into three well-interpretable clusters: positive, negative, and social role attributions. We show that the composite networks defined on these three relationship groups overlap but do not fully coincide with the network measures most often used in adolescent research, such as friendship and dislike. (C) 2017 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000395601700008
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="8">
<title>Actor-based analysis of peer influence in &lt;i&gt;A Stop Smoking In Schools Trial&lt;/i&gt; (ASSIST)</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2010.07.001</url>
<snippet>As shown by the success of network intervention studies that exploit the occurrence of peer influence in their target group, the reliable assessment of peer influence processes can be important for informing public health policy and practice. A recently developed tool for assessing peer influence in longitudinal social network data is stochastic actor-based modeling. The body of the literature in which this method is applied is growing, but how reliable are the results? In this paper, we identify two shortcomings in this literature: the questionable assumption of temporal homogeneity, and the potential dependence of results on the inclusion of nuisance parameters in the model specification. These issues are resolved by analyzing the data of three schools selected from ASSIST, a large UK-based trial of a school-based smoking prevention intervention. Results show that the co-evolution of friendship and smoking is a time heterogeneous process, and that results are sensitive to specification details. However, the peer influence parameter is not affected by either, but emerges as surprisingly stable over time and robust to model variation. This establishes confidence in the method and encourages detailed future investigations of peer influence in ASSIST. (C) 2010 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000305495600007
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="9">
<title>Network formation in organizational settings: Exploring the importance of local social processes and team-level contextual variables in small groups using bayesian hierarchical ERGMs</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2022.07.001</url>
<snippet>Statistical models for social networks, such as exponential random graphs (ERGMs), have increasingly been used by organizational scholars to study the social interactions inside organizations, departments, and teams. While such models have been successful in providing insights about the local processes that underlie these interactions (such as homophily, reciprocity or transitivity), an additional interesting avenue for research focuses on the role of group -level contextual variables (such as the climate or composition of a team or organization) when considering a multitude of teams or organizations. In this paper we show how, in a team context, integrating team -level factors in a multilevel framework (i.e., a Bayesian hierarchical ERGM) enables us to answer questions about: 1) how team -level contextual factors might provide alternative explanations for the emergence of intra-team ties, and 2) whether any variation in local tendencies between teams might be dependent on such team -level variables (i.e., cross -level interactions). Using data collected among 103 MBA students who were grouped into 18 teams of 5-7 members to work on a project, we study the impact of members expertise and perceived psychological safety on advice seeking behavior. At a local level, we focus on the effect of these nodal attributes for homophily and differences in advice seeking and giving, while at the team level we incorporate the average expertise and the teams psychological safety climate. Our results show that expert members are more likely to be the recipient of advice ties, but also that this effect is more pronounced in teams where the overall level of expertise is high. For psychological safety, we find that a high psychological safety climate impacts the advice relations among all members in the group, not solely those who themselves perceive a high level of psychological safety, suggesting that the team climate has an impact on all its members. This illustrates how a Bayesian hierarchical ERGM allows us to obtain relevant results even when studying small -sized groups.
WOS:001188361400001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="10">
<title>Negative ties and signed graphs research: Stimulating research on dissociative forces in social networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2019.09.004</url>
<snippet>
WOS:000501619700001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="11">
<title>"It must be me" or "It could be them?": The impact of the social network position of bullies and victims on victims' adjustment</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2010.07.002</url>
<snippet>It was examined in this study whether the association between victimization and psychological adjustment (depression and self-esteem) is moderated by the classroom network position of bullies and victims. Multivariate multilevel regression analysis was used on a large sample representative of grades three to five in Finland (N=7192 children from 376 classrooms). Consistent with the person-group (dis)similarity model and attributional mechanisms, it was found that victims were better adjusted in classrooms when others shared their plight and when they could attribute the blame to bullies. The results indicate that victimization consequences might be partly generated by person-environment interactions. (C) 2010 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000313304100002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="12">
<title>Exploratory social network analysis with Pajek</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2005.12.002</url>
<snippet>
WOS:000238117100005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="13">
<title>The co-evolution of gossip and friendship in workplace social networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2012.07.002</url>
<snippet>This study investigates the co-evolution of friendship and gossip in organizations. Two contradicting perspectives are tested. The social capital perspective predicts that friendship causes gossip between employees, defined as informal evaluative talking about absent colleagues. The evolutionary perspective reverses this causality claiming that gossiping facilitates friendship. The data comprises of three observations of a complete organizational network, allowing longitudinal social network analyses. Gossip and friendship are modeled as both explanatory and outcome networks with RSiena. Results support the evolutionary perspective in that gossip between two individuals increases the likelihood of their future friendship formation. However, individuals with disproportionately high gossip activity have fewer friends in the network, suggesting that the use of gossiping to attract friends has a limit. (C) 2012 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000313304100025
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="14">
<title>The way bullying works: How new ties facilitate the mutual reinforcement of status and bullying in elementary schools</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2018.12.006</url>
<snippet>This study addresses the puzzle how high-status bullies in elementary school are able to maintain high status among their classmates despite bullying (some of) them. The dynamic interplay between bullying and status was studied, focusing on how relational bullying affects the creation, dissolution, and maintenance of status attributions, and vice versa. Longitudinal round-robin peer nomination data were obtained from 82 school classes in 15 Dutch elementary schools (2055 students; 50&#37; boys) followed over three yearly measurements, starting out in grades 2-5 when students were aged 8-11. An age-dependent effect of bullying on the creation of new status attributions was found. Whereas the youngest group punished bullying by a refusal to attribute status to the bully, this turned into a reward of bullying in the oldest groups. Unexpectedly, high-status bullies seemed to avoid continual bullying of the same victims, pointing to explanations of why their status can persist.
WOS:000501619700007
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="15">
<title>Social network engineering and race in a police academy: A longitudinal analysis</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2009.08.001</url>
<snippet>This research examined an attempt to facilitate racial integration by populating squads (i.e., workgroups) in a police academy with mixes of recruits that reflected the racial demographics of the larger cohort. This was part of the social infrastructure of the academy. Additionally, a fixed seating arrangement was considered as a second element of academy infrastructure capable of impacting racial integration. We examined the consequences of these academy components over time with regard to race by combining ethnographic accounts With social network data collected throughout the academy and using a variety of network analytic tools. These consequences with regard to race were examined as a part of social network evolution. The academys social arrangements did accelerate the creation of social knowledge of recruits about each other and the formation of friendship ties both within and between races. However. our results point to cleat limitations to such infrastructural engineering and have implications for both recruitment to police academies and dealing with race. They shed light also oil processes of homophily and group composition over time and have implications for Studying social networks. (C) 2009 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000274948700004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="16">
<title>A real-coded genetic algorithm for two-mode &lt;i&gt;KL&lt;/i&gt;-means partitioning with application to homogeneity blockmodeling</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2014.11.007</url>
<snippet>The two-mode KL-means partitioning (TMKLMP) problem has a number of important applications in the social and physical sciences. For example, the intra-block variability measure associated with TMKLMP underscores its direct relevance to two-mode homogeneity blockmodeling of binary and real-valued social networks. We present a real-coded genetic algorithm for obtaining TMKLMP solutions. A simulation study showed that the new algorithm compares favorably to a multistart implementation of a two-mode KL-means heuristic, which is recognized as a top-performing method for TMKLMP. The merit of the proposed method is demonstrated via an application to the blockmodeling of social network data associated with signing of environmental advertisements in the New York Times as a part of the Turning Point Project. (C) 2014 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000351979100003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="17">
<title>Unpacking Burt's constraint measure</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.02.001</url>
<snippet>Burt (1992) proposed two principal measures of structural holes, effective size and constraint. However, the formulas describing the measures are somewhat opaque and have led to a certain amount of confusion. Borgatti (1997) showed that, for binary data, the effective size formula could be written very simply as degree (ego network size) minus average degree of alters within the ego network. The present paper presents an analogous reformulation of the constraint measure. We also derive minima and maxima for constraint, showing that, for small ego networks, constraint can be larger than one, and for larger ego networks, constraint cannot get as large as one. We also show that for networks with more than seven alters, the maximum constraint does not occur in a maximally dense or closed network, but rather in a relatively sparse "shadow ego network", which is a network that contains an alter (the shadow ego) that is connected to every other alter, and where no other alter-alter ties exist.
WOS:000527272000006
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="18">
<title>Measuring knowledge and experience in two mode temporal networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2018.05.003</url>
<snippet>Two mode social network data consisting of actors attending events is a common type of social network data. For these kinds of data it is also common to have additional information about the timing or sequence of the events. We call data of this type two-mode temporal data. We explore the idea that actors attending events gain information from the event in two ways. Firstly the event itself may provide information or training; secondly, as co-attendees interact, they may pass on skills or information they have gleaned from other events. We propose a method of measuring these gains and demonstrate its usefulness using the classic Southern Women Data and a covert network dataset. (C) 2018 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000444666300007
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="19">
<title>Social context, spatial structure and social network structure</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2010.09.002</url>
<snippet>Frequently, social networks are studied in their own right with analyses devoid of contextual details. Yet contextual features - both social and spatial - can have impacts on the networks formed within them. This idea is explored with five empirical networks representing different contexts and the use of distinct modeling strategies. These strategies include network visualizations, QAP regression, exponential random graph models, blockmodeling and a combination of blockmodels with exponential random graph models within a single framework. We start with two empirical examples of networks inside organizations. The familiar Bank Wiring Room data show that the social organization (social context) and spatial arrangement of the room help account for the social relations formed there. The second example comes from a police academy where two designed arrangements, one social and one spatial, powerfully determine the relational social structures formed by recruits. The next example is an inter-organizational network that emerged as part of a response to a natural disaster where features of the improvised context helped account for the relations that formed between organizations participating in the search and rescue mission. We then consider an anthropological example of signed relations among sub-tribes in the New Guinea highlands where the physical geography is fixed. This is followed by a trading network off the Dalmatian coast where geography and physical conditions matter. Through these examples, we show that context matters by shaping the structure of networks that form and that a variety of network analytic tools can be mobilized to reveal how networks are shaped, in part, by social and spatial contexts. Implications for studying social networks are suggested. (C) 2010 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000300131600004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="20">
<title>Missing data in cross-sectional networks - An extensive comparison of missing data treatment methods</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.02.004</url>
<snippet>This paper compares several missing data treatment methods for missing network data on a diverse set of simulated networks under several missing data mechanisms. We focus the comparison on three different outcomes: descriptive statistics, link reconstruction, and model parameters. The results indicate that the often used methods (analysis of available cases and null-tie imputation) lead to considerable bias on descriptive statistics with moderate or large proportions of missing data. Multiple imputation using sophisticated imputation models based on exponential random graph models (ERGMs) lead to acceptable biases in descriptive statistics and model parameters even under large amounts of missing data. For link reconstruction multiple imputation by simple ERGM performed well on small data sets, while missing data was more accurately imputed in larger data sets with multiple imputation by complex Bayesian ERGMs (BERGMs).
WOS:000527272000011
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="21">
<title>Network-building behavioral tendencies, range, and promotion speed</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2014.03.006</url>
<snippet>We studied 459 Ukrainian civil servants to determine how career network-building behavioral tendencies relate to network range and promotion speed. We identify two main behavioral tendencies for initiating social relationships: (a) networking within formal structured groups organized around activities created specifically to encourage members to form personal bonds (structured foci) and (b) individually driven networking outside these structured foci. The study shows that individually driven networking is related to broader network range, while structured foci networking has an inverted-U relationship to network range. The optimal networking for range involves a moderate level of structural foci networking and high levels of individually driven networking. Broad network range is related to faster promotion speed to higher organizational levels. Extroverts have a tendency toward individually driven networking, while high Machiavellians have a tendency toward both individually driven and structured foci networking. (C) 2014 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000340338600007
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="22">
<title>Introduction to the special issue on advances in two-mode social networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2013.03.002</url>
<snippet>
WOS:000320479500001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="23">
<title>An exact algorithm for a core/periphery bipartitioning problem</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2010.08.002</url>
<snippet>The discrete optimization problem associated with partitioning a set of actors into core and periphery subsets has typically been approached using approximate procedures such as exchange heuristics, genetic algorithms, and simulated annealing. Although these procedures are effective and scalable for large networks, they do not guarantee an optimal bipartition. In this paper, an exact algorithm is presented for a core/periphery bipartitioning problem. Unlike the approximate procedures in the extant literature, this new algorithm, which is based on the principles of branch-and-bound programming, affords a guarantee of an optimal bipartition. Computational results for empirical and simulated data sets reveal that the proposed algorithm is extremely efficient for networks with 40 or fewer actors, and is often scalable for networks with up to 60 actors. (C) 2010 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000291962000002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="24">
<title>Similarity in friendship networks: Selection or influence? The effect of constraining contexts and non-visible individual attributes</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2009.06.003</url>
<snippet>Most research on similarity in friendship networks focuses oil clearly visible individual attributes (i.e. attitudes and behaviors) in contexts where choices whom to befriend are relatively unconstrained. These studies often reveal that social selection rather than social influence is the dominant cause of similarity among friends. We argue that in a setting where social collaboration is crucial and friendship choices are more constrained, influence might be the main reason for similarity found among friends. In addition, we examined whether social categorization and peer control amplifies the social influence process among friends. Using a stochastic actor-based model for network dynamics, we analyzed a three-wave dataset of first year Royal Netherlands Naval College officer students oil friendship formation and military discipline. The data Supports our first hypothesis that students adjust their own military discipline to that of their friends. Contrary to our expectations, we did not find Support for the idea that individuals adjust their discipline more to friends who are of the same military specialty, and neither more to friends who exert peer control. We elaborate oil these findings in the discussion. (C) 2009 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000274948700008
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="25">
<title>A multiple indicator approach to blockmodeling signed networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2008.03.005</url>
<snippet>Regardless of whether the focus is on algebraic structures, elaborating role structures or the simple delineation of concrete social structures, generalized blockmodeling faces a pair of vulnerabilities. One is sensitivity to poor quality of the relational data and the other is a risk of over fitting blockmodels to the details of specific networks. Over fitting blockmodels can lead to multiple equally well fitting partitions where choices cannot be made between them on a principled basis. This paper presents a method of tackling these problems by viewing (when possible) observed social relations as multiple indicators of an underlying affect dimension. Quadratic assignment methods using matching coefficients, product moment correlations and Goodman and Kruskals gamma are used to assess the appropriateness of using the sum of observed relations as input for applying generalized blockmodeling. Data for four groups are used to show the value of this approach Within which multiple equally well fitting blockmodels for single relations are replaced by unique (or near-unique) partitions of the summed data. This strategy is located also within a broader problem of blockmodeling three-dimensional networks data and suggestions are made for future work. 
WOS:000257568200007
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="26">
<title>A graph-theoretic perspective on centrality</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2005.11.005</url>
<snippet>
WOS:000240890700012
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="27">
<title>Who are the objects of positive and negative gossip at work? A social network perspective on workplace gossip</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2011.11.003</url>
<snippet>Gossip is informal talking about colleagues. Taking a social network perspective, we argue that group boundaries and social status in the informal workplace network determine who the objects of positive and negative gossip are. Gossip networks were collected among 36 employees in a public child care organization, and analyzed using exponential random graph modeling (ERGM). As hypothesized, both positive and negative gossip focuses on colleagues from the own gossipers work group. Negative gossip is relatively targeted, with the objects being specific individuals, particularly those low in informal status. Positive gossip, in contrast, is spread more evenly throughout the network. (C) 2011 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000302394600005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="28">
<title>Geodesic based centrality: Unifying the local and the global</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2016.09.005</url>
<snippet>A variety of node-level centrality measures, including purely structural measures (such as degree and closeness centrality) and measures incorporating characteristics of actors (such as the Blaus measure of heterogeneity) have been developed to measure a persons access to resources held by others. Each of these node-level measures can be placed on a continuum depending on whether they focus only on egos direct contacts (e.g. degree centrality and Blaus measure of heterogeneity), or whether they also incorporate connections to others at longer distances in the network (e.g. closeness centrality or betweenness centrality). In this paper we propose generalized measures, where a tuning parameter 8 regulates the relative impact of resources held by more close versus more distant others. We first show how, when a specific 8 is chosen degree-centrality and reciprocal closeness centrality are two specific instances of this more general measure. We then demonstrate how a similar approach can be applied to node-level measures that incorporate attributes. When more or less weight is given to other nodes at longer distances with specific characteristics, a generalized measure of resource-richness and a generalized measure for diversity among ones connections can be obtained (following Blaus measure of heterogeneity). Finally, we show how this approach can also be applied to betweenness centrality to focus on more local (ego) betweenness or global (Freeman) betweenness. The importance of the choice of 8 is illustrated on some classic network datasets. (C) 2016 Published by Elsevier B.V.
WOS:000395601700002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="29">
<title>Networks containing negative ties</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2014.03.005</url>
<snippet>Social network analysts have often collected data on negative relations such as dislike, avoidance, and conflict. Most often, the ties are analyzed in such a way that the fact that they are negative is of no consequence. For example, they have often been used in blockmodeling analyses where many different kinds of ties are used together and all ties are treated the same, regardless of meaning. However, sometimes we may wish to apply other network analysis concepts, such as centrality or cohesive subgroups. The question arises whether all extant techniques are applicable to negative tie data. In this paper, we consider in a systematic way which standard techniques are applicable to negative ties and what changes in interpretation have to be made because of the nature of the ties. We also introduce some new techniques specifically designed for negative ties. Finally we show how one of these techniques for centrality can be extended to networks with both positive and negative ties to give a new centrality measure (PN centrality) that is applicable to directed valued data with both positive and negative ties. Crown Copyright (C) 2014 Published by Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000337015400010
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="30">
<title>Collecting survey-based social network information in work organizations</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.04.003</url>
<snippet>Collecting social network data among organization members using surveys is challenging and requires a well considered strategy. Based on extensive past experience with collecting social network information in work organizations with surveys, we identify and discuss four major elements of the data collection process, all linked with and dependent on the specific research question and objective: 1) negotiating access to the organization; 2) identifying the networks boundary, the relevant formal organizational structures that affect social networks, and the sampling approach; 3) deciding how to approach research subjects and collect network data; and, 4) providing useful and ethically-sensitive feedback to the organization and its members. Decisions on each of these elements and their co-alignment, particularly with respect to the chosen research question, is crucial to a successful study. We offer guidelines and provide examples for each of these elements.
WOS:000700623500003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="31">
<title>Networks and public health: A review of network epidemiology: A handbook for survey design and data collection</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2006.07.002</url>
<snippet>
WOS:000244397100013
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="32">
<title>Maintaining the duality of closeness and betweenness centrality</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2015.08.003</url>
<snippet>Betweenness centrality is generally regarded as a measure of others dependence on a given node, and therefore as a measure of potential control. Closeness centrality is usually interpreted either as a measure of access efficiency or of independence from potential control by intermediaries. Betweenness and closeness are commonly assumed to be related for two reasons: first, because of their conceptual duality with respect to dependency, and second, because both are defined in terms of shortest paths. We show that the first of these ideas - the duality - is not only true in a general conceptual sense but also in precise mathematical terms. This becomes apparent when the two indices are expressed in terms of a shared dyadic dependency relation. We also show that the second idea - the shortest paths - is false because it is not preserved when the indices are generalized using the standard definition of shortest paths in valued graphs. This unveils that closeness-as-independence is in fact different from closenessas-efficiency, and we propose a variant notion of distance that maintains the duality of closeness-as-independence with betweenness also on valued relations. (C) 2015 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000367423900014
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="33">
<title>Non-response in social networks: The impact of different non-response treatments on the stability of blockmodels</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2012.02.002</url>
<snippet>Discerning the essential structure of social networks is a major task. Yet, social network data usually contain different types of errors, including missing data that can wreak havoc during data analyses. Blockmodeling is one technique for delineating network structure. While we know little about its vulnerability to missing data problems, it is reasonable to expect that it is vulnerable given its positional nature. We focus on actor non-response and treatments for this. We examine their impacts on blockmodeling results using simulated and real networks. A set of known networks are used, errors due to actor non-response are introduced and are then treated in different ways. Blockmodels are fitted to these treated networks and compared to those for the known networks. The outcome indicators are the correspondence of both position memberships and identified blockmodel structures. Both the amount and type of non-response, and considered treatments, have an impact on delineated blockmodel structures. 
WOS:000313304100008
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="34">
<title>Introduction to the special issue on Network Dynamics (Part 2)</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2012.05.001</url>
<snippet>
WOS:000305495600001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="35">
<title>Prismatic effects of negative ties</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2019.07.004</url>
<snippet>Research on negative ties has focused primarily on the harm they do. In this paper, we show that negative ties can also have beneficial effects. We argue that, like positive ties, negative ties can link actors together in the minds of observers. As a result, we theorize that negative ties with high-status actors can benefit a focal actor, whereas negative ties with low-status actors can harm the focal actor. This prismatic effect depends on the existing status of the focal actor: a focal actor of low status is likely to benefit far more from negative ties with high-status actors and suffer more from negative ties with low-status actors than will an actor of high-status. To test our ideas, we analyze the phenomenon of "diss songs" in hip-hop music. A diss song is a song in which a rapper makes derogatory comments about another rapper, constituting a negative tie. We analyze the effects of negative ties among 53 rappers over 20 points in time on audience reaction as measured by record sales. We find that negative ties with high-status actors enhance future sales for low-status actors. However, negative ties with lower-status actors have no effect on the future sales of both low- and high-status actors. Just as some researchers have reported both positive and negative consequences of social capital, our study demonstrates that negative ties can also have both positive and negative outcomes.
WOS:000501619700003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="36">
<title>Doing Social Network Research</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2015.04.007</url>
<snippet>
WOS:000358626400017
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="37">
<title>Categorical attribute based centrality: &lt;i&gt;E&lt;/i&gt;-&lt;i&gt;I&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;G&lt;/i&gt;-&lt;i&gt;F&lt;/i&gt; centrality</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2012.06.002</url>
<snippet>In a paper examining informal networks and organizational crisis, Krackhardt and Stern (1988) proposed a measure assessing the extent to which relations in a network were internal to a group as opposed to external. They called their measure the E-I index. The measure is now in wide use and is implemented in standard network packages such as UCINET (Borgatti et al., 2002). The measure is based on a partition-based degree centrality measure and as such can be extended to other centrality measures and group level data. We explore extensions to closeness, betweenness and eigenvector centrality, and show how to apply the technique to sets of subgroups that do not form a partition. In addition, the extension to betweenness suggests a linkage to the Gould and Fernandez brokerage measures, which we explore. (C) 2012 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000313304100020
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="38">
<title>On variants of shortest-path betweenness centrality and their generic computation</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2007.11.001</url>
<snippet>Betweenness centrality based on shortest paths is a standard measure of control utilized in numerous studies and implemented in all relevant software tools for network analysis. In this paper, a number of variants are reviewed, placed into context, and shown to be computable with simple variants of the algorithm commonly used for the standard case. (C) 2008 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000255583700003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="39">
<title>Where do intra-organizational advice relations come from? The role of informal status and social capital in social exchange</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2011.04.002</url>
<snippet>Social status and social capital frameworks are used to derive competing hypotheses about the emergence and structure of advice relations in organizations. Although both approaches build on a social exchange framework, they differ in their behavioral micro-foundations. From a status perspective, advice giving is a means to generate prestige, whereas asking advice decreases ones relative standing. At a structural level these motivations are expected to result in an overrepresentation of non-reciprocal dyads and non-cyclical triadic structures in the advice network, as well as in active advice seekers being unlikely to be approached for advice, especially by active advice givers. From a social capital perspective, advice seeking creates obligations for the advice seeker. At the structural level, this results in an overrepresentation of reciprocal dyads and cyclical triads, and active advice seekers to be unpopular as targets of advice seeking, especially for active advice givers. Analyses of four waves of a longitudinal sociometric study of 57 employees of a Dutch Housing Corporation provide partial support for both approaches. In line with the social capital perspective, we find reciprocal advice relations to be overrepresented at the dyad level. Results at the triad level support the social status arguments, according to which high status individuals will avoid asking advice from low status individuals. The implications for macro-structural properties of intra-organizational advice network are discussed. (C) 2011 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000305495600005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="40">
<title>Visualization methods for longitudinal social networks and stochastic actor-oriented modeling</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2011.06.002</url>
<snippet>As a consequence of the rising interest in longitudinal social networks and their analysis, there is also an increasing demand for tools to visualize them. We argue that similar adaptations of state-of-the-art graph-drawing methods can be used to visualize both, longitudinal networks and predictions of stochastic actor-oriented models (SAOMs), the most prominent approach for analyzing such networks. The proposed methods are illustrated on a longitudinal network of acquaintanceship among university freshmen. (C) 2011 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000305495600002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="41">
<title>Individuals' power and their social network accuracy: A situated cognition perspective</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2018.01.006</url>
<snippet>Individuals differ in how accurately they perceive their social environment, but research and theory provide conflicting predictions on whether powerful people are more or less accurate than others. Drawing on social network theory and the situated cognition theory of power, we examine the relationship between individuals formal and informal power and their perceptual accuracy of social network relationships. We propose that individuals perceptual accuracy is related to: 1) their formal and informal power in the organization; 2) the type of relationship being perceived (positive/negative valence) and its relevance to task and goal completion; and 3) the dependence relationship with the target of perception (i.e., whether the perceiver is dependent on the perceived to get their work done). Predictions were tested using cognitive social structure data collected from a technical call center. Results showed that power was generally linked to increased perceptual accuracy, particularly for the types of relationships most relevant for task and goal completion. We further demonstrated that social network accuracy was related to employees outcomes, including subsequent transfer, promotion, and exit from the organization. (C) 2018 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000432768600013
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="42">
<title>Modeling non-linear effects with neural networks in Relational Event Models</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2024.05.004</url>
<snippet>Dynamic networks offer an insight of how relational systems evolve. However, modeling these networks efficiently remains a challenge, primarily due to computational constraints, especially as the number of observed events grows. This paper addresses this issue by introducing the Deep Relational Event Additive Model (DREAM) as a solution to the computational challenges presented by modeling non-linear effects in Relational Event Models (REMs). DREAM relies on Neural Additive Models to model non-linear effects, allowing each effect to be captured by an independent neural network. By strategically trading computational complexity for improved memory management and leveraging the computational capabilities of graphic processor units (GPUs), DREAM efficiently captures complex non-linear relationships within data. This approach demonstrates the capability of DREAM in modeling dynamic networks and scaling to larger networks. Comparisons with traditional REM approaches showcase DREAM superior computational efficiency. The model potential is further demonstrated by an examination of the patent citation network, which contains nearly 8 million nodes and 100 million events.
WOS:001251593100001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="43">
<title>Networks and public health: A review of network epidemiology: A handbook for survey design and data collection" (vol 29, pg 154, 2007)</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2007.03.001</url>
<snippet>
WOS:000248429500008
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="44">
<title>Analysis of two-mode network data using nonnegative matrix factorization</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2011.05.001</url>
<snippet>Nonnegative matrix factorization has been offered as a fast and effective method for analyzing nonnegative two-mode proximity data. The goal is to structurally represent a nonnegative proximity matrix as the product of two lower-dimensional nonnegative matrices. Goodness of fit is typically measured as the sum of the squared deviations between the observed matrix elements and the estimated elements yielded by the product of the matrix factors. The preservation of nonnegativity of the factors has been touted as a major practical advantage over comparable decomposition methods (e.g., principal component analysis, singular-value decomposition, spectral analysis) because of its propensity for a more coherent additive interpretation. We provide descriptions of the nonnegative matrix factorization model and a rescaled gradient descent algorithm for estimating the factors. A small numerical example is provided along with application to three network matrices from the empirical literature. (C) 2011 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000294520200003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="45">
<title>Induced, endogenous and exogenous centrality</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2010.06.004</url>
<snippet>Centrality measures are based upon the structural position an actor has within the network. Induced centrality, sometimes called vitality measures, take graph invariants as an overall measure and derive vertex level measures by deleting individual nodes or edges and examining the overall change. By taking the sum of standard centrality measures as the graph invariant we can obtain measures which examine how much centrality an individual node contributes to the centrality of the other nodes in the network, we call this exogenous centrality. We look at exogenous measures of degree, closeness and betweenness. (C) 2010 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000283402000008
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="46">
<title>Partitioning signed social networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2008.08.001</url>
<snippet>Structural balance theory has proven useful for delineating the blockmodel structure of signed social networks. Even so, most of the observed signed networks are not perfectly balanced. One possibility for this is that in examining the dynamics underlying the generation of signed social networks. insufficient attention has been given to other processes and features of signed networks. These include: actors who have positive ties to pairs of actors linked by a negative relation or who belong to two Mutually hostile Subgroups; some actors that are viewed positively across the network despite the presence of negative ties and subsets of actors with negative ties towards each other. We suggest that instead viewing these situations as violations of structural balance, they can be seen as belonging to other relevant processes we call mediation, differential popularity and internal Subgroup hostility. Formalizing these ideas leads to the relaxed structural balance blockmodel as a proper generalization of structural balance blockmodels. Some formal properties concerning the relation between these two models are presented along with the properties of the fitting method proposed for the new blockmodel type. The new method is applied to four empirical data sets where improved fits with more nuanced interpretations are obtained. 
WOS:000262547600001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="47">
<title>Stochastic actor oriented model with random effects</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2024.01.002</url>
<snippet>The stochastic actor oriented model (SAOM) is a method for modelling social interactions and social behaviour over time. It can be used to model drivers of dynamic interactions using both exogenous covariates and endogenous network configurations, but also the co -evolution of behaviour and social interactions. In its standard implementations, it assumes that all individual have the same interaction evaluation function. This lack of heterogeneity is one of its limitations. The aim of this paper is to extend the inference framework for the SAOM to include random effects, so that the heterogeneity of individuals can be modelled more accurately. We decompose the linear evaluation function that models the probability of forming or removing a tie from the network, in a homogeneous fixed part and a random, individual -specific part. We extend the algorithm so that the variance of the random parameters can be estimated with method of moments. Our method is applicable for the general random effect formulations. We illustrate the method with a random out -degree model and show the parameter estimation of the random components, significance tests and model evaluation. We apply the method to the Kapferers Tailor shop study. It is shown that a random out -degree constitutes a serious alternative to including transitivity and higher -order dependency effects.
WOS:001172463300001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="48">
<title>Does proximity matter? Distance dependence of adolescent friendships</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2011.01.002</url>
<snippet>Geographic proximity is a determinant factor of friendship. Friendship datasets that include detailed geographic information are scarce, and when this information is available, the dependence of friendship on distance is often modelled by pre-specified parametric functions or derived from theory without further empirical assessment. This paper aims to give a detailed representation of the association between distance and the likelihood of friendship existence and friendship dynamics, and how this is modified by a few basic social and individual factors. The data employed is a three-wave network of 336 adolescents living in a small Swedish town, for whom information has been collected on their household locations. The analysis is a three-step process that combines (1) nonparametric logistic regressions to unravel the overall functional form of the dependence of friendship on distance, without assuming it has a particular strength or shape; (2) parametric logistic regressions to construct suitable transformations of distance that can be employed in (3) stochastic models for longitudinal network data, to assess how distance, individual covariates, and network structure shape adolescent friendship dynamics. It was found that the log-odds of friendship existence and friendship dynamics decrease smoothly with the logarithm of distance. For adolescents in different schools the dependence is linear, and stronger than for adolescents in the same school. Living nearby accounts, in this dataset, for an aspect of friendship dynamics that is not explicitly modelled by network structure or by individual covariates. In particular, the estimated distance effect is not correlated with reciprocity or transitivity effects. (C) 2011 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000300131600003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="49">
<title>Univariate and multivariate models of positive and negative networks: Liking, disliking, and bully-victim relationships</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2012.08.001</url>
<snippet>Three relations between elementary school children were investigated: networks of general dislike and bullying were related to networks of general like. These were modeled using multivariate cross-sectional (statistical) network models. Exponential random graph models for a sample of 18 classrooms, numbering 393 students, were summarized using meta-analyses. Results showed (balanced) network structures with positive ties between those who were structurally equivalent in the negative network. Moreover, essential structural parameters for the univariate network structure of positive (general like) and negative (general dislike and bullying) tie networks were identified. Different structures emerged in positive and negative networks. The results provide a starting point for further theoretical and (multiplex) empirical research about negative ties and their interplay with positive ties. 
WOS:000313304100027
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="50">
<title>Exponential random graph models and pendant-triangle statistics</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2024.07.002</url>
<snippet>The paper builds on the framework proposed by Pattison and Snijders (2012) for specifying exponential random graph models (ERGMs) for social networks. We briefly review the two-dimensional hierarchy of potential dependence structures for network tie variables that they outlined and provide proofs of the relationships among the model forms and of the nature of their sufficient statistics, noting that models in the hierarchy have the potential to reflect the outcome of processes of cohesion, closure, boundary and bridge formation and path creation over short or longer network distances. We then focus on the so-called partial inclusion dependence assumptions among network tie variables and the pendant-triangle, or paw, statistics to which they give rise, and illustrate their application in an empirical setting. We argue that the partial inclusion assumption leads to models that can reflect processes of boundary and bridge formation and that the model hierarchy provides a broad and useful framework for the statistical analysis of network data. We demonstrate in the chosen setting that pendant- triangle (or paw) effects, in particular, lead to a marked improvement in goodness-of-fit and hence add a potentially valuable capacity for modelling social networks.
WOS:001290324200001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="51">
<title>A second look at Krackhardt's graph theoretical dimensions of informal organizations</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2011.10.006</url>
<snippet>Krackhardt (1994) proposed four dimensions to describe and measure the amount of hierarchy in networks of informal organizations. We examine these conditions, suggest some relaxations and prove that they are both necessary and sufficient to guarantee an arborescence (or out-tree). In addition we suggest situations some of which are outside of informal organizations in which fewer of the conditions can be used to capture the hierarchical tree structure. (C) 2011 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000302394600001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="52">
<title>Moral bureaucracies and social network research</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2019.11.001</url>
<snippet>In the wake of Europes General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR), research ethics governance does not just affect the ethical dimensions of social research but also the range of scientific decisions available to researchers. Because of the sensitive status of personal data and the aversion to even minimal risk by what we call "moral bureaucracies", we are concerned that social network researchers will increasingly limit their research decisions to "safe" options, like reusing anonymized datasets, choosing target populations based on convenience rather than theoretical relevance, and routinely subcontracting fieldwork to professional data collection companies, among others. We also suggest that scientific associations and social scientists in general need to adopt a proactive role in preserving both scientific freedom and genuine ethics advice within this new regulatory framework.
WOS:000685648800003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="53">
<title>Power in politically charged networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2013.04.007</url>
<snippet>We offer a theory and measure for determining powerful nodal positions based on potential inter-actor control in "politically charged" networks, which contain both allies and adversaries. Power is derived from actors that are dependent on the focal actor and sociometrically weak, either due to a lack of alternative allies or from being threatened by others. We create a new Political Independence Index (PII), compare it to other established measures, and illustrate its use in the setting of an international network of alliances and military conflicts from 1946 to 2000. Results show that politically independent nations as measured by PII have smaller increases in military personnel than others over time. (C) 2013 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000328803800013
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="54">
<title>Actor non-response in valued social networks: The impact of different non-response treatments on the stability of blockmodels</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2016.06.001</url>
<snippet>Social network data usually contain different types of errors. One of them is missing data due to actor non response. This can seriously jeopardize the results of analyses if not appropriately treated. The impact of missing data may be more severe in valued networks where not only the presence of a tie is recorded, but also its magnitude or strength. Blockmodeling is a technique for delineating network structure. We focus on an indirect approach suitable for valued networks. Little is known about the sensitivity of valued networks to different types of measurement errors. As it is reasonable to expect that blockmodeling, with its positional outcomes, could be vulnerable to the presence of non-respondents, such errors require treatment. We examine the impacts of seven actor non-response treatments on the positions obtained when indirect blockmodeling is used. The start point for our simulation are networks whose structure is known. Three structures were considered: cohesive subgroups, core-periphery, and hierarchy. The results show that the number of non-respondents, the type of underlying blockmodel structure, and the employed treatment all have an impact on the determined partitions of actors in complex ways. Recommendations for best practices are provided. (C) 2016 The Authors. Published by Elsevier B.V.
WOS:000389730200005
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="55">
<title>Popularity breeds contempt: The evolution of reputational dislike relations and friendships in high school</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2016.07.006</url>
<snippet>In this study, we examined the dynamics of the perception of "dislike" ties (reputational dislike) among adolescents within the contexts of friendship, perceived popularity, substance use, and Facebook use. Survey data were collected from a longitudinal sample of 238 adolescents from the 11th and 12th grades in one California high school. We estimated stochastic actor-based network dynamic models, using reports of reputational dislike, friendships, and perceived popularity, to identify factors associated with the maintenance and generation reputational dislike ties. The results showed that high-status adolescents and more frequent Facebook users tended to become perceived as or stay disliked by their peers over time. There was a tendency for friendships to promote the creation and maintenance of reputational disliking but not vice versa. Adolescents tended to perceive others as disliked when their friends also perceived them as disliked. There was no evidence that either cigarette smoking or drinking alcohol affected reputational dislike dynamics. This study highlights the important role that the hierarchical peer system, online peer context, and friendships play in driving information diffusion of negative peer relations among adolescents. (C) 2016 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000389730200008
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="56">
<title>Creating the thin blue line: Social network evolution within a police academy</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2017.03.011</url>
<snippet>Whenever major schisms between police and communities come to public attention, there are always passionate calls for an increased emphasis on - and improvement of - police training. This rhetoric is so common that police leaders joke that there is no societal problem so big that it cant be fixed by better police training. Still, professional socialization in law enforcement remains an important topic with a great deal of resources being devoted to developing initiatives and augmenting existing curricula. This training comes in many forms including learning the nuts and bolts of many legal processes and acquiring the practical skills for law enforcement. However, beyond this, there is a socialization process with multiple facets including the development of solidarity and trust among a cohort of recruits. We attempt to understand the basic mechanisms of network creation in police academies as the foundation of the socialization processes within them. By focusing on these network mechanisms underlying the establishment of the Thin Blue Line, we offer an understanding of the underlying social processes foundational for the transmission of police culture. In short, we think the recruit network structure functions as a vehicle for cultural transmission within police academies. (C) 2017 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000403527900009
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="57">
<title>Node centrality in weighted networks: Generalizing degree and shortest paths</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2010.03.006</url>
<snippet>Ties often have a strength naturally associated with them that differentiate them from each other. Tie strength has been operationalized as weights. A few network measures have been proposed for weighted networks, including three common measures of node centrality: degree, closeness, and betweenness. However, these generalizations have solely focused on tie weights, and not on the number of ties, which was the central component of the original measures. This paper proposes generalizations that combine both these aspects. We illustrate the benefits of this approach by applying one of them to Freemans EIES dataset. (C) 2010 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
WOS:000279409000009
</snippet>
</document>

</searchresult>
