<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<searchresult>
<query>Global</query>
<document id="1">
<title>A concluding comment: Toward a critical social network analysis</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.12.004</url>
<snippet>The authors of articles in this special issue on "Ethics in SNA" contribute to enriching the continuing discussion of major ethical dilemmas that social network analysts need to confront. These articles encourage us to replace silence with thoughtful consideration and innovative paths forward. I highlight three themes that emerged in my own reading of these contributions: moving beyond "ethics versus science," deepening reflexivity, and possible approaches toward a critical SNA.
WOS:000685648800010
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="2">
<title>Networks are a lens for power: A commentary on the recent advances in the ethics of social networks special issue</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.12.003</url>
<snippet>
WOS:000685648800002
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="3">
<title>Order of recall and meaning of closeness in collecting affective network data</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.12.006</url>
<snippet>The paper investigates how study participants handle the so-called "hierarchical mapping technique", an affective name generator developed by Antonucci (1986), which is accompanied by a diagram enabling respondents to compare alters with regard to different degrees of closeness. By applying the thinking-aloud method, we identified three patterns in the order of recalling alters: closeness as overarching schema (with either role relationships or relationship properties as subordinate schema), roles and foci as overarching schema, and a fraying schema. In addition, we investigated how study participants understand and interpret "closeness". The meanings of closeness can refer to various relationship properties, cultural framing, and relationship dynamics. Results show that specific meanings of closeness are related to different recall patterns. Furthermore, recall patterns vary according to the socio-economic status of the participants. Finally, implications for the construction of name generators and data collection are discussed.
WOS:000614282000011
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="4">
<title>Collecting large personal networks in a representative sample of Dutch women</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.07.012</url>
<snippet>In this study we report on our experiences with collecting large personal network data (25 alters) from a representative sample of Dutch women. We made use of GENSI, a recently developed tool for network data collection using interactive visual elements that has been shown to reduce respondent burden. A sample of 758 women between the ages of 18 and 40 were recruited through the LISS-panel; a longitudinal online survey of Dutch people. Respondents were asked to name exactly 25 alters, answer sixteen questions about these alters (name interpreter questions), and assess all 300 alter-alter relations. Nearly all (97&#37;) respondents reported on 25 alters. Non-response was minimal: 92&#37; of respondents had no missing values, and an additional 5&#37; had fewer than 10&#37; missing values. Listing 25 alters took 3.5 +/- 2.2 (mean +/- SD) minutes, and reporting on the ties between these alters took 3.6 +/- 1.3 min. Answering all alter questions took longest with a time of 15.2 +/- 5.3 min. The majority of respondents thought the questions were clear and easy to answer, and most enjoyed filling in the survey. Collecting large personal networks can mean a significant burden to respondents, but through the use of visual elements in the survey, it is clear that it can be done within reasonable time, with enjoyment and without much non-response.
WOS:000591504600006
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="5">
<title>Whose results are these anyway? Reciprocity and the ethics of "giving back" after social network research</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2019.10.003</url>
<snippet>Bridging the social networks, field methods and ethics literatures, I make the case that the process of reporting research findings is an ethical issue, and recommend elevating it in the research design. I draw on a reflective account of three research experiences with settings in, respectively, online health communities, economic or-ganizations, and the mainstream media. I proceed in steps, discussing release of personal network results to individual participants, of whole network results to the researched community, and finally of general results to wider audiences, under a unifying idea that a reciprocity obligation underlies the reporting process. I claim that communication should follow an iterative rather than a linear approach to reach all relevant stakeholders, thereby mitigating the vulnerabilities that arise from research.
WOS:000685648800009
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="6">
<title>Social network analysis: New ethical approaches through collective reflexivity. Introduction to the special issue of Social Networks</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.12.001</url>
<snippet>Research in social network analysis (SNA) faces unprecedented ethical challenges today due to both technological developments ('big' data) and a growing tendency toward institutionalization of ethics governance. We argue that a suitable response requires a more comprehensive approach to SNA ethics, and we identify two main paths toward this goal. First, we need to recognize the breadth of the subject, no longer limited to anonymity and consent. Second, we need to encourage the active participation and contribution of SNA scholars. We advocate a need for greater reflexivity at both individual and collective levels, whereby researchers can learn from their own and their peers' experiences, and foster a more ethically 'virtuous' approach within the whole SNA community.
WOS:000685648800001
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="7">
<title>The presentation of the networked self: Ethics and epistemology in social network analysis</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2019.06.002</url>
<snippet>Drawing on the seminal work of Goffman, Krackhardt and others, this paper argues that there is a crucial step in between participants perceptions and the collection and visualisation of data - i.e. what we call the presentation of the networked self. We employ examples from our own empirical work in the UK to argue that the presentation of the networked self requires researchers to adopt a highly reflexive approach. Framing our analysis within the context of contemporary society - including the impact of social media on a networking mindset - we explore the range of ethical dilemmas which can emerge during a research encounter.
WOS:000685648800004
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="8">
<title>Exploratory social-spatial network analysis of global migration structure</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.09.007</url>
<snippet>At the global level, international migration can be considered as a network of migration exchanges between different countries. Employing an exploratory network analysis of the international migration structure, the present paper examines the structural characteristics of this network and the status of the countries. The analysis is done using the socio-spatial approach. Results show that as the severity of network ties grow, the number of ties reduce significantly and ties are asymmetric. Most of the migrations in the international migration structure have also taken place outside the near and neighboring countries. The network analysis showed two migration patterns of "International Migratory Highways" and "Migratory Clusters". In the first migration pattern, migra-tions are largely asymmetric and towards the major centers of immigration, while in the second one, migrations are mostly symmetric and within specific geographical areas.
WOS:000591504700006
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="9">
<title>Moral bureaucracies and social network research</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2019.11.001</url>
<snippet>In the wake of Europes General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR), research ethics governance does not just affect the ethical dimensions of social research but also the range of scientific decisions available to researchers. Because of the sensitive status of personal data and the aversion to even minimal risk by what we call "moral bureaucracies", we are concerned that social network researchers will increasingly limit their research decisions to "safe" options, like reusing anonymized datasets, choosing target populations based on convenience rather than theoretical relevance, and routinely subcontracting fieldwork to professional data collection companies, among others. We also suggest that scientific associations and social scientists in general need to adopt a proactive role in preserving both scientific freedom and genuine ethics advice within this new regulatory framework.
WOS:000685648800003
</snippet>
</document>

<document id="10">
<title>Ethical implications of network data in business and management settings</title>
<url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2020.09.001</url>
<snippet>Reflecting on the compilation and analysis of a range of network datasets drawn from our own work and some prominent examples, we consider the ethical challenges in dealing with network data in business and management settings. We argue that the managerial processes that characterize such settings introduce particular ethical sensitivities in the stages of commissioning and research design, and when collecting, analyzing and reporting network data. These sensitivities arise from the imperatives of business, motivations for commissioning network analyses and the legal authority that managers have over employees. We argue that ethical considerations are much more pervasive in business and management network research than in many other fields. In this contribution, we present a range of ethical challenges in network research in business and management settings that arise at several stages of the research process. For each issue identified, we describe the ethical problem and propose mitigation remedies. From this reflection, we suggest guidelines for other researchers to consider when designing research projects in this application area.
WOS:000685648800005
</snippet>
</document>

</searchresult>
